Acknowledgement

I have been longing to write this letter of thanks ever since I started meeting people for the purpose of writing this book.

At the forefront of my thoughts is Dr. R.S. Praveen Kumar, IPS, Secretary, TSWREIS for sharing the dominant perspective behind Poorna’s success. I immensely thank him for describing every detail related to the expedition that has left me inspired for life.

My thanks to Poorna’s coaches Mr. Sekhar Babu and Mr. Parmesh Singh, for bringing alive the everyday events that constituted the expedition and for putting up with my queries constantly. I thank Mr. Anand Kumar, Poorna’s partner in this journey, who walked me through the expedition with his narration and for sharing his keen observations of Poorna and her sparkling spirit.

During my interviews with the aforementioned, every person got in touch with their self, allowed me the honour of looking into them for a brief while. While each of them owned a deep philosophy sprouting from extreme agony, they always respected the thought of existence and life. The perspective of every person touched a chord in me and left me with tears of happiness. I am extremely grateful to them for such an ecstatic experience that I would treasure forever.

I thank Jyothi aka Mr. Roshan Ghatraj, Course Director, HMI and Wing Commander Sridharan for sharing their experiences with the Swaeroes at HMI and Ladakh respectively.

I thank Mr. Pranesh Siravara and Mr. Ravindranath, of Prism Books Pvt. Ltd., for their trust and conviction in me to write this book.

I thank Ms. Shubha Srikanth, the incredible editor who quietly altered and alarmed me in equal measure. She shares the accomplishment of the book as much as I do.

I thank Mr. Chandrahaas, Retired Chief Commissioner, Income Tax, for pitching in at the right time to enhance the content of this book.

I thank Ms. Sathyavathi Kondaveeti, Chief functionary, Bhoomika and Ms. Mrunalini Chunduru, Retired Professor, Telugu University for recommending me to Prism Books Pvt. Ltd.,

My thanks are due to Dr. P.S.R. Sharma, Dr. Venkat Raju, Mr. Shaik Mannan, Mrs. Lakshmi Bai, Swapna, employees of TSWREIS for providing the facts and photographs.

I thank my friends, Padmaja, Sireesha, Charita and my helpers Swathi, Zakiya and Swarna who supported me in their own ways to complete this book.

I am in awe of Poorna and her family, Poorna for her humility, kindness grit and tenacity, and her parents for respecting Poorna’s choices. Thanking them would never be enough. I admire their simple and beautiful souls.

Finally, much love to my partner Krishna Mohan, for his support and excitement, and Dhruv, my special kid who this time took a turn and tolerated my tantrums.

This book defines all the people who championed the cause called ‘Poorna’ and I am grateful to be a part of it.

Aparna Thota

Foreword

It was August 2014.

The new state of Telangana was just born. The wounds of decades long struggle haven’t yet started healing and the borders between two states seem very artificial and surreal. Amidst all this I happened to visit Markapur town in Prakasam district of Andhra Pradesh. On the way, I couldn’t resist the temptation to visit a Social Welfare Residential School for Girls in Vijayapuri South, next to the mighty Nagarjuna Sagar dam.

I was there quite early that morning, and the school was busy preparing for assembly. Ms. Padmaja, one of the committed school leaders of social welfare system, insisted that I should address the school assembly. As I approached the gathering reluctantly, I could see the joy in the eyes of the children when they saw their former Secretary in their school, which is a rare event. Without wasting time, I posed a straight question to the gathering: ‘How many of you want to scale Mount Everest?’ I have no idea why I asked that question, but it was involuntary. Perhaps, everyone assembled there looked like Poorna.

Lo and behold, all six hundred hands went up in the air. This was a dream come true spectacle in a schooling system which has been emblematic of neglect, mistrust, and helplessness. None of the students knew the dangers of high altitude mountaineering. Strange as it may seem, it was the same kids and their parents who had to be goaded to sign up for rock climbing camps, leave alone mountaineering. Everywhere, we were greeted with thumbs down when we broached the topic of mountaineering during pre-Poorna days. But some events change the course of history.

Poorna and Anand’s audacious assault on centuries old inferiority triggered this tsunami of confidence in the young minds, leading to many unimaginable happenings in welfare schools which were on ventilator support. That was also when it struck me that Poorna’s story must reach not just the nooks and corners of India, but of the world. Her story must become a beacon of hope for the millions of marginalised children across the world. Co-incidentally, Prism Books Pvt. Ltd., approached me with a proposal to publish a book on Poorna’s life and achievements. I could not have found a better channel to take Poorna to the world. I agreed instantly. Prism assigned the task to Ms. Aparna Thota. When Aparna met me to capture this transformative power of Poorna, for a moment, she looked equally dogged and stubborn, like Poorna.

I consider myself to be a lucky witness to this silent but steady revolution happening in the minds of the marginalised in this part of India. Since the author of this book, Aparna brilliantly takes all of us through the arduous execution of Operation Everest from tiny hamlets in the jungles of Nizamabad in the south of Vindhyas to the mighty peaks of upper Himalayas, I want to focus on why we planned this chilling expedition, putting our reputation on the block.

In the history of social welfare in this country, the policy makers hardly attempted to capture the imagination of their voiceless brethern. I can say this emphatically as I am a product of such a welfare system. Most of the welfare schemes in this country have been, by and large, mere palliative programs that fail to address the crux of the problem. Operation Everest is one such effort not only to remove mental barriers, but also to unlock the infinite potential of the oppressed in the world.

Poverty alleviation programs have largely been based on a top down model – ‘I know what is good for you and you will have to follow this to get out of poverty’. This approach worked to a great extent and gave some relief to the poor. But this could not create the critical mass of leaders or idols from the communities who could lead the change on their own. Even if it was done, it was half hearted and the so called idols created were recklessly stereotyped, stigmatised, and allowed to fade away. The Twitter post on English language of Hima Das, the girl from Assam who clinched gold medal in International Athletic Meet in 2018 is a sad reflection of the stigma toward these underserved sections. Poorna and Anand and many others are no exception to this trend.

In Social Welfare in Telugu states, the policy makers and legendary bureaucrats like S.R. Sankaran, P.S. Krishnan, Madhava Rao, K. Raju clearly wanted to come out of this indefinite pessimism from day one. Operation Everest is one such step in that direction. We wanted the communities that produce such wonder kids to celebrate every moment of glory, however trivial it may be.

Telugu governments realised very early that providing mere reservations to the oppressed sections in the government sector in a globalised era, is not enough. In fact, they went beyond and started preparing their children for entry into those niche sectors from which the poor have been historically excluded. I thank the governments profusely for helping us play a role in this endeavour. But it wasn’t easy.

I am working in the Social Welfare Department by choice. I am the first cop to head this department in our state, which is usually headed by the officers of Indian Administrative Service. Since it was not common, a few well meaning bureaucrats convinced the Chief Ministers of the day to give me a chance. I thank both the Chief Ministers for their generosity and bold vision. Since I had to learn everything from scratch, I focused more on field trips rather than file pushing. My rendezvous with reality was a shocking experience. Many children realised for the first time, that there is a Secretary who is supposed to take care of their needs. There was a huge trust deficit among parents and teachers. Around half of the teachers whom I met, had never seen the head of their department. With the average tenure of previous secretaries being 6 to 8 months, it is not very difficult to imagine what kind of foundations one could have laid for the future of the poor children.

But I was determined to reverse this in the precious two year tenure given to me. Since I had no time, I wanted to do things differently with greater speed. I scrambled everyday for that turning point. Thanks to Mr. Raymond Peter, our the then Principal Secretary, I happened to meet Sekhar Babu, the unassuming mountaineer and this encounter changed the trajectory of all our lives forever. The phenomenal transformation in our lives post Poorna’s summit has been described in a granular detail by the author in this book.

Aparna painstakingly captured the adventure behind the adventure. She patiently collected first hand accounts of everyone who was instrumental in this operation including those who coached our children in the Himalayan Mountaineering Institute located in Darjeeling, West Bengal. This is an expedition of another kind for this debutant author who tried her best to encapsulate what her protagonist had to do to prove the Swaero’s first Commandment: I am not inferior to anyone.

As I described earlier, Poorna’s expedition was launched not to break records, but to break the mental barriers of the poor in their journey towards liberation. This expedition filled the hearts of many kind hearted, but gritty bureaucrats and students with so much confidence that after this feat, many students from interior forests of neighbouring states made it to the summit of Everest. This expedition triggered such a powerful chain reaction that this year in Telangana, around 150 students cruised their way to prestigious medical colleges and 530 students qualifying JEE Mains to join prestigious colleges of technology in this country. This has never happened in 35 years of our existence!

This book must be read by parents and children and the policy makers who want to tap the innate human potential. Poorna’s adventure changed my life. It injected me with tons of fresh energy and confidence. Telangana Government gave me extraordinary stability in this assignment. Even Poorna’s life underwent tremendous change. She continues to challenge the highest peaks in all the continents to tell us, with the same humility, that there is no limit to human potential, whether you are born rich or poor. All that one needs is just an opportunity.

Such opportunities again knocked the gates of social welfare school in Vijayapuri South in 2017. This time it was Sandhya Bai, a 12th grader from the same school (the school I described in the beginning) and daughter of farm labourers, who grabbed the opportunity to set her foot on the peak of Mount Everest. Poorna’s achievement inspired this girl and she was one among those six hundred children who said yes to Everest in 2014. Government of Andhra Pradesh and my counterpart in Andhra Pradesh, Col. Ramulu made this possible. And now it is your turn to grab the next opportunity.

May Mother Nature be with you in every step on the way to your various Summits.

Dr. R.S. Praveen Kumar, IPS.
Secretary, TSWREIS, Hyderabad.

11 July 2019

Publisher’s Note

It is with great pleasure and pride that we present ‘POORNA’ to the world. We are very excited and happy to creatively portray Poorna’s meteoric rise from Pakala to Mouth Everest. Poorna’s is an inspiring story of grit and determination; a narrative of perseverance, endurance and patience. Her feat is a result of her single-minded focus.

Ms. Aparna Thota has done a commendable job in visualizing the entire journey of Poorna, recording with immense dedication, every travail and triumph. We appreciate the time and effort that she has invested in painstakingly interviewing all the people who were involved in Poorna’s journey to give us a comprehensive account of her achievement. Aparna has indeed made the book engaging and fascinating.

Shubha Srikanth, a seasoned editor, took the book to greater heights, by giving it coherence and lucidity with her editorial and creative skills.

Poorna’s life is an inspiration for the younger generation that in today’s world is deprived of genuine role models and heroes. We strongly believe that this book will motivate adults and youngsters alike, to aspire for rich experiences that bring long-lasting joy, while adding valuable dimensions to their personality.

This book would not have been possible without the wholehearted support and encouragement of Dr. R.S. Praveen Kumar, IPS, who not only instantly agreed to our proposal to bring out Poorna’s accomplishment, but also guided us from start to end. We are grateful to him. We thank TSWREIS for providing us with high-resolution photographs of the various phases of Poorna’s training and ascent.

Prism is thankful to all those who have helped in different ways in the making of this book.

Enjoy reading and experience the sheer immensity of the Himalayas and the remarkable triumph of this young girl, Poorna Malavath.

Happy Reading.

Pranesh Siravara

About the Author

Aparna Thota is a postgraduate in Social Work, a writer and a poet, Urban lifestyles, struggles of marginalized people and the nuances of everyday life find expression in her works. Through her characters, she sifts through the layers of human emotions and the driving forces within and around. In her stories, she unconditionally supports women and their choices to grow beyond the boundaries prescribed for them.

Poorna is her first biographical work as a novelist. She has embraced the story of Poorna as her own. This book is an expression of her love to all those girls who refuse to compromise on what they are offered and relentlessly fight their way through oppression and discrimination:

‘Every success story of a person is an inspiration and a hope for the rest of society. Poorna might not have been aware of her place in the social hierarchy when she started her humble journey from a remote hamlet. Her conquest of Mount Everest, is a gigantic leap in the history of silenced sections of our country.’

Poorna has compelled us to pause and record this historic event and Aparna Thota has succeeded in capturing the journey beautifully.

Prologue

Sagarmatha!

Here, I am, on top of the world.

The universe cheers for me. The sky bejewelled with stars is my gorgeous crown. Take me into your arms, for I have come all the way only to meet you. Mother, hug me and kiss me.

My glory will remain embedded in your bosom forever like a fossil.

Like a mother who proudly shows her newborn for all to see, uphold me to show me to your brothers and sisters. Tell them, Mother, how adorable I am! Proclaim to the world that this girl is your precious offspring. This girl born to an almost forgotten tribe down South, amidst the sweltering heat of the plateau, travelled all the way, climbed dangerous mountains, crossed corpses, to meet her mother, her epitome of strength!

I have come all the way for you, my Mother.

I have come Mother, to be cradled by you.

I am humbled Mother, in the knowledge that earth and mankind are but an invisible, insignificant, dispensable speck in the larger scheme of the eternal universe. We are ephemeral; the universe is permanent.

Hail Swaeroes! Look, the sky is NOT our limit. Love is in the air. Grit is our strength; energy is our determination, and endurance, our forgivingness. There is fire in you; stoke it; keep it raging.

Keep climbing. Hold on to the rope of hope. Wear gears of esteem. Work out to acclimatize, create your own sphere for our destination is our goal.

Sagarmatha, here I go. To send my brothers and sisters who are left behind in primeval times to commence their own voyage toward new horizons, a voyage for progress and dignity.

A voyage like my own.

When I can, you can, all of us can!!

Poorna Malavath

Gorgeous But Treacherous

18 April 2014
6.45 am
The Mount Everest

It is not a normal day. Although it appears like one.

The sun rose in the East; the winds caressed with the usual tenderness.

On such a not-so-normal day, the rays of the Sun kissed the mountains of the Himalayan range, one after another: the highest peak, the Summit point of the Everest (8,850 meters), second highest, the Karakoram or K2 (8,611 meters), the third highest Kanchenjunga (8,586 meters) the fourth, Lhotse (8,516 meters) and all the other peaks scattered around the Everest, shimmered gloriously. One after another. As if set to a brilliant, invisible algorithm!

Mount Everest, upon glimpsing the Sun, blushed; transformed from the dull, drab grey of the limestone, and donned a mantle of splendid gold. Encouraged, the Sun generously sprinkled its golden dust on all the hundreds of mountains, one by one, each with its own characteristic height, gradient and affability. The mountains then cast off their gilded crests offered by the Sun to don their silver crests. The daily saga had just begun.

However, the mystic routine of the mountains did not end in this splendid course of nature. Nature chose otherwise.

The cosmic rhythm was to be wrecked. An infinitesimal crack on the mighty Himalayas was all it took.

The large unstable blocks of ice softened and loosened during day and hardened and tightened during the nights. It all started with a micro movement in the western shoulder of the Everest.

Micro inch by micro inch, the crack travelled on the surface as if an invisible dagger had carved it out. It travelled at monstrous speed, sketching a menacing fissure on the vast mountain canvas. A massive Serac of 34.5 meters on the western shoulder ripped off the mountain.

The 113 feet thick Serac weighing 14.3 million kilograms, quietly separated itself from Mount Everest, like a slice of orange gently pulled out of the fruit. The last connect broken, it accelerated at lightning speed, sliding down with irrepressible energy, devouring everything on its way.

An Avalanche on a seemingly ordinary day!

The avalanche descended rapidly to hit right below Camp 1 (5,800 meters), passed through the Khumbu icefall, speeding, dropping, sliding and maneuvering its way amidst the tresses of the mountain, diverting and changing tracks. Every element on the mountain surrenders to the avalanche. What choice does it have in the face of elemental fury?

The millions of tons of rapidly sliding ice came to a standstill in a few seconds.

Was it tired? Or was it content?

Content, perhaps for it had devoured twenty-five human lives.

Every mountain will one day collapse. A mountain is in the making for thousands and thousands of centuries. Large parts of the earth move and collide with land forms to form Fold Mountains. The mountain randomly sheds a minute piece of itself, a display of its incredible malevolent power!

To remind man of his fallibility! Of his transience!

Everest is mystic but dangerous!

Gorgeous but treacherous!

Everest, the assassin!

Everest, the God of all mountains.

Mount Everest, the highest eight-thousander!

The Flitting Butterfly

30 August 2013
4.30 pm
Social Welfare Residential School, Tadwai

It’s almost evening, but the sun is still bright and blinding. Girls with tightly plaited hair, tied with red ribbons and dressed in checked shirts and maroon skirts are standing under the luxurious canopy of a huge tree in the volleyball court of their school playground. They are looking up, craning their necks and searching for something among the overhanging branches.

‘There she is!’ someone yelled, pointing at a small figure that appeared momentarily amidst the broad-leaved branches.

‘Poornaaa,’ one of them shouted.

An instant later, the girls got a clear glimpse of Poorna on the sunshade of their classroom, next to the tree. She was gliding up toward the parapet wall with the help of the ventilator sill. No, she did not hoist herself to the terrace. Instead, with one hand on the parapet wall, she pushed herself back to catch hold of a sturdy tree branch and stretched out her other hand, to reach the ball on a leaved branch. As she took a swing, with her left hand, she tapped the ball from above. The ball lazily jostled against the leaves and fell to the ground with a soft thud. Poorna’s legs were still on the ventilator sill. With one hand clutching the parapet wall, she carefully landed on the sunshade and leapt toward another sturdy branch. She crawled down and jumped from the trunk. She dusted her skirt and picked up the ball, swirled it precariously perched on her forefinger and headed toward the volleyball court, a big smile lighting up her face.

The girls took their positions on the court. Poorna stepped into the service zone. Her upper body bent slightly forward, she held the ball in her outstretched left hand, tossed it into the air and hit it with great force toward the other court. Another teammate jumped high and spiked the ball with precision into a gap.

‘GOAL!!’ the girls shouted.

Swapna blew the whistle and marked a point.

This was not the first time that Poorna gained a point or retrieved the ball during a match. A swift, high throw often landed the ball on tree branches or on terraces of the school buildings. Poorna would be the only one to recover the ball, no matter where the ball landed. Even before Swapna realised, Poorna would climb a tree effortlessly and leap from branch to branch; hoist herself from window sill to window bar; or scurry up rainwater and drainage pipes. She would create access where none existed. Swapna enjoyed watching her dark, lean structure climb, leap and slide down with ease. Today, as she watched Poorna play, she knew who she would recommend for the mountaineering course. That morning she had received an email circular from the Secretary of Social Welfare Residential Schools asking her to recommend two students for a rock-climbing camp.

Swapna and Poorna joined the Government Social Welfare Residential School of Tadwai three years ago. It was Swapna’s first job after completing the Bachelor of Physical Education (B.P.Ed course). Swapna found Poorna, who joined the sixth grade, receptive, responsible and highly energetic. She was also good at sports. They developed a warm bond. Swapna often sought Poorna’s assistance, especially during matches and tournaments.

Poorna was an outstanding volleyball player and had steered the school team to win several zonal matches. Poorna’s power and agility on the court, her precision in aiming the ball at a weak opponent or a gap had Swapna proudly declare to the headmistress, ‘Madam, give me Poorna and two other players. We’ll win any volleyball tournament!’

The next day Swapna sent word to Poorna asking her to meet her at the sports inventory room.

‘Poorna, I’ve got this email from the Secretary of Social Welfare Residential Schools asking me to select two students for a rock-climbing camp. Ravali from Intermediate First Year has agreed to go. We need one from Ninth standard. Do you want to go?’ She said, raising her eyebrow.

‘Rock climbing? What’s that?’ Poorna asked, taking the ball from the almirah.

‘It is a sport Poorna. You will be taught how to climb steep rocks with ropes and other equipment.’

Without a second thought, Poorna said, ‘I’ll go. I am used to climbing the hills around my village.’

‘Sure? But the camp is scheduled during holidays.’

‘Holidays? Oh no, please, Madam! I want to go home. Plan it earlier. Please?’

‘No, silly. I am not the one who decides. The Secretary does. Besides, the camp is at Bhongir. About a hundred students from different schools will participate in the camp. This is a rare opportunity Poorna. I want you to go!’

‘How long is the camp?’

‘Five days – 30th September to 4th October. So, tell me. Shall I recommend your name for the camp?’

‘Yes, madam.’ Poorna twirled the ball on her forefinger. ‘Now, how about this?’ she pointed to the ball.

‘Let’s start marking at 3 o’ clock.’ Swapna took the ball from Poorna’s hands. ‘You may now go back to class.’

Poorna pulled a long face and ran out.

Swapna locked the sports room and headed toward the principal’s office.

‘Did she agree?’ Dhanalakshmi, the principal asked.

‘Yes, madam.’

‘And the inter first-year girl, Ravali?’

‘She is willing too.’

Ravali was a State-level wrestling champion in the Under-Seventeen Category.

‘Are you sure of these two girls?’

‘Yes, Madam.’

Swapna beamed with pride. Ravali and Poorna had evolved into fine sports-persons under her tutelage.

She called Mannan, the Sports Officer.

‘Sir, we’ll send two students. I’ll mail their details by noon. Alright, Sir,’ she said as she scribbled in her diary – ‘Medical Fitness Certificate and Non-Judicial Agreement’. ‘I’ll arrange for these, Sir. I’ll upload the scanned copies while submitting the form online.’

She made the next call to Poorna’s father, Devidas.

Mountaineering sounds interesting. Wish they had planned the camp during school days. Thought Poorna. She would really miss going home.

Poorna’s father, who had visited her the previous week, had mentioned that during the upcoming Dussehra vacation, her uncle would stay with them longer than usual. For a moment, she regretted her decision to attend the camp. She loved her uncle’s children! The younger was born just three years ago when she had joined the school at Tadwai. Besides, she missed her parents and was eager to go home.

The thought of her parents brought to her mind images of them working relentlessly, all day long. Her father, Devidas, riding his bicycle to and fro from Pakala to Kondapur, to attend to routine electrical repair work; busy in the farm, culling out weeds; or, at other times, fixing a chair or the navvar (cot made by weaving long strip of thick cloth on an wooden frame) in the front yard of the house. Poorna clung to her father whenever she was home for the holidays. She enjoyed helping him in whatever he did and learned by observing him. Before Poorna joined the school at Tadwai, her whole family would go to the nearby forest to collect ippa poolu (Mahuva flowers) and beedi aakulu (tobacco leaves). A set of hundred beedi aakulu fetched them no more than a rupee, and they made ippa saara (hooch liquor) with ippa poolu.

Devidas hailed from the Banjara community. His ancestors had migrated from Rajasthan and had somehow created a niche at Pakala, more a hamlet than a village, in Kamareddy district. When the joint family split, Devidas was left with just one acre of land. When he realized he couldn’t make both ends meet if he depended on this meager piece of land, he decided to learn a new skill that could be another source of income. He knew that there was a great demand for electricians. The farmers of the neighbouring hamlets called for an electrician when the bore-well engine fused out, and that happened very often because of constant power fluctuations. Devidas decided to learn to be an electrician. On days when the farm did not require his labour, he cycled to Kondapur, a small town near Pakala, to learn what it takes to be an electrician.

The residents of Pakala had another option: to go to the Gulf countries. However, Devidas was sure he would not want to do that. He knew of friends and relatives who, through brokers, had struggled to clinch a job in the Gulf. Once there, they didn’t mind doing any odd job, be it scavenging or construction labour. The women ended up as housemaids or nannies. The early days after the son of the household migrated seemed hopeful to the family. They exulted over small gifts, sent through a friend or relative, that usually included clothes, electric trimmers, soaps and perfumes and not to mention the customary dates. The first visit back home for him was only after five years. This grand visit would sink the family into a financial crisis because of needs that were waiting to be met and the obligation to bring gifts. The wife became pregnant again; the mother’s long-pending surgery couldn’t be put off anymore; a brother wanted to start a business; a sister had to be married off and so on. The family would now owe more to the money lender than ever before. And so, he journeys back to the foreign land, to work harder.

Devidas found this whole saga meaningless. He would often tell his wife, ‘I’ll never send my children to a foreign land. The Gulf – a mirage! Succeed or fail they may, but here, in this land.’

Despite their poverty, Devidas and Lakshmi were determined to educate their children and dreamt of a better future for them. Devidas not only dreamt but planned and worked toward making his dream come true. He invested in educating his children. He encouraged them to study. He knew that education and employment were the only means to prevent them from being sucked into the throes of poverty.

An acre of land and a cycle were the family’s only inherited properties. They did not even have a house of their own after the joint family split. Devidas and Lakshmi worked relentlessly and built a hut to sleep and an extended thatch for a functioning kitchen.

Poorna did not remember precisely when, but the desire for education had embedded itself deeply in her mind. One hot summer night, when all of them sat outside their hut gazing at the clear star-lit sky, Poorna had asked her parents if they had ever studied in a school. No, said her father. Two of Devidas’s younger brothers were the only ones who had gone to school. They were the first generation who had had some formal education. Poorna’s mother was sent to school, with a penku (a clay tava, that doubled as a slate) and chalk. She was often beaten by her teacher, and so she hated school. On her way back home, she would break the penku, hoping her parents would not send her to school. But, she would promptly be given a new one the same evening. She went back each day and broke the penku with a vengeance. After some days, her wish was fulfilled. She was stopped from going to school and was asked to graze cattle.

Poorna and her brother Naresh, loved to listen to their mother’s school misadventure story. They would laugh till their tummies hurt. Then, Lakshmi would gently, lovingly take Poorna’s and Naresh’s hands into hers, and whisper, ‘Never, be like us. Let this poverty end with us. You must study and get government jobs. Your children’s hands must be soft and clean, and their heels, always smooth. You must never live under a leaky roof hoping and praying that it survives the monsoon. You should always have enough to eat and share.’ Tears trickled down Lakshmi’s cheeks as she said these words.

Poorna admired her mother immensely. Lakshmi spent her time mostly between the kitchen and the farm. Poorna had never heard her mother complain or whine. She had learned to make the most of what was available and ran the house efficiently. She made ambli (porridge) out of jonna (jowar) or ragi (millet) when there was no rice at home. She was a lever, smoothly supporting her husband’s dreams for a better future.

After a hard day’s labour, watching his daughter skip, hop and jump around was a treat for Devidas. He loved her every antic and every tantrum. He would hoist her on his shoulders and run around the house. The house would be filled with their laughter. Lakshmi felt blessed at such times. As Poorna grew, Devidas admired her even more. Poorna was a wild butterfly, flitting here and there. Devidas never controlled her. He wanted her to deal with life, as it came, independently. Poorna was sent to a nearby Anganwadi centre. She would escape from the centre and run to her mother working in the fields. She was then admitted to the local primary school, a furlong away from her house. She enjoyed going to school. Devidas saw a sprightly, curious child in Poorna.

One day, she found her big brother, Naresh riding her father’s cycle – the one that Devidas had inherited from his father. This old bicycle was his only mode of transport to neighbouring villages. Poorna watched her brother struggle to cycle. After two days of effort, he finally learned to balance and peddle. She wanted to give it a try. Ten-year-old Naresh refused to part with the cycle. She tried negotiating by tempting him with toffees. He pushed her away. Not one to give up easily, she started beating him. Naresh relented. He knew she wouldn’t budge until she got what she wanted.

Within no time, Poorna learnt to cycle. She wasn’t tall enough to sit on the seat and peddle. She put one leg through the V-shaped gap below the cycle bar to reach the pedal and roamed around the whole village. Every time she was losing balance, she would loudly chant, ‘Jai Hanuman! Jai Hanuman!’. She believed that she always grew stronger after chanting Jai Hanuman. She visited the Hanuman temple next to her house every day. Hanuman, the lord of strength, helped her overcome all her fears.

‘Tu padgi tho…? (What if you fall?)’ Naresh asked, genuinely concerned.

‘Ma jaavu tho…? (What if I don’t?)’

She peddled away toward her friend’s house on the other side of the village.

Poorna was adamant about one thing. She loved challenging herself to push the limits of her physical abilities and strength. She wouldn’t stop until she overcame the hurdles while learning a new skill. She was a determined soul. Once an idea or thought came to her mind, she would pursue it until she put it into action.

When her primary school teacher had asked the children of the class what they wanted to become when they grew up, Poorna had thought hard. She finally decided that she wanted to become a policewoman. The power, fear, risk and challenges attached to that uniform excited her. During one of her cycling escapades, she suddenly spotted a policewoman in the neighbourhood. Her heart skipped a beat, and her legs began to tremble. She dropped her cycle and rushed into her house. She hid next to a trunk and waited for a while with her eyes closed. She believed that the uniformed policewoman was there to arrest her and perhaps put her behind bars. After a long time, she gathered the courage to step out and heaved a sigh of relief when she found no trace of the policewoman. Later, she found out that the policewoman in khaki dress was none other than her neighbour Uma akka (elder sister), dressed in the NCC uniform given by her school.

Poorna was a bold and courageous girl. Her parents were simple, straightforward people who knew no guile. She had imbibed from them a sense of righteousness. Except for the police, she feared nothing. She believed that if she was right, then there’s nothing to fear. Naresh, the little lad, worried for her when she fought fiercely for what she wanted and for what she considered right. Once, she fought girls much older than her for a skipping rope. After some verbal exchange, the girls gave her the skipping rope and walked away.

Naresh was amused. ‘Poorna, aren’t you scared? You fight with big girls.’

‘Why should I be? I am not wrong. I told them that I wanted the rope after they finished. They were teasing me,’ she said and started skipping.

Education for most children came to a halt after primary school in Pakala, unless parents were willing to and could afford to send their children to the tribal hostel at Kamareddy. Devidas, however, applied to the Social Welfare Residential School at Tadwai in Nizamabad district, on the advice of Ravi, the local primary school teacher, and a distant relative. Qualifying applications were chosen through a lottery. Days passed with no intimation from the school. Devidas wasn’t prepared to take a chance. He admitted Poorna to the Tribal Welfare Hostel at Kamareddy, 45 kilometres from Pakala.

Poorna still remembers how she had sobbed the night away. The hostel was a shabby single room with a dilapidated toilet at the other end of the compound. There were only ten girls in the hostel. The school was almost two kilometres from the hostel, and the girls had to cover the distance by foot. The food was awful. Poorna cried every night and prayed that her parents would take her home from this wretched place. She didn’t mind quitting studies altogether or pleading her primary school teacher to accommodate her for one more year, but she would never stay in this ghastly place.

Devidas arrived at the end of two weeks. He announced that out of all the six girls who had applied to the Social Welfare Residential School, Poorna was the lucky one. He admitted her to the school in Tadwai. Poorna took an instant liking to this school. The teachers were knowledgeable; the premises was clean and tidy, and the food was scrumptious. What more could she ask for?

What if I hadn’t won the lottery? What if I was forced to stay there? She often wondered.

To this day, she shudders when she remembers the few days she spent at Kamareddy tribal hostel.

After lunch, Swapna went to the administration office, a small room adjacent to the principal’s chamber. The clerk greeted her with a smile. The only computer in the school was placed here. It was also connected to the internet. She requested the clerk cum computer operator to open a particular website. She sat at the computer and keyed in the details on the online form.

Student name | Class | Age
Ravali M | Inter Ist year | 16 years
Poorna Malavath | Class 9 A | 13 years

Swapna hit the ENTER key. She would not have imagined that her action would one day create history.

The Touch of Rocks

30 September 2013
6.30 am
Bhongir

She felt that the rock was watching her keenly; assessing her worth.

One single rock! So steep, almost vertical. How do you ever climb a vertical rock?

She looked at the rock from different angles.

The surface of this rock is as smooth as butter.

She imagined climbing the rock. It seemed a formidable task.

I have never seen such a huge rock around my village.

A sharp whistle shook her from her thoughts.

‘Girls! Fall into five rows. Maintain one arm distance. Make it faster,’ Parmesh, the trainer ordered.

There were a few sloppy moves in the group. ‘NOW!’ he yelled.

The girls quickly fell into five rows.

‘That’s better,’ he mumbled.

‘Good morning!’

‘Good morning, Sir’ a feeble response was all he received.

‘Arey bhai, jaranta energy to cheppunri! (Show some energy!) GOOD MORNING!’

‘Good morning, Sir!’ They shouted in unison.

‘Good-morning!’

‘Good-morning, Sir,’ the sharp response pierced the morning breeze.

‘Excellent! One last time. GOOD MORNING!’

‘GOOD MORNING, SIR!’ Pat came the reply. Their reflexes had been activated.

Parmesh’s energy was infectious. Sekhar Babu, the founder of ‘Transcend Adventures’, a rock climbing training school, had roped in Parmesh as a trainer. Parmesh, in fact, had trained Sekhar Babu in rock climbing. After being trained by Parmesh, Sekhar Babu followed Parmesh’s footsteps and got himself certified by the Himalayan Mountaineering Institute (HMI). After a few years, he established ‘Transcend Adventures’ and hired Parmesh as a trainer. Together, they began to conduct annual rock climbing camps for school children. They intended to pass on the art and technique of mountaineering to the younger generation, to kindle interest and invoke passion for mountaineering.

Parmesh scanned the group again. He saw one girl out of line. ‘ Eh ladki! Teekh se khado.’ (Fall into the line.)

Poorna quickly fell in line.

‘Introduce yourselves.’

One by one, the girls introduced themselves. Poorna tried to memorize the names, in vain. The voices began to drown. Soon, her focus narrowed down to the enormous, solitary rock that stood majestically before her eyes. She scanned the entire length of the rope that hung from atop the hill down to the ground. A seat was attached to the rope. A tall, fair, lean man sat on it, held the rope and started to climb the rock with ease and finesse.

What would it take to climb this rock!!? What if I fall?

Before she realized, it was her turn to introduce herself.

‘Poorna Malavath, 9th Class, Tadwai School.’

She shouted and turned to her right, indicating the next girl to take over.

This puny thing must be the youngest of all, Parmesh thought. Can she measure up to the challenge?

He decided to wait and watch. He was not one to jump to conclusions.

Parmesh asked the respective PETs to take the girls for a run, while he sorted the equipment.

After the run, Poorna stood in the queue for breakfast.

‘Only two idlis?’ Sekhar Babu asked, peering into her plate. ‘Have more. You have a long day ahead.’

Poorna smiled sheepishly but did not go for a second helping.

Parmesh summoned the girls after breakfast. He asked the PETs to take attendance.

Sekhar Babu headed toward the rope, while Parmesh addressed the girls.

‘Do you know why you are here?’

‘Yes, Sir.’

‘Why?’ he asked, pointing at Poorna.

‘Sir, to learn to climb this rock.’

‘Do you want to?’

‘Yes, Sir,’ the girls yelled.

‘Great! You are interested and motivated. A positive mindset is essential to learn a new skill.’

Pointing to the rock, he said, ‘This rock is five hundred and fifty feet high. We will ascend only three hundred and fifty feet. Rock climbing is one of the most adventurous sport. You must be wondering what you will gain out of this sport.’

‘Strength,’ said one girl.

‘Concentration,’ said another.

‘Yes, physical stamina, emotional balance and more importantly, you will discover yourselves.’

How do you discover yourself by climbing a rock, Poorna wondered.

‘You are a lucky bunch. Very few get such an opportunity at this young age. Will you put in your best efforts?’

‘Yes, Sir.’

‘If you think you are here for an excursion, you may leave immediately. If you do not work hard, you will be sent back without a second thought. Do you follow?’

‘Yes, Sir.’

‘Success and failure are part of learning. If you focus one hundred percent, you will succeed. Observe carefully. Listen attentively. You’ll master the art of climbing this big rock by the end of the course. Otherwise...’

He gave the group a tough look.

The girls headed toward their respective PETs to collect their gear, which included a pair of climbing shoes.

Sekhar Babu demonstrated the technique of fixing the harness around the waist. He then wore on the helmet and fastened it. He climbed with the help of the rope. His body moved along the surface of the rock as he climbed. Poorna was awestruck! He had climbed the three hundred and fifty feet in a matter of minutes!

He then demonstrated rappelling, the technique of ascending and descending with the help of a rope, a harness and a carabiner. He first locked the rope, harness and carabiner. He held the carabiner in his right hand and applied breaks whenever necessary while ascending.

‘This method is called ‘belaying’,’ he said, and warned the girls, ‘Control over body and speed is very important.’

Parmesh asked Sekhar Babu to demonstrate techniques to balance the body during descent. Sekhar Babu demonstrated how to rappel with speed. He glided down smoothly like a striker on a carrom board.

Parmesh demonstrated ‘speed jumping’ and explained that an experienced mountaineer could rapel down hundreds of feet with ease and speed.

‘During this course, you will hear me mention several technical terms. I’ll explain a few of them now. Listen carefully,’ Parmesh said, and continued,

‘Pinch hold – holding on to the grip in a pinching style.

Three-point technique – while climbing, all the three limbs are on the rock.

Bucket hold – a full grip of the rock using the whole palm and fingers.

Side-cut hold – holding the rock from the grips available on the sides.

Undercut hold – holding the rock with the grips available under the cracks.

Friction or pressure hold – the climber applies friction on the rock with a full palm.’

The first batch of five girls was ready to go.

‘Use your toes and fingers to get a grip in the crevices and edges of the rock,’ said Parmesh.

He demonstrated how to place the foot on the rock edge or in a crevice and said, ‘As much of the foot as possible must find a place on the rock for maximum balance while climbing down.’

Parmesh said, ‘Start climbing. Let your instincts guide you. Make friends with the rock. Bond with the rock. Now remove your mittens and start.’

‘Ready with your equipment?’

‘Yes, Sir.’

A sudden hush descended on the ground. The morning sun was moving higher up in the sky.

‘Ready?’ Parmesh’s voice echoed against the huge rock.

‘YES, SIR.’

Parmesh blew the whistle, and the students ran toward the rock. Poorna ran enthusiastically, letting go of all her fears.

She managed to take two steps and struggled for grip.

‘Aghh...!!!’ She fell.

Her palms were bruised. She pulled herself on to her feet. Dusting her pants, she noticed that only Roja akka had made some progress.

Poorna turned toward the rock and glued her eyes on it. She resolved .

I will climb this!

She took a deep breath and muttered, ‘ Jai Hanuman!’

Poorna’s little fingers searched for cracks on the rock surface; some grip that she could latch on to. She found a crack. She gripped her fingers in the crack and hoisted herself two steps. Another grip and she moved up another two. She searched for another, and she found it. She covered another two steps. Poorna reached out for one more, stretching her hands as far as possible. Her vision was limited to just a few feet of rock spread before her enormously. She reached out to a few more grip points and started crawling upwards, pushing her body against gravity. Sweat trickled down her temples and cheeks. Her moist hands left impressions on the rough rock surface. Poorna pushed herself up relentlessly.

‘Poorna’, she heard Parmesh. She felt a sudden jolt as when woken from a trance. She arched her neck back to look down. She almost lost grip. She turned toward the rock and took a deep breath.

‘That’s enough. Descend now.’

She assessed the situation. She hadn’t moved too high up, but she was high enough to hurt herself if she were to fall. She moved an arm down to find a grip. The descent wasn’t as easy as the ascent. She tried lowering one hand while the other was gripped tightly in a small crack in the rock. She panicked. How would she reach the ground? She tried to get a stronghold with her feet, but they trembled vigorously.

‘Poorna, bring one hand down. Just one…a little lower. Yeah…yeah…right there…you got a grip…good.’ Poorna followed Sekhar Babu’s words.

She managed to climb down and landed safely. She was sweating profusely, and her legs were still trembling.

It took the girls almost an hour to climb and descend from the huge rock.

‘Tell me, which was difficult? Climbing up or climbing down?’ Parmesh asked.

‘Climbing down, Sir,’ Ravali said.

‘You are right. That’s because you have still not mastered the technique of descent. Some of you were so scared that you froze midway. And this girl, shouts and screams for help. Some of you even performed break dance up there.’ The girls giggled.

‘Now, you will learn to balance yourself and your body. You are doing good. Techniques will make you more confident. You will also learn to use rock climbing and mountaineering equipment. Do you know that you have already tried a style of rock climbing?’ He waited for an answer. No one had an answer.

He continued. ‘It is called Traditional Climbing, also called Trad Climbing.’

Parmesh picked up a rope. ‘Remember the rope is a mountaineer’s lifeline. You will learn to make different types of knots. Knots keep the rope intact. You will also learn to coil a rope. These ropes are very long. More than a hundred meters long. Coiling them and keeping them safe is important. On the last day, you will take up practical and theory tests, and appear for a viva. You will be graded based on your performance.’

He added, ‘This course is specially designed for students of Social Welfare Residential Schools. This is a rare opportunity. This same course for the boys from your schools concluded yesterday. They did very well. Now it is your turn. Are you all ready?’

‘YES, SIR.’ The girls roared.

‘Good. Now I want you to try bouldering. Boulders are rocks that are 10-15 feet high.’

Parmesh led the group to the small boulders scattered around Bhongir rock. Poorna followed right behind him.

Before they could get started, he demonstrated different kinds of hitches. ‘This is the Clove hitch used to tie the rope to the anchor. And this, the Italian hitch, for attaching the carabiner and the belay device to be used while belaying and finally the Girth hitch, for attaching the sling to the harness.’

He then briefed them on how to balance themselves on the rocks.

Poorna held the rope and climbed with confidence, but she found descent difficult. She remembered to keep her legs slightly apart and hold the rope tight. When she landed, her eyes twinkled with a sense of achievement.

As the girls were taking turns, Parmesh noticed Poorna joining the line again for another chance. He signaled Sekhar Babu to keep an eye on her.

Parmesh didn’t fail to notice those eyes; calm, but focused and knowing, like an eagle, waiting for an opportunity.

By the third day, Poorna was comfortable applying the basic techniques of rock climbing. She followed Parmesh’s instructions to the tee, but she was still shy and reserved. Poorna learnt to make knots and hitches in no time. Mother Knot was the simplest of all. She learnt to make the Figure 8 Knot, Square Knot, also called Reef Knot. She especially liked the Fisherman Knot and the Double Fisherman Knot for their exclusive style of locking. Bow Line Knot though was a little tricky, but she learnt it. She also learnt the Middle Man Knot, Guide Man Knot, Friction Knot and End Man Knot.

That evening, the girls lodged at Aleru Social Welfare Residential School, twenty-five kilometers from Bhongir rock. This school remained open even during holidays to board student trainees.

The next day was more interesting. Parmesh picked up each piece of equipment and described its usage and functionality. He also talked about different concepts and terminology associated with mountaineering. The most important technique for top climbing is belaying. The belayer stands on the ground and controls the length and tension of the rope by locking or loosening the rope, which is looped through the anchor at the top. The climber and the belayer coordinate with each other while the climber takes the support of the belay to ascend and descend the rock. As the climber proceeds upward, the belayer pulls the rope to provide sufficient tension. During descent, the belayer releases the rope through the belaying device, also called verso or with another piece of equipment called the descender.

Poorna practised belaying. She locked herself through the carabiner and shouted out as taught, ‘I’m ready for climbing.’

The belayer responded, ‘Climb on.’

A few steps ahead, she said, ‘Belay tight.’

The belayer pulled the rope to induce tension.

Once she reached the top, she said, ‘I am at the anchor.’

‘Okay,’ she was acknowledged.

While descending, she said, ‘Lower me.’

The belayer responded, ‘Lowering.’

On reaching the ground, she said, ‘I am safe.’

Parmesh told them that the belay rope is the lifeline of climbing when using belay technique, although it is not preferred in high altitudes as the ropes are already fixed for climbers. For great heights as the Everest, they use an equipment called Jumar to ascend and descend and this method is called ‘jumaring’. The Jumar is also called the Ascender and the Descender according to the purpose for which it is used.

The equipment has enormous load bearing capacity. The smallest equipment can take weights starting from 1,200 kg. Poorna connected the concept of ‘breakpoint’ that she had learnt in her physics class to the breaking point of the equipment. She was surprised that a carabiner could withstand weights upto 2,500 kg when locked and up to 8,000 kg when unlocked. Parmesh encouraged the girls to touch, feel and hold different equipment. Poorna held a Pitton in her hand. She imagined a mountaineer hanging in the air with just the anchored Pitton for support. She looked at it with great respect.

Such a tiny piece of equipment! What critical functionality! She thought.

She handed the Pitton back to Sekhar Babu.

Day three was bright and sunny. An incident, both disturbing and motivating occurred during training. Bharathi, a fellow student, rappelled too fast and lost balance. Unable to keep pace, she tumbled over, close to the ground. Despite the secure helmet, she hurt her head. She was bleeding. The girls panicked. Sekhar Babu calmed them and called for a doctor from Bhongir. The doctor said that although the injury was superficial, the skin on the scalp was torn and needed two sutures. She was taken to the clinic. Since anesthesia was not available at the clinic, Bharati took the stitches without local sedation. She did not complain! They returned to the camp site. Sekhar Babu decided to send her home to recuperate. Bharathi began to sob.

‘Nanna, nenu ponu.’ (I don’t want to go back, father.)

Poorna wondered how Bharathi could refer to Parmesh as ‘ Nanna’ (father).

‘I don’t want to go home. I don’t want to miss the training. I want to be here…with my friends and complete the course.’

‘Fine,bidda (child). Stay with us. But you will not climb until you are better. You need to rest now.’

Poorna saw Parmesh in his most kind and endearing form that day. Bharathi and Parmesh had known each other for only these three days.

‘You are a crazy girl! You didn’t cry when you were sutured without anaesthesia, and now you cry because we wanted to send you back? Pagal ladki! (Crazy girl!). But remember. You will not climb until you are fine.’

Over the next two days, the girls underwent rigorous climbing practice. They used various equipment and practised different techniques. Poorna’s focus was only on devising the best possible method to climb. On the fifth day, the girls took up the practical and theory tests and the viva. They climbed the 350 ft with ease.

The Petite Girl and Her Immense Determination

4 October 2013
4.30 pm
Bhongir

A rustic, makeshift dais was erected for the Valedictory Function. The group of girls and the boys who had trained at Bhongir earlier had assembled. A big black car cruised into the Aleru Social Welfare Residential School campus. Poorna couldn’t get a clear view of the people who alighted. Sekhar Babu, Parmesh and principals from a few welfare schools flanked the car. After the customary handshakes and exchange of pleasantries, Poorna noticed a well-built figure approach them.

Ah! That must be Mr. Praveen Kumar IPS! Thought Poorna.

Till this day, Poorna had no idea that her school was part of the Social Welfare Residential Schools of Andhra Pradesh (now bifurcated into Telangana and Andhra Pradesh). She was eager to see the official who headed all the schools: Secretary, Dr. R.S. Praveen Kumar, IPS, ( The Secretary of Social Welfare Residential Schools) Chief Guest of the Valedictory function.

His pace was brisk. Poorna hadn’t seen anyone walk with such confidence and self-assurance. His shadow fell on Poorna as he walked past her. She joined her hands in applause along with the other children. Deevena, one of the participants of the camp, stepped forward to offer him a bouquet.

The sternness of his features disappeared for a moment, and a warm smile lit his face as he said, ‘Thank you!’

Poorna found his smile affable.

His tall, chiseled frame and tonsured head stood him apart from the crowd. But his dark complexion made him one among them. He smiled at some, greeted others and nodded in acknowledgement. For a few moments, he looked at the massive Bhongir rock spread before him.

He turned around and said, ‘Wonderful! So, all of you have climbed this rock!’

‘Yes, Sir. 350 ft,’ they shouted.

His smile gradually broadened and turned into a light chuckle.

Sekhar Babu formally welcomed the Chief Guest.

The children listened to the Chief Guest’s speech with rapt attention.

‘You are little bundles of unlimited energy. Did you ever imagine that you could climb this rock? Never! Right? Well, now you have climbed this steep rock. That means you can climb any mountain. You can reach any mountain. You can reach any height. Man has reached the moon. Can you imagine that? The world laughed when it first heard that man would travel to the moon. But man reached the Moon nevertheless. You would have laughed if you were told that you could climb a steep rock, 350 feet high. Here you are! Proud that you have accomplished the task! How did you climb? Not because you had the climbing equipment. Not because you learnt the techniques of climbing. You climbed because of your determination. Now you know that with determination, you can climb any rock. You can reach any summit. You can achieve any goal! You only need to know what you want and put all your efforts in that direction. This is just the Bhongir rock. Do you know that the Everest is the highest peak in the world! You must aim for the Everest. That is why I named this training program, ‘Project Everest’. Set difficult and challenging goals for yourselves. Always think big and aim big.’

Praveen Kumar distributed certificates. Poorna and Roja shared the Best Performer award in the Girls category. Nagaraju won the Best Performer award in the Boys category. Poorna walked brisk, with chin up and head held high, just like Praveen Kumar. Praveen Kumar gave her the Best Performer Award certificate and a cash prize of  R 5,000, and said, ‘Good job!’ She was chosen among the one hundred and ten children who came to Bhongir from all over the State.

Poorna was delighted. Deep in her heart, Poorna was taken in by his words.

After the event, snacks were served. Praveen Kumar, Sekhar Babu and a few other teaching staff were immersed in conversation. Praveen was listening attentively.

‘Bharathi,’ Sekhar Babu called, ‘Come here.’

Bharathi ran up and stood next to Parmesh. Praveen Kumar patted her shoulder, and said, ‘Good performance.’

Sekhar Babu then called out to Nagaraju. He sprung up from the group of children sitting under the tree.

It was Poorna’s turn to meet the Secretary. As she walked up, she wondered what she would say to him.

‘So, Poorna,’ he said, extending his hand toward her, ‘You stood first.’

‘Yes, Sir,’ Poorna’s smile gleamed over her dark face. She held out her tiny hand. He held her hand warmly and said, ‘It’s lovely meeting champions like you Poorna. Keep it up!’

Poorna pranced back to her friends.

He called me a champion!

Praveen watched Poorna as she ran toward the Bhongir rock to join her friends chatting under the sprawling shade of a large tree. Her small frame stood in stark contrast to the rock.

The immense rock. The petite girl.

The petite girl and her immense determination.

The irony struck him.

The petite girl conquered the immense rock. Sheer will! Sheer determination!

He was in awe of the potential of the human mind.

‘Wow,’ he thought! ‘Just wow...’

He turned toward Sekhar Babu. ‘Tell me more; how did the children perform?’

‘Sir,bacche to bohot acche hain, (The children performed very well) Sir! Both boys and girls are very energetic, motivated and focused, Sir.’

‘That’s good to know. I am glad I have signed this program with you...the two-men army has done a good job!’

‘Sir, to be honest, for some of these children, climbing this rock was a cakewalk. A few of them have great potential. They are cut out for trekking and expeditions. The children, their PETs …nobody knows this.’

‘I see. This is interesting.’

‘Well, do you think these children should be given the next level of training?’

‘Well...yes...but not all of them. I can see the spark in some of the children...they can reach great heights, literally...’

‘Hmm.’

‘But definitely, a few can become great mountaineers.’

‘So, what is the next level of training?’

Sekhar Babu gave it a serious thought and said, ‘HMI, Sir.’

‘Himalayan Mountaineering Institute? Are you serious? Aren’t there any other training centres closer to school?’

‘No, Sir. No other mountaineering school in South India. And the children are good enough to be sent to HMI.’

HMI is a world-class institute established by Jawaharlal Nehru recognizing mountaineering as an organized sport after Tenzing Norgay summited Mount Everest in 1953.

HMI, for these children..!!How absurd.

Sekhar Babu for a moment, regretted the thought.

HMI is maintained by the Ministry of Defence. These are high school children! But unless one tries, one never knows. There’s nothing to lose. It’s a proposal, after all.

Praveen Kumar stood up. ‘Okay, time for me to leave.’ His gunman called for the vehicle on his wireless. The vehicle revved into the campus. The chauffeur opened the door and waited. Praveen Kumar waved goodbye to the children sitting under the canopy of trees. Upon seeing him, they stood up at once.

Mountaineers!

He said to himself under his breath and got into the vehicle. The door closed with a soft thud.

Fifteen minutes later, Sekhar Babu received a call from Praveen Kumar.

Praveen Kumar came straight to the point.

‘Sekhar Babu, I think we can go ahead with the HMI proposal. Before that, I want you to convince my boss, the Principal Secretary of Social Welfare Residential Schools.’

‘Your boss? I convince him?’ Sekhar Babu suspended all formalities for a moment and said, ‘Sir, you must be joking. How can I?’

‘You can convince him. I will arrange for a meeting. Meanwhile, short-list the top twenty performers who can be sent to HMI.’ Praveen Kumar hung up.

Two weeks later, Poorna packed her bags for a training camp to be held at Social Welfare Residential School in Gowlidoddi, located in the suburbs of Hyderabad. This was the pre-level training for students shortlisted for advanced training at The Himalayan Mountaineering Institute (HMI), Darjeeling.

Warming Up to the Frozen Mountains

26 October 2013
6.00 pm
Secunderabad Railway Station

Excitement was palpable among the nineteen children travelling to Himalayan Mountaineering Institute (HMI). One more boy, Praveen Kumar, would join them at Vishakapatnam. The children looked smart in their sports uniform, with ‘Social Welfare Residential School’ printed on the back of their t-shirts. Their excitement peaked when the train whistled and began to move slowly. For most of them, this was their first ever train journey. Their nervous excitement was uncontainable. A few, for whom this was not the first, bossed over the novices. Some suppressed their excitement to look cool. However, for everyone, this was the first journey across the State borders. The train chugged along, drowning the buzz of chatter.

The children were travelling by sleeper class to New Jalpaiguri Railway Station junction from where they would be driven to HMI in Darjeeling. They were scheduled to reach the station in thirty-six hours, i.e., next evening.

Parmesh scanned the entire compartment to ensure everything was in order. He was quite satisfied: students were comfortable; the luggage was tucked below the berths; there was enough food for breakfast and lunch; above all, the children were in good spirit.

He took attendance, and this was the third time; the first at Secunderabad railway station platform; and, second, before the train started: Poorna, Roja, Bharathi, Deevena, Abhilasha, Saika Krishnaveni, Ramalakshmi, Sarita, Ravali, Rupa, Anand, Gangadhar, Satya Rao, Madhukar, Anjani Prasad, Mohan Prasad, Nagaraju, Srikumar, Shyam Prasad. Once Praveen Kumar joined them at Vishakhapatnam, they would be ten girls and ten boys.

Aghh...twenty adolescents and three of us!

The thought rooted itself in Parmesh’s mind. He looked nervously at Surekha, the PET teacher. She returned a reassuring smile. She was well-acquainted with the children, as she had worked with them for a whole month. The fact that she taught at one of the Social Welfare Residential Schools was an added advantage. Anil, Paramesh’s assistant, accompanied them.

The engine was replaced at the Khajipet station. After breakfast, the children played antyakshari. The train resumed after a twenty-minute halt. A quarter of an hour passed. Parmesh began to feel anxious. It took a couple of minutes for him to figure out what was bothering him. Then it hit him. The train that was supposed to make a right turn at Khajipet had taken a left turn. He enquired with his fellow passengers. They had no clue. He rushed to the TTE.

‘We had to change the route. The cyclone has hit Odisha. Two bridges have collapsed at Srikakulam. So we have taken a detour.’

Oh! Praveen Kumar. How will he reach the camp? We are not even going via Vishakapatnam!

He called Sekhar Babu to brief him of this unexpected development. Sekhar Babu assured that he would help Praveen reach Darjeeling. By evening, after much anxiety, Parmesh learnt that the train was redirected via Khajipet-Karimnagar-Nagpur-Madhya Pradesh-New Jalpaiguri instead of the regular Khajipet-Vijaywada-Vishakhapatnam-Bhuvaneswar-Kolkata-New Jalpaiguri route. Since the train was unscheduled, it was accommodated between two other trains at every station. Paramesh could not reach the platform to buy food for the children. He managed to pick up whatever little he could within the limited time to keep hunger at bay.

The train reached New Jalpaiguri after fifty-six hours! Although it was evening, the sun was still blazing, and the heat hit them in the face. Sekhar Babu had arranged taxis for the journey to Darjeeling. Parmesh instructed the students to keep their jackets handy before boarding the taxi. The children were puzzled. The temperature was higher than in Hyderabad for that hour. They reached Darjeeling after a three and a half hour drive, at 7.30 pm.

The children were rushed into their rooms. Despite wearing jackets, their teeth chattered, and hands shivered. They were in a sub-zero temperature zone for the first time in their lives. They quickly freshened up and assembled for dinner, eager to snuggle back into the warm comforters.

Parmesh read out the schedule for the next day at the dining table. Since HMI does not entertain foster care, Parmesh, Anil and Surekha had also enrolled themselves into the program so they could watch over the children.

28 October 2013
5.45 am
HMI Ground

The children gathered at the practice ground for their workout. The morning fog was still dense. The temperature was as low as 6˚c. Despite the long journey and sudden shift in weather conditions, the children had managed to beat fatigue to assemble at the practice ground on time.

Parmesh beamed with pride.

He had conducted training for thousands of children.

These children are different. They have fire in their belly. These are not the spoilt brats coming out of incubation chambers. Education is a luxury for these children, he thought.

The junior instructor arrived first and took attendance. The senior instructor arrived at 6 am.

‘These children...??!!’ He said with surprise and disbelief.

He went through the chart and looked at them again. Turning toward Parmesh, he said, ‘These children are too young. How can we train them? We have never trained such young ones.’

‘But, this is a special course. We have written approval. Praveen Kumar Sir has already taken the necessary permission. He has also spoken to Captain Samuel.’

Captain Samuel Larlintunga is the officiating principal of HMI.

‘Maybe. But the minimum qualifying age for this program, after all concessions, is seventeen. How can we accept children below fifteen years?’

‘Yeh toh chote bacche hain bhai! (These are small children!) Below fifteen years, we are stretching this too far!’

Parmesh checked the chart. He knew that all the children were under seventeen. But he did not expect some of them to be as young as thirteen! ‘Sir, but we have permission ...’

The senior instructor thought for a few seconds.

‘Accha. Pehle inko running ke liye le jaavo…’ (Ok, first take them out for a run.)

The junior instructor blew the whistle. The students started the four-kilometer run around the hill adjacent to HMI. No sooner had they started, one of them came back limping, clutching his stomach, face contorted in pain.

‘Sir,’ he said, gasping for breath. ‘My stomach is aching.’

The senior instructor gave Parmesh a sharp look.

Parmesh knew the tedious train journey and sudden change in climate had not gone well with the children. A three-day long train journey had landed them from one of the hottest regions to one of the coldest areas of India. The children needed some time to acclimatize themselves to the new environment.

The junior instructor mustered all his energy and shouted, ‘Run!!’

But his voice went flat. He could not bring himself to use the loud, commanding tone he always used during training sessions. But these are not trainees. Too young to be called ‘Trainees of HMI’.

‘These children are too young for this course,’ said the senior instructor over breakfast. ‘They are still children.Naadaan hain. Fit ho to sahi. Par woh kaafee nahin hain. (They are innocent. Yes, they are fit, but that is not quiet enough.) Their lungs, calf muscles, bone and body length, are still developing.’

After a few minutes of silence, he finally said, ‘ Teek hain. (Alright). Our Course Director will be back in three days. In the meantime, let’s complete the theory lessons, equipment handling and rock climbing exercises.Phir dekhenge.(we shall see what we can do.)’

Parmesh was relieved.

By evening, Praveen Kumar arrived at the institute along with his father. The children gathered around him as he shared with great enthusiasm his adventurous travel to HMI.

Praveen’s father was in awe of the beauty of Darjeeling. He had never seen a hill station with such extreme temperatures.

Gaping at the Nepali instructors, he asked Parmesh, ‘Sir, are we in India?’

‘Yes. Yes. We are!’

29 October, 2013

Parmesh was called to the Course Director’s chamber. He was hoping and praying that the children will be allowed to complete the course. His anxiety turned to surprise when he entered the Director’s chamber.

‘Arey! Jyothi Sir!!’

Roshan Ghatraj is known as ‘Jyothi’ among colleagues and friends.

‘Don’t you recognize me? I am Parmesh Singh, your student from the 2001 batch.’

Jyothi was the course instructor when Parmesh completed his Advanced Mountaineering Course in HMI in 2001.

After a few seconds, he said, ‘ Haan, yaad aaya Parmesh. Kaise ho?’ (Yes. I remember Parmesh. How are you?)

‘Teek hoon Sir! Abhi toh meraa waat lagee hain!’ (I am good, Sir. But right now, I am in a soup.)

‘Haan, haan sunaa hain. Baito.’ (Yes, I heard about that. Please sit.)

In a bid to convince Jyothi, Parmesh explained that the children had undergone rock climbing lessons and that he had assessed them as quick learners, quite tough for their age.

‘Teek hain, Sir. Let’s do one thing. Let’s give them a test. Let the children do the Tiger Hill exercise. They will leave by 7.00 am and return by 2.00  pm,’ Parmesh suggested.

‘Generally it is 1 pm,’ Jyothi corrected him, with a smile.

‘Yes, Sir! Generally, it is 1 pm. But I need one more hour, considering their age’.

‘Sure. Take one and a half hours. But be careful. These are children. Not that you don’t know. We are answerable to their parents,’ Jyothi said looking straight into Parmesh’s eyes, with a serious demeanor.

Parmesh knew Jyothi well. He is well-meaning. He is always concerned about the well-being of his students, not just because he is answerable.

As he walked out, Parmesh decided not to tell the children that this would be an elimination test of sorts. The fitness and the feasibility of training these children now rested entirely on his judgment. He felt all the more responsible for the children now.

30 October, 2013
10.30 am
Course Director’s Office, HMI

The next morning, Poorna and her friends began jogging toward Tiger Hill. They were at ease in the new locale after three days of routine. Tiger Hill is 11  km from HMI and 2,590 meters above sea level. The sunrise point on the hill is a tourist attraction. The entire Kanchenjunga range is visible from atop Tiger Hill. Under a clear sky, even the peak of Mount Everest, 172 km away is visible. The children reached the hilltop in a few hours.

The atmosphere at Tiger Hill is almost similar to the atmosphere on the Himalayan range. The oxygen content is low, and staying at the top is usually not recommended beyond 15 minutes for first-time climbers. Parmesh was keen that the children get a glimpse of the Kanchenjunga range. But a thick layer of fog had reduced visibility to nil. With no luck, the officer accompanying the students suggested that it was time to leave. However, Parmesh requested for another fifteen minutes hoping the fog would clear, but in vain.

Parmesh looked at his watch as soon as they entered HMI. He called Jyothi, who was in a meeting. Jyothi looked at the large wall clock in his room. It showed 1 pm.

Parmesh said jocularly, ‘Shall we go again?!’

‘Yes, Sir!’ roared the children.

‘But Sir...,’ Madhukar mumbled. ‘Lunch karke jaayenge Sir, bahut bhook lag rahi hain.’ (Let’s go after lunch. We are quite famished.)

The group burst out laughing.

Jyothi agreed to send the children to HMI Base Camp for the ‘height gaining process’, an essential aspect in mountaineering that helps acclimatization at higher altitudes.

1 November 2013
Darjeeling to Yaksum

A seven-hour drive, with a two-hour lunch break at Jorethang took the children to Yaksum, a fairly big village in west Sikkim, located at an altitude of 1,780 meters (5,840 feet above sea-level). From Yaksum, they would trek back to HMI Base Camp located in Chaurikhang, in west Sikkim, over three days via the Bakhim-Dzongrila route. The Yuksom-Dzongri trek is a popular high-altitude trek in west Sikkim. The trek path passes through dense forests, alpine lakes and culminates at the Kangchenjanga. The temperature in early November is quite pleasant, with large patches of picturesque green tracts of land.

2 November 2013
Yaksum to Bakhim

Bakhim is at an altitude of 3,100 metres (9,000 feet approximately) and is also called Camp 1. The trek from Yaksum to Bakhim is twelve kilometers. The children were scheduled to start at 7 o’ clock. A fit adult, who is a seasoned trekker, usually covers this distance in five to six hours.

‘Teek hain, yeh to bacchen hai. Chaar baje tak pohoche to bi teek hain. (These are children. It’s good enough even if they reach by 4 o’ colock .) We’ll have late lunch. Let’s carry some chocolates and biscuits to munch along the way,’ the HMI staff suggested.

Parmesh was alert for symptoms of mountain sickness. Although the trek could be covered in six hours, Parmesh remembered that he had taken more than six hours to reach Bakhim the first time.

Each of them carried a rucksack containing a sleeping bag, a few clothes, climbing equipment and food to eat on their way. Parmesh and the HMI staff made sure that the students got a break once every hour and a half. They stopped by a stream or waterfall and munched on chocolates and biscuits.

After a three-hour trek, Bharathi leaned against a near-by tree, threw her rucksack on the ground and slumped on to the ground.

‘I cannot do it anymore, Sir. Chala alisipoyaanu. (I am exhausted.) Can I go back?’ Parmesh gauged that this was not a symptom of acute mountain sickness.

He called out to the rest of the children, ‘Bharathi is not feeling well. Can a few of you please carry her luggage?’

No one came forward. Carrying their own rucksacks was tiring enough.

‘Come on. Let’s distribute her luggage.’

Everybody looked away.

‘I can help, Sir,’ Anand offered.

A few other students made hesitant offers.

‘Very good!’

Parmesh took out the sleeping bag and gave it to Anand. He distributed her equipment into two other rucksacks. He fastened the rucksack again and lifted it to check the weight.

‘Should not be more than two kilos. Now take it,’ he said and helped Bharathi wear on her rucksack again.

The team reached Bakhim in six and a half hours. Parmesh loved the surprise written large on the faces of the HMI staff who welcomed them.

Bharathi was attended to by a doctor. It was her mind playing games, probably because of home sickness. In a day, she was back on her feet.

The HMI personnel advised Parmesh to halt at Bakhim for two nights, considering that the altitude difference between Yaksum and Bakhim was around 5,000 feet. The next halt, Dzongri was at 13,200 feet. Treading slowly is the key to survival and acclimatization in these extreme temperatures.

After lunch, the group was taken for a short walk to a small hillock just to assess their fitness level. The next day too, exercise was limited to a short walk.

2 November 2013

It was Diwali. The HMI personnel gave each child two candles and asked them to cut each to make three smaller candles. A halwai was called to prepare sweets. They lit the candles around the stay-house. The house glowed elegantly amongst the snowy mountains of Himalayas.

4 November 2013
Bakhim to Dzongri

The team headed to Dzongri, also called Camp 2, at an altitude of 13,200 feet. Dzongri is picture perfect with a beautiful blend of greenery and snow. This exotic trek path is internationally famous. Although seasoned trekkers were known to take eight hours to cover the distance, the children covered it in seven and a half hours.

The contingent returned from Dzongri to HMI.

‘Manntalu, manntalu...,’ (It’s burning... burning...) Parmesh heard someone scream from the dining area that evening.

Parmesh rushed to find Mohan jumping up and down while the other children were trying to figure out what was happening. Anand was recording this scene on Parmesh’s mobile with a mischevious smile! Mohan had washed his hands in cold water, although hot water was available. Little did he know that tap water would be chill and chilled water would burn the skin, just like hot water. It took about fifteen minutes for the burning sensation to subside. Parmesh took this opportunity to warn the children against ‘metal bite’. A piece of metal, for instance, a spoon, when left outside the whole night, would stick to the skin and peel the skin off if pulled. He strongly recommended that the students wear gloves or mittens before holding or clasping any object.

Although Mohan recovered in fifteen minutes, his friends teased him about this incident all through the expedition.

5 November 2013
Dzongri to HMI

The team started its journey at 7.00 am to the HMI Base Camp, which is at an altitude of 14,600 feet. They reached HMI Base Camp by 3.30 that noon. The last four hours they trekked on a snow track. There were no signs of greenery around, no grass, no bushes and no trees. All they could see was an endless white carpet of snow. A sudden silence descended on the bubbly and chirpy children. The infinite whiteness of the snow mountains reflected in their eyes. Huge tents of mountains rose up to the skies. The sky, hanging above with its corners tucked into the mountains with the valleys blissfully snuggled in between was indeed breathtaking. The innocent souls were instantly, irrevocably hypnotized by the mystic Himalayan range.

Parmesh observed every member of his team, for it was at this altitude and at this temperature that trekkers often suffered from Acute Mountain Sickness (AMS). Usually about a fourth of any trekking contingent suffers from symptoms of AMS including headache, nausea, restlessness, breathing problems, cramps, etc. The most dangerous symptom is hypothermia, a drop in body temperature due to exposure to the strong chilly winds that sweep across the mountains. Appropriate clothing is very essential to prevent hypothermia.

Pulmonary edema or accumulation of water in the lungs is another critical condition. The atmosphere at such high altitudes contains tiny particles of snow, which enter the lungs during breathing. The snow particles condense due to body temperature, and the lungs fill up with water, narrowing the lung space for oxygen. Typically, in the tropics, the air is composed of 70% oxygen and 30% other gases. In high altitudes such as the Himalayas, the atmosphere comprises only 50% oxygen, and the rest is other gases. The lungs begin to take in more air for want of more oxygen. This activity cannot be stopped as it is an involuntary process initiated by the body for survival. This process continues during sleep too. If the body fails to adjust, then oxygen will have to be administered externally. To avoid these severe conditions, acclimatization is very essential. Experienced mountaineers can also become victims of this condition. A mountaineer will have to allow his body to acclimatize each time he undertakes an expedition. Acclimatization allows the body enough time to naturally produce more Red Blood Cells to absorb oxygen that is required for survival at such heights.

Parmesh was only thankful that none of his children had to face any of these symptoms. The children played on the premises of HMI Base Camp. Every four or five hours, the HMI Base Camp staff was instructed over walkie-talkie by HMI staff to assess the children. A sick child would have to be sent back to HMI. But none of them had to go. The children of Social Welfare Residential Schools displayed acute survival instincts.

The team is fit and fine, HMI staff regularly updated their Secretary, Praveen Kumar.

10 November 2013
Mount Renock

The children successfully summited Mount Renock, 16,500 feet above sea level in the Kanchenjunga range of mountains. This was their first real mountaineering expedition and first victory in mountaineering. Three students who couldn’t cope with the hectic schedules were dropped at the Base Camp.

The children were mesmerized by the view from atop Renock. They were awestruck by the sublime beauty surrounding them – the expansive stretch of pure whiteness, broken by a hint of green and brown here and there amidst the howl of the strong, chill winds. They hoisted the Indian flag and shouted slogans of Social Welfare Residential Schools.

13 November 2013
Darjeeling

The trekking contingent arrived in Darjeeling, having experienced a euphoria that they hadn’t known ever before. They had witnessed and embraced nature in all its enormity and glory. Jyothi Sir was thrilled to receive the children. He was relieved that all of them were in good form.

Along with the euphoric expression, he also noticed a serenity, and calmness that comes out of a sublime experience. This euphoria is not just a sensual high but also that which emanates from a heightened spiritual experience. He was quite familiar with this expression on the faces of hundreds of people who came to HMI. But this was the first time he saw it on the faces of young, innocent children, who are nearer to the spiritual realm of life. Their innocence mingled with sublimity reminded him of the serenity of monks in a monastery.

He remembered his initial concern.

How can we train these small children? How can we take them to the mountains?

Captain Samuel had advised Jyothi Sir, ‘Just run the course. Let’s see how they perform.’

Jyothi was almost sure that the children would not make it till the finishing line. The children had proved him wrong. He carefully examined the training chart. The children had excelled in glacier walk, height gaining, Jumaring and rock climbing. Their performance motivated the course instructors to teach them more and more.

During the expedition, Jyothi instructed his staff to check on the children all through the night. This was the first time that the children slept in sleeping bags. However, the bags were too big.

Language was a barrier. The HMI staff was conversant in English and Hindi. Most children couldn’t speak or understand Hindi. A smattering of English and gestures were the only mode of communication. Nevertheless, they bonded well.

16 November 2013

HMI had organized a graduation ceremony for the Welfare School contingent and had invited the Secretary, Mr. Praveen Kumar and Sekhar Babu to the event. The children were excited that Mr. Praveen Kumar was coming all the way to be part of the event.

As soon as he arrived at HMI, he met Parmesh and said, ‘Where are the children. I want to meet them right away!’

‘Han han Sir, hum bhi taras rahe hain,’ (Yes Sir, even we are eagerly waiting) said Sekhar Babu.

The children rushed to the lobby to meet Praveen Kumar. The large lobby echoed with the children greeting Praveen Kumar in one go. Praveen happily welcomed the energy. There were twenty handshakes competing with each other – all transmitting love and gratitude.

He saw in them, the future, the future of Swaeroes, his icons of the future.

As he looked, his gaze turned quizzical. ‘Guys, where is your winter wear?’

The children looked at themselves and wondered. Only Sekhar Babu and Praveen were wearing sweaters. After the early morning drill, the children had had their bath and rushed to meet Praveen Kumar, forgetting their winter wear. Praveen Kumar looked at his smart watch. The barometer showed 4˚c!

Defying Odds, Vision for Future

17 November 2013

‘Yehjo material hain….’ (These children...) Jyothi paused amidst deep thought and said, ‘Praveen Kumar ji, yeh aisi waisi material nahin hain. Yeh aath hazaar meter par tak chalne ki laayak hain…’ (They are not run-of-the-mill kind. They are good for 8,000 meters too.)

Praveen stopped short hearing these words. He wasn’t sure he had heard Jyothi right. He turned to look at the expression on Jyothi’s face. Jyothi was looking into the distance; his eyes fixed on nothing in particular. He certainly wasn’t joking.

Praveen understood exactly what Jyothi had just implied. The children were capable of reaching the DEATH ZONES! Let alone DEATH ZONES, Praveen Kumar hadn’t even imagined he would send the children to HMI. Praveen Kumar would have dismissed these words, had they come from anyone other than Jyothi. But now he was gripped by them.

Jyothi seemed convinced. According to Jyothi, they are ready for the next big step.

Is he convinced? Does hethink so?

He could not elicit answers from himself just yet. He parked the questions and decided to think over them another time.

After presenting the certificates, Jyothi took him around the HMI campus. He was high praises for Praveen’s initiative to give the children an experience of the HMI camp. He also lauded the commitment of the trainers and the supporting staff.

Praveen thanked him and said, ‘Sir, all things said and done, the children are the real heroes. Their energy and tenacity are incomparable. They are self-motivated.’

Praveen bid goodbye to the children.

Sekhar Babu and Parmesh headed to the cafeteria.

‘Parso, bacchon ko phir se Tiger Hill pe leke jaana hain Sir! (The day after, we plan to take the children to Tiger Hill.) I want them to see the Kanchenjunga range from there,’ Parmesh said.

‘A wall climbing workshop has also been planned, Sir,’ Sekhar Babu added.

‘Fantastic. We will meet once you are back,’ said Praveen.

The car cruised through the lush green tea gardens swirling down the ghats to reach Bagdogra airport from Darjeeling. Praveen Kumar sat in the front seat. The crisp fresh air was soothing.

Nothing is more precious for Praveen, than time. He has a clear vision for his life. He knows exactly what he wants to do with his life and what he wants to achieve during this lifetime. He is on a mission. And nothing and nobody can stop him. His vision and mission are not self-centered. All his efforts are directed outward, toward humanity. He believes that he is a mere instrument to promote equality and balance in the life of those communities that are marginalized and deprived of the privileges and benefits of the democratic system; no it’s not even the privileges and benefits; it is the basic human rights as guaranteed by the Indian Constitution.

He was preoccupied with something else now. His conversation with Jyothi was replaying itself again and again in his mind. He shuffled in his seat. De, Praveen Kumar’s driver, tried to divert his attention to the men and women picking tea leaves, but his mind wouldn’t budge.

The children can reach the DEATH ZONES at 8,000 meters above sea level!

There are only fourteen DEATH ZONES in the entire world. It isn’t easy to survive in these zones, and hence the name. At altitudes of around 8,000 meters, the air pressure drops to 30% compared to that at sea level. Hence the oxygen intake reduces to 30%. Surviving sub-zero temperatures is another gigantic challenge. Above 8,000 meters, the temperature drops to as low as -50˚C. Under such conditions, keeping oneself emotionally stable is critical. Physical endurance would have been achieved through training and workouts. But psychological endurance has to be achieved on the go. Praveen knows for a fact that the ratio of mountaineers who perish in the DEATH ZONES is more than in any other zone.

Can the students be expected to succeed while exposed to such high risk zones? He wondered.

Saath aath hazaar ke laayak!!

These words sent a chill up his spine. Jyothi thinks the children can reach the DEATH ZONE!! These innocent, carefree children?? Jyothi would never be casual; and, certainly not when he is talking about children. This is his assessment of the Social Welfare School children.

My children. My Swaeroes!

His heart swelled with pride.

My Swaeroes are top class mountaineers! Yes. They are! worthy of scaling 7,000 - 8,000 meters.

His Swaeroes! Mountaineers!

No ordinary teenager will bathe in cold water in this climate! No teenager will step out of his room without winter wear! What singular mental strength do these children possess to be able to summit a mountain at an altitude of 16,500 feet from sea level? What energy, what constitution do they inherit to achieve this feat, with such minimal training?

To be or not to be?

He tapped his fingers rhythmically on his armrest.

To send them or not?

But why am I taking this on myself? My intention was to give these children an opportunity. An experience. Is this not enough?

He saw the faces of the beaming children.

Poorna! Happy. Full of energy. Focused. From a small village. She climbed Mount Renock. 16,500 feet!

Bharathi! Perseverance incarnate!

Roja! She has already devised her own technique of climbing. Not to mention her precision!

Don’t they deserve a chance to do more? But why do more? What’s the limit?

Why do I need to prove this? And to whom?

Why does Praveen Kumar want a transfer?

Praveen Kumar took a deep breath. He certainly knows why.

Two roads diverged in a wood, and I –

I took the one less travelled by,

And that has made all the difference.

It’s been two years since he requested a transfer to the Social Welfare Department from the Police Department. He had spent 17 years in the Police Department. He started his career as an Assistant Superintendent of Police and grew in rank to become the Joint Commissioner. He was honoured with several medals from the Government of India, including the President’s Gallantry Medal. He was one among the 6,000 officers who have won this medal; the chosen 6,000 among the 20 lakh police officers in India.

He was part of the ‘Greyhounds’, the police force that specializes in anti-insurgency operations against Naxalites and Maoist terrorists in Andhra Pradesh. The covert operations were always life threatening. Despite his success in the Police Forces, he often felt disgruntled.

What am I really achieving? Fame and Honor?

My life revolves around promoting myself and my family…I, me, myself? Is this my sole purpose in life?

He and his family lived a life of comfort and luxury—a sprawling bungalow, chauffeur-driven cars, security personnel, a fleet of servants. He gained authority and power. But material gains didn’t bring him fulfilment or satisfaction. The more he had, the more he felt worthless. He spent harrowing, sleepless nights desperate to cross the chasm between what he is and what he wants to become.

His heart beat for the poor, the needy, those at the fringes, the underprivileged, the battered, the tribal woman who was raped; the pregnant adolescent married off at a tender age; the tenth grader who topped the district but soon fell into bad company and died a few years later of liver cirrhosis. He thought of all those women beaten by their inebriated husbands; of children whose future was stunted by poverty and of those that wanted to study but had to help eke out a living.

During the Telangana movement for a separate State, he had led the operation to quell the agitating students at Osmania University. During the day, he controlled and suppressed their activities; but during the evenings he would find himself in a tea stall engrossed in intense conversations with the same students to understand the core issues facing the youth. He learned two important things about these students: poverty and hopelessness. The rural youth had fire in their belly, big dreams in their eyes; they had knowledge and ambition. But poverty thwarted them from moving forward and the State machinery failed to give them jobs. And thus, the dissonance with the State and its institutions. He loathed himself for being a part of this same system!

This awakening was a decisive moment. He took study leave and joined the Harvard University for a Masters Program in Public Administration.

He met and interacted with a lot of people from different parts of the world. He realized that these were people who had wrenched themselves out of the circle of petty materialistic fulfilment; found their true calling; they were working for a greater purpose; a purpose that contributed to the upliftment of humanity; to reach out to larger populations and that had made a difference to their lives.

Life is not all that hopeless.

He remembered telling himself one night. He regained confidence.

He had found his purpose. He knew he could start afresh.

He still spent sleepless nights; but not in torment or guilt. But in chalking out a roadmap to achieve his vision.

Memories of his childhood hit him very often. His village near Achampet in Telangana frequently rose before his eyes. A few incidents from childhood had been etched in his memory. He remembered overhearing his father, a school teacher, hurtfully telling his mother about being asked to clear his leaf-plate ( istaraaku) in a social gathering only because he was an ‘untouchable’. Praveen was slapped once by his teacher for accidentally touching his new shirt. He was made to sit on the back bench because the front benches were reserved for the upper caste boys. During his growing years, the pain and humility made him vengeful. Fortunately, he had been able to channelize his energies to excel in his education and profession. But he was always plagued by guilt because equality and justice were still a far cry for most of his brethren.

After his Masters at Harvard, he returned to his homeland with a crystal clear vision. He sought an appointment with the Chief Minister. He requested the Chief Minister to provide him an opportunity to serve in the Social Welfare Department. He explained that he could serve the country better in this department, of which he was a beneficiary too. Yes, he was a student of the Social Welfare hostel during his school days.

What would a kakhi-clad gun-wielding cop do in the Social Welfare Department, was the question on the minds of both the departments. His request raised eyebrows in the bureaucratic circles. Only three friendly officers supported his decision. Fortunately, the Chief Minister gave his nod and granted the transfer.

After taking charge, he experienced immense resistance from the Teacher’s Union of Social Welfare Residential Schools. He called them for a meeting and explained that he volunteered for this post because he was committed to the cause of educating deprived children. Gradually he gained their trust.

Just when he thought he had settled down, he realized that he was not really in touch with the ground realities. Knowing is not the same as experiencing.

He visited a few schools over two weeks. His first school visit was a shocking experience. The schemes were in place, but poverty and discrimination were also still in place! He dug deep into the system to find the loopholes ailing the system. Discrimination continued to thrive in its ugly primitive form.

Most of the residential schools were very shabby. Only 8% of the schools had bare minimal infrastructure. The parents of the students were forgotten and disrespected. Teachers absolutely had no idea what to teach or how to teach. During one of the visits, an English teacher fainted because Praveen Kumar asked her to read the lesson out loud! He discovered that she had joined the school with a fake certificate.

The school kitchen was unhygienic and stank. The food was unpalatable. The children were gloomy, spiritless and weak–malnutrition written all over them. Sanitation and hygiene were extremely poor. The girls’ schools were worse off. The system had tolerated such extreme abuse for so many years! He was appalled. But his conviction to bring about a change only grew stronger.

That night he spoke to his family for over two hours at the dinner table. He explained how he felt. His wife, Laxmibai, understood. His little children couldn’t understand the intensity of the problem, but they understood their father’s turmoil. His wife accompanied him next day to one of the girls’ schools. He showed the despicable condition of the toilets. Nothing could be worse. No human being deserves to live in filth. His wife observed quietly.

On their way back, they hardly spoke to each other. The silence consumed their dinner-time as well. And then she said, ‘You are right, Praveen. You are working for an honourable cause. Just focus on them as a priority. They need help.’

Praveen started his work on a war footing. He went from one residential school to another, driven only by one vision: to give children quality education, holistic development, health and hygiene. Over the next six months, he hardly visited home. He travelled from one district to another, visiting schools, conducting audits, identifying lacunae, understanding problems, quantifying the support required and simultaneously acting upon it. Meanwhile, he introduced new programs. He encouraged the children to study and the teachers to teach. He became a tyrant for lazy teachers. For those teachers and officials who understood his intentions, he was a breath of fresh air. Gradually things started falling into place.

He organized an alumni meet. He was pained to find that most of them worked as janitors or occupied the lowest ranks, despite their good academic performance. He thus focused on the integrated growth of the children.

He introduced alternate education practices. He involved NGOs. He introduced chess, film-making and horse-riding. He introduced life-skills training programs such as gender sensitization, environmental awareness, and need for cleanliness and hygiene. He reopened the science symposiums and sports programs that had been scrapped fifteen years ago.

He was not surprised when he discovered that the tenure of the previous few secretaries was not more than three months. No wonder that the welfare system was ignored and the consequences glaringly visible in these schools, which impacted the lives of hundreds of children, whose parents had admitted them here, trusting the State machinery. He wanted to identify the specific interest and talent of every child and help them excel. He would not compromise; he would not give up until the children got what they deserved. He would ensure that every child evolved into an adult empowered to generate happiness within and around.

Despite poverty and dismal living standards, he noticed an undying spark in these children. Despite the ill care, the children had amazing survival instincts; despite malnutrition, they possessed raw energy. What a rare gift! – survival instinct and raw energy! The capital force for a successful sporting career, especially in adventure sports. Tapping these latent qualities and channelizing them appropriately is the way forward, he decided.

He soon identified a sports officer among the experienced Physical Directors of various residential schools. He went through their profiles, shortlisted and interviewed them. He was impressed with Mannan, a committed officer, who believed that games and sports promoted physical and mental health. Mannan’s thoughts aligned with his own vision for the Social Welfare System. He believed that children can perform better in academics, as sport induces discipline and body-mind balance. It releases the unrest and helps the children focus better on academics.

Praveen met his boss Raymond Peter, Principal Secretary of Social Welfare Department, a seasoned bureaucrat. Known to be a tech savvy officer, he had implemented technological initiatives in the Transport Department making it less corrupt, and people friendly. He continued the transparency drive even in the Social Welfare Department. Praveen proposed an adventure-sports program for the children. The ninth and the eleventh standard children could be chosen since the tenth, and the twelfth would be busy with their board exams. Raymond Peter liked the idea. He referred Sekhar Babu (the first South Indian to climb Mount Everest) who ran a school to train rock climbing enthusiasts.

Praveen spent three hours talking to Sekhar Babu to understand his worth as a ‘teacher’, especially for children with no background in rock climbing or mountaineering. Praveen knew the difference between being a successful mountaineer and a good trainer. No doubt Sekhar Babu is a world class mountaineer, but how good is he as an adventure sports teacher? Praveen preferred best teachers over best performers for training his children.

The interview soon turned into a discussion and Praveen asked questions to understand the sport, the potential and the scope better. After three hours of discussion, Praveen was convinced about Sekhar Babu’s passion, interest and abilities. There was a more important reason why Sekhar Babu was ideal for his children. He hailed from a modest background though not from the same social strata as the welfare school children. His father was an RTC bus driver who could barely make both ends meet with his earnings. Though he scaled Mount Everest and owned a rock climbing company called ‘Transcend Adventures’, he was unassuming and down to earth. He cared little about his appearance or physical grooming. (He was dressed casually and wore rubber chappals for the meeting.) Sekhar Babu wasn’t even trying to make a statement about himself through his clothes or appearance. His life revolved around mountaineering; the passion to kindle interest and groom youngsters in mountaineering. Praveen Kumar congratulated himself for investing his belief in Sekhar Babu.

He never revealed to Sekhar Babu that his boss Raymond Peter had referred him. The moment Sekhar Babu owned the students’ future and recommended them for higher courses, Praveen was glad that he had invested his belief in Sekhar Babu. The duo met Raymond Peter with a proposal in hand.

Praveen told Sekhar, ‘ Bhai, boss ko manaana tumhaara kaam hain.’ (Convincing my boss is your job.)

The moment Sekhar Babu stepped in along with Praveen, Raymond stretched out his hand and said, ‘ Kya bhai, kaise ho? Humaare bacchein kaise hain?’ (How are you? How are our children?).

Praveen enjoyed the animation on Sekhar Babu’s face.

‘Kya dekh rahe ho. Maine hi bheja tha tumhaare pass.’ (I was the one who sent him to you!)

It took a few seconds for Sekhar to comprehend the situation.

‘Sir, aap?’.

He looked at Praveen, ‘Sir, you should have told me. Peter was my boss as well.’

‘He knows,’ said Raymond Peter. ‘I told you, right? I referred you to Praveen Kumar. I told him that there is a crazy fellow called Sekhar Babu who left his job as an Assistant General Manager in Andhra Pradesh Tourism Department to teach rock climbing.’

Sekhar Babu worked in Andhra Pradesh Tourism (then non-bifurcated) and reported to Raymond Peter who was Managing Director of Andhra Pradesh Tourism Department.

With the support of Raymond Peter, Sekhar Babu and Mannan, Praveen Kumar achieved the singular feat of successfully sending the children of Welfare Residential Schools to summit Mount Renock.

While Raymond Peter helped by giving administrative approval, Mannan and Sekhar Babu executed the mission. Mannan convinced the teachers and principals of the various schools about the positive effects of sports in general and mountaineering in particular. He also convinced parents about the importance of sports and assured the safety and well-being of their children. He motivated the Physical Education Directors and Physical Education Trainers to enrol their two best students for the training. Sekhar Babu totally owned his dream of training the students to be the best. What gave Praveen Kumar the confidence in Sekhar Babu was the fact that Sekhar Babu was as crazy as he was. He would do anything to pursue his passion and a cause in which he believed.

During his journey in the Social Welfare Department, Praveen Kumar examined the term Dalit that referred to the deprived caste of the country. He was aghast to learn that it meant ‘broken/scattered’. Are these people really broken and scattered? If broken, who broke them and what makes them broken? Is it the body, confidence or the soul? Why did they allow themselves to be broken? Praveen wanted to give a name that is empowering, emphasizing self-reliance rather than past victimization.

Thus, Swaeroes was born. SW stands for Social Welfare and aeros (in Greek) means flying in the sky, indicating the sky being the limit for achievement. He framed a few guiding principles. He spent time with a lot of people for several days and came up with the Ten Commandments of Swaeroes.

1. I am not inferior to anyone.

2. I shall be the leader wherever I am.

3. I shall do what I love, and be different.

4. I shall always think big and aim high.

5. I shall be honest, hardworking and punctual.

6. I shall never blame others for my failures.

7. I shall never beg and cheat.

8. I shall repay what I borrow.

9. I shall never fear the unknown.

10. I shall never give up.

Swaeroes and their Ten Commandments were launched on 22nd October 2012 at Ravindrabharathi. The day was significant because it was the birth anniversary of Mr. S.R. Sankaran, the famous IAS Officer, who dedicated his life to the emancipation of the marginalized from the yoke of slavery. He fought against the jogini system (a religious practice in which young girls are ‘married’ to Gods and their life is dedicated to prostitution as an occupation. Usually, girls from the scheduled castes are made ‘joginis’.). Child labor and caste discrimination. He remained single and donated his entire pension to the most marginalized children.

He sent invites to all the Swaeroe alumni. He created a self-declaration and the Swaeroes oath. Membership to the Swaeroes community was open for all, provided they met a few requirements and participated in an oath-taking ceremony.

Swaeroes! He said to himself. The sky is the limit!

What distinguishes the privileged from the underprivileged? Praveen knows the answer:

OPPORTUNITY.

Opportunities can be created. I will create them. I will go to any length to create opportunities and show the world that given opportunities, anybody can do anything. The one other requirement, besides opportunity, is WILL POWER.

My Swaeroes have abundant will power. They have just proved it beyond all doubt.

I will send them to Mount Everest.

Dear Mount Everest! My Swaeroes will soon be visiting you!

On Testing Grounds

20 November 2013
9.30 am
Secunderabad Railway Station

The train chugged to a halt amidst announcements of arrivals and departures.

Passengers poured out of the doors like ants spilling out of their holes. The children were eager to return home after a long, exciting journey to the lap of the Himalayas. They were not the same anymore. They returned with renewed energy, enthusiasm and a sense of new-found self-confidence. While most children of their age are engrossed in grooming themselves or fighting over petty things, here were the Swaeroes, returning after a glimpse of the sublime at a tender age.

Parmesh took attendance while Sekhar Babu helped them with their luggage. They stepped on to the platform carrying their luggage.

The platform suddenly drowned in the jolly rhythms of drums. Anand dropped his luggage and craned his neck to see what was happening. To his amusement, he saw a music band –children in uniform playing different instruments. He grinned and waved animatedly at a familiar face: Praveen Kumar stood with the band. He waved back. Anand started dancing to the beats of the drum. The children waved at Praveen Kumar and joined Anand in the dance. They were overwhelmed by this very warm and special welcome. Poorna, shy as she was, remained at the back; her face animated by a wide grin and twinkling eyes. The children were garlanded and felicitated at the station. Sweets were distributed.

Praveen Kumar turned toward his young achievers and signalled the band to stop playing.

‘I am with a bunch of celebrities!! Your achievement is no mean feat! There’s a surprise waiting for you. You have an important meeting coming up with someone very special. Any guesses?’

The children exchanged looks.

‘The honourable Chief Minister wishes to meet you in person!’

The children were dumb struck. They looked at each other in disbelief.

‘Day after tomorrow, you have an appointment with the Chief Minister at his office. He wishes to talk to you. Isn’t that wonderful?’

‘That’s not all. Get ready for another set of interviews. The channels are planning to make a documentary on your achievements. It will be telecast on V6, Sony, E TV, Sakshi TV,’ Mannan, the Sports Officer added.

As the news began to sink in, the children cheered and clapped.

With a sudden explosion, the drum began to beat again and picked up pace while the children danced with gay abandon.

The next day, the media was abuzz with reports of the success of the Swaeroes.

24 November 2013
Chief Minister’s Office, Hyderabad

The children looked fresh and smart in their blazers. They were accompanied by Sekhar Babu, Parmesh and Mannan. Parmesh whispered: back erect, shoulders upright and chin up.

When Praveen Kumar saw them, he knew the difference. They were transformed. They easily made eye-contact and they bore a demeanour that exuded self-assuredness, self-esteem and self-respect.

Little Ambedkars, Praveen Kumar said to himself.

‘So guys, are you ready to rock?’

‘Yes, Sir!’

They were ushered into the conference room. The children were wide eyed and quiet. They were mesmerized by the grand interiors of the conference room.

Poorna knew this was a very prestigious and important meeting. Not everybody gets an audience with the Chief Minister!

Parmesh briefed the children on the code of conduct, knowing very well that they needed no briefing or monitoring. They were far too mature for their age, and discipline had become a way of life.

Chief Minister, Kiran Kumar Reddy, entered the conference hall accompanied by Raymond Peter, Principal Secretary and flanked by gunmen. All of them stood up. The Chief Minister gave a warm smile and asked them to sit down. The children were smiling from ear to ear.

Praveen Kumar briefed the Chief Minister about the expedition undertaken by the children. He explained that the children were shortlisted based on their performance during the rock climbing course; performance criteria included physical stamina, emotional endurance, self-discipline and team behaviour. He showed photographs of the children scaling Mount Renock. He explained the environmental challenges they faced and how they cleared each hurdle effortlessly, despite their tender age.

‘Wonderful! Congratulations! I am really proud of you,’ he said.

‘Thank you, Sir’.

‘So, what is your name?’ the Chief Minister pointed to one of the students.

‘Anand, Sir.’

‘Anand, tell me about yourself. Where do you come from, and what do your parents do?’

‘Sir, I am from Kaliveru village. My father’s name is Kondal Rao and mother’s name is Laxmi. My mother is an Anganwadi helper in our village. Father works as a mechanic in a local cycle shop. My brother is in the fifth class. I am studying in first year Inter in Annapureddypalli Social Welfare Residential School in Khammam, Sir.’

He exuded confidence and self-assurance. Praveen Kumar beamed with pride. Interacting with new people had certainly given the children a sense of personal identity.

‘So what sport do you play?’

‘All kinds, Sir. Kabaddi, kho-kho, athletics. I am a champion in my school, Sir!’ he beamed.

‘Champion? Great!’

He addressed Satya Rao now. ‘At what level do you compete?’

Satya Rao hesitated.

‘That’s okay, tell me,’ the Chief Minister encouraged.

‘Sir, I am a State level athlete.’

‘Great, most of you are into sports.’

‘Sir, in fact, all the children here excel in sports,’ said Raymond Peter.

Praveen Kumar introduced each student, highlighting their specific skills, competence and endurance.

‘I’m glad there are so many girls in this program. So how was the experience?’ He asked Abhilasha.

Abhilasha’s face flushed with the attention focused on her.

‘It was really good, Sir. We climbed 16,500 feet.’

‘Wonderful! So this is the first time you saw snow-capped mountains! How was the view of Kanchenjunga range?’

The children were quiet for a few seconds as they recalled the magnificent views. Their eyes lit up. The majestic ranges and the powerful impact it had had on them gave them goose bumps. And then, everyone started talking at once.

‘Sir, you should see to believe.’

‘It’s paradise on Earth, Sir.’

‘I felt I was in another land altogether. It is an out-of-the-world experience,’

The Chief Minister smiled. He asked the shy girl with bright shining eyes, ‘What did you feel?’

Poorna’s face was animated, ‘Sir, the mountains are so enormous that I can gaze at them forever. The snow ranges are never ending. It was very calm, and I felt very tiny, Sir.’

That’s philosophical! Thought Praveen Kumar.

The conference room filled with excitement and energy.

Parmesh had to hush the children to lower their voices.

Sarita continued, ‘Sir, the view of the Kanchenjunga range from Tiger Hill is mesmerizing. And then, to actually climb one of those distant mountains…That was very thrilling, Sir.’

Chief Minister, Kiran Kumar remarked, ‘That must have been a great feeling.’

The children said in unison, ‘Yes, Sir.’

‘I have never felt this happy and proud of myself, Sir,’ said Nagaraju his voice quivering.

Praveen Kumar whispered to Raymond Peter, ‘Sir, this is the right time to propose the Mount Everest Expedition.’

‘No. Not now. It’s too early. Let us wait a little longer.’

The meeting that was scheduled for ten minutes stretched to forty-five minutes.

‘What did you gain from this expedition?’

Poorna thought that this was a strange question.

So what did I gain?

How can someone ask, what is the use of climbing?

Do we wonder similarly about cricket? Or science or dance or any discipline for that matter?

Then why climbing? What do we gain?

Poorna felt unsettled.

‘We gained confidence, Sir,’ Anand replied. ‘Climbing a mountain of 17,000 feet from sea level .…we did it. We are confident that we can accomplish any task with hard work.’

Everybody clapped.

Praveen’s happiness knew no bounds. These guys are remarkable.

Soon after the Chief Minister’s meet, the Deputy Chief Minister Damodar Rajanarasimha invited all the children to his residence for dinner. He felicitated the twenty children and appreciated them for their success.

‘What is the best method to assess an individual’s ability to climb Mount Everest?’ Praveen Kumar asked Sekhar Babu over tea.

‘A trekking expedition to the mountains during extreme winter is the best option. That would be a good opportunity to assess physical fitness, mental tenacity and survival instincts.’

‘Hmm. Give me a list of ten children who you think can go to the next level. You can ask HMI to help us with the selection process?’

‘Okay, Sir... Par Sir , budget?’

‘Don’t worry about that. We have sufficient funds in the Welfare Department budget itself. Identifying the right candidates is the priority now.’

‘And Everest?’

‘We will work that out later. First, let us see how the children will shape up.’

Sekhar Babu and Parmesh drew up a list of ten children based on the review report from HMI. The list included four girls - Poorna, Bharathi, Sarita, Roja and, six boys - Anand, Gangadhar, Satya Rao, Madhukar, Mohan Prasad and Nagaraju.

Sekhar invited the ten children for a discussion. He proposed the Mount Everest expedition plan. In preparation for the expedition, the children would first embark on a two-week expedition to Ladakh.

The children let out a collective gasp of excitement. Poorna was ready to start tomorrow if need be! They shot a volley of questions to Sekhar Babu. He answered each question patiently. He also mentioned that the Ladakh Winter Expedition would help draw up a final list of the best climbers for the Everest expedition.

He then said, in a serious tone, ‘Praveen Sir is trying to give you an opportunity, few children of your age can hope for this. He is risking his own job and reputation. If you want to achieve something great in this lifetime, this is the opportunity. This is the path for a better, brighter future, not just for you, but for future generations. Make the most of it. Give it your best shot.’

Praveen requested Wing Commander Sridharan to join the expedition as Ladakh is governed by the Ministry of Defence. Defence personnel in the expedition team would help in getting clearances and other support.

The pre-Ladakh Winter Expedition training was to be held at Gowlidoddi.’ The children were housed at the Girls’ College at Gowlidoddi, the Magnet School and the IIT-Medical Academy Junior College. Their academics were also taken care of since the children would attend Gowlidoddi Village Welfare Residential School and Training sessions would be conducted on the grounds of the school.

Physical trainers monitored the diet and physical fitness of the children. Venugopal, the Yoga instructor, conducted ‘Art of Living Course for Children’, which included asanas for flexibility and strength; breathing exercises to enhance lung power and prepare the body for efficient breathing at higher altitudes; and, Suryanamaskara for mind and body balance.

In the meantime, Roja, whose mountaineering techniques were by far the best had a medical problem. She had to leave the training mid-way. The trainers and the children were disappointed. Poorna missed Roja the most.

One day, amidst training sessions, Sekhar Babu informed the children that they would be driving down to Hyderabad to meet someone special. The children learnt that a super achiever was being felicitated at the Ramakrishna Mission Ashram in Gandhinagar locality in Hyderabad.

The children arrived at the Ashram. In the auditorium, on the dais were seated a few people. The hall was brimming with audience. As the program began, the lady who sat on the dais was welcomed and introduced.

The children were stunned by her story. A national-level volley ball player, she was pushed out of a moving train by thieves. She was thrown on to the parallel track. She lay there while another train from the opposite direction ran over her leg. Her left leg had to be amputated to prevent gangrene, and a steel rod had to be inserted in her right leg to hold the shattered bones together. Two years after the accident, she summited the Everest to become the first woman in the world with a prosthetic leg to scale Mount Everest!

The first female amputee to climb the Mount Everest – Ms. Arunima Sinha, they announced. The crowd burst into applause.

‘Oh! Chekkakaalu,’ (colloquial expression for a prosthetic leg) the children whispered among themselves.

Poorna was awestruck!

She observed Arunima intently.

Arunima was dressed in formal pants, shirt and shoes. No disability was apparent. She was calm and composed and had a steady expression. Her face expressed contentment, and her body exuded sheer confidence. Nothing about her sought pity or sympathy.

What made Arunima summit the Everest? Is it her own steely resolve? Poorna wondered .

The children were introduced to Arunima. Each of them shook hands with her. Poorna wanted to say a few words of praise and gratitude, but she fell silent.

It was time to return to their camp at Gowlidoddi. Walking out of the Aashram, Poorna swore that she would never quit until she accomplished her goal. No matter what!

There was very little time left for the expedition. Sekhar Babu had a lot of work on his hands. Foremost, he would have to book tickets to Leh. The first leg of the journey would be from Secunderabad to Delhi by train, and the last from Delhi to Leh city by air. Praveen Kumar requested the Department of Railways through a committed senior Railway official Mr. Bharat Bhushan to book a separate cabin for the children under the emergency quota.

The children would be flying in an aircraft for the first time. This is indeed a historic event in the annals of Welfare Schools. Praveen was overwhelmed.

The children were delighted to receive their passports, a prerequisite, to visit Leh. So far, the ration card was their only prized possession. The tour to the local police station to collect their passports in their native villages was a matter of great pride. These children were the first from any Social Welfare Residential Schools to hold passports. Although many alumni held passports, they only travelled to the Gulf countries to do menial jobs.

The contingent of nine Swaeroes with their trainers Srilatha, Parmesh and Sekhar Babu reached Delhi by AP Express on the morning of 27th December 2013. Wing Commander Sridharan joined them in Delhi. On the morning of the 29th, they took a GoAir flight to Leh from Delhi. After the first train journey just two months ago, now they were experiencing their first air journey.

Sekhar Babu clicked pictures of the children in the airport and next to the aircraft and shared them with Praveen Kumar through WhatsApp.

They have come this far. They will go further to conquer the world and carve a better future for themselves, he thought .

Despite their excitement, the children appeared extremely composed. However, their curiosity was irrepressible. They explored every nook and corner of the flight. From the runway to the washroom, everything was new.

For Poorna, the take-off was a breathtaking moment. She felt butterflies in her stomach. Sarita and Poorna held each other’s hands and smiled sheepishly.

Once airborne, the aircraft cruised smoothly. Poorna looked out of the window. It was indeed exhilarating to be high up above in the air like a bird!

Anand’s joy knew no bounds. He remembered watching airplanes as they zipped overhead in the open skies, while he grazed his uncle’s cattle in the meadows. And today, he is travelling in one of them to Ladakh! He was certain that none in his village knew that such a place existed in India. Not that he had heard of Ladakh until a few weeks ago!

Parmesh and Sekhar Babu relaxed in their seats.

29 December 2013
Leh city, Ladakh

The team along with Wing Commander Sridharan landed in Leh city, in the Ladakh region of the State of Jammu and Kashmir, the perfect location for a winter trekking expedition.

This expedition would help the trainers assess the cold-bearing capacity and the survival instincts of the children. It would give them an insight into the emotional stamina of the children at higher altitudes and cold temperatures, which is extremely important for mountaineering.

Ladakh, which literally means, ‘the land of high passes’ is a region that lies at an altitude of more than 3,000 meters. It is one of the most picturesque mountain regions in the world. The region is spread over the north-eastern part of the State of Jammu-Kashmir. Leh, at an altitude of 3,500 meters, is the largest city in the Ladakh region, inhabited mostly by Shia Muslims and Tibetan Buddhists. The average winter temperature of Leh is about a maximum of 10°C and a minimum of -20°C. It is called a cold dessert, as greenery is scarce with vast and versatile shades of brown lands dappled with patches of snow here and there.

The first three days at Leh were reserved for acclimatization. Although the sky was clear during the day, the average temperature remained at 0°C.

They went around the city of Leh – to the market, the army office, the Leh Lake and other tourist places. They bought camping equipment and some other essentials for the forthcoming treks. For the first time they would be sleeping in tents.

Poorna noticed that there were no straight roads; only roads that coiled around the snow covered hills.

Shekar took the children over what seemed like a thick sheet of glass. The children hesitated to step on it, lest it should break!

‘Sir, what really is this?’

‘Take a guess, Poorna.’

‘You are standing on the frozen Lake of Leh.’

The children then looked more closely to find tiny puddles beneath cracks, which were the only proof that it was indeed a frozen lake! They also discovered that the ice rink upon which a few people were skating at a little distance was also a frozen lake! They were amused to hear that at times, the drain water, the tap water and even the rivers froze. Despite the low temperatures, the local people were clad in regular clothes, apart from a sweater and cap for warmth. The children were amused that an egg, when dropped from a height, couldn’t break, and cutting a potato with a knife was equal to sawing dry wood!

The 31st of December 2013 turned out to be a fun filled experience for the children. They celebrated the Losar festival in Ladakh city. The King made an appearance before the public and participated in the celebrations. The city looked colourful in the festive atmosphere, and the children enjoyed watching fire stunts performed all over the city.

Although Sekhar Babu had planned a trek to Stok Kangri, the highest mountain in the Stok Range of the Himalayas in the Ladakh region, the idea was dropped due to rough weather and heavy snowfall. Instead, they decided to camp at Gyamsa (4,100 meters), 25 km from and 500 meters above Leh. This was their first experience of organized camping.

The first day of 2014 found the children in a valley near Khardung La, where they camped overnight. The temperature after sunset dropped to below -30˚C. Three male sherpas and one female sherpa were hired to assist them. While at Leh, they had shopped for camping equipment. A low lying area was chosen for pitching the tent, so it would be protected from strong winds and landslides. The children learnt to pitch and build their own tents. They drilled the pegs into the ground and fastened the tent ropes around them. A typical tent accommodated three people.

Sekhar Babu insisted that the children clothed themselves in four layers – thermal wear, feather jacket, fleece jacket and a windproof suit. At night, they ended up wearing more layers to remain warm, in addition to the mandatory woollen socks, gloves and caps. They spent the night in sleeping bags, which kept them warm. Sleeping bags are designed to bear temperature of -10, -20, -30˚C and so on.

Every day after 7 am, the children, the sherpas and Sekhar Babu would go trekking and return only by 4 pm. They would have dinner by 6.30 in the evening, as the nights are very long and the days are short in Leh. After dinner, they played or indulged in some entertainment activity in the dining tent and hit the bed by 8 pm. The children would fall asleep instantly, for they would be exhausted from trekking all day.

The trekking routes were designed to take them 500-600 meters above Leh city, which landed them at 4,600 meters above sea level.

Once, while on Kharmulah road, they ran short of water and had to melt ice for potable water. This then became a regular affair. Melting ice gave them more water than melting snow. Wing Commander Sridharan explained the concept of density to the children. About 2 kilos of snow yielded one cup of water whereas the same quantity of ice gave them 3 cups of water.

During the treks, they would hit long tracts of land covered in snow. The children would then change into snow boots from trekking shoes. They also had to remove their thermal wear while hiking, because the heat generated from body movement would remain trapped and cause excessive sweating, which in turn would lead to dehydration and exhaustion. However, as soon as they returned to the camping site, they would change back into thermal wear to prevent hypothermia, a condition in which body heat is lost very quickly, resulting in dangerously low body temperatures.

Communicating with the children was a tough task for Sridharan. Shekar Babu and Parmesh doubled as interpreters. Poorna as always took time to warm up to the Commander.

Parmesh and Sekhar Babu observed the children closely all the time; not to assess conscious performance, but to assess their constitutional strength and survival instincts.

They maintained notes: Who exhibits leadership qualities? Who is quick to find solutions? Who gives up easily? Who helps others? Who is organized and efficient?

Sound sleep is a sign of wellness, especially in the mountains. In higher altitude, the air pressure is 30% lesser. The heart works harder to pump in more oxygen into the blood. Blood pressure and pulse rate increase. This body process continues even in sleep. If the body fails to take in enough oxygen, the brain cannot relax, and sleep is often disturbed. Undisturbed, sound sleep is a sign that the body has adapted to the high altitude and that it is getting sufficient oxygen.

To test the efficacy with which the body was adapting, Parmesh had devised a simple technique. He would randomly call out the names of the children during sleep.

‘Satya Rao.’

‘Yes, Sir!’ He responded from another tent.

«Sarita…»

‘Haan, Sir.’

‘Anand.’

Silence.

‘Anand,’ A little louder this time.

Silence.

‘Poorna.’

Silence.

‘Poorna.’

Only the murmur of deep, long breathing.

No response is a good response.

Parmesh was happy to note that most children had acclimatized well to the weather.

On the 4th of January, the contingent returned to Leh and headed to Khardung La Pass, at 18,300 feet above sea level, in the Karakoram Range. They had trekked almost 17,500 feet when they realized that the route was under repair and the consequent possibility of landslides. So they returned to Leh.

The next day they headed to Pangong Lake in a 16-seater van. En route, near Chang La pass, they stopped for tea at Tsoltak Lake. The children loved to have tea in small tea stalls on winding roads amidst luxurious snow cover. Besides, sipping on steaming tea every now and then was a necessity in the cold, damp climate to pull up their spirits. The children climbed back into the vehicle.

‘Arre, eh kya kiya maine!’ (Oh! What did I do?) The driver sighed. He turned the ignition key several times, but the van only made a clicking sound and didn’t start up.

‘Oh! What happened, Sir?’ Anand asked.

Sekhar Babu explained, ‘The driver switched off the engine by mistake. At these temperatures, if the engine is not running, the diesel freezes. Drivers generally do not turn off the engine during short stops.’

As much as the driver tried, the vehicle would not start. Since traction is very low on snow surfaces, the driver put snow chains to the wheels of the van as a precaution to prevent the vehicle from slipping.

The children huddled inside the van. Parmesh and Wing Commander Sridharan were making rounds to beat the cold. Sekhar Babu and the driver were trying different ways and means to defreeze the diesel in the engine.

A slow-moving army truck pulled up to the side, and a few army men got off the vehicle.

‘Kahan jana…?’ (where are you headed?) they asked in a familiar accent. They belonged to the Madras (Chennai) Regiment. Most of them hailed from Telangana. They invited the children to their camp. The entire contingent climbed into the army van.

Bharathi, however, didn’t get off the van.

‘Come on, beta. Get down,’ Paramesh called out to her. But she didn’t move. She was shivering vigorously.

Parmesh cajoled her again. She was adamant. Her lips were trembling.

‘No. No. I won’t,’ she managed to say amidst gasps.

‘I won’t come, you go ahead with your Everest expedition. I won’t come.’

Paramesh went into the van and sat next to her. It took a lot of talking to get her out of the van and into the army truck.

The children were obviously worried and tensed, Sekhar explained, ‘You already know atmospheric pressure reduces at high altitudes. The lungs have to work harder to take in more oxygen. And when the lungs are unable to do so, the reduced intake of oxygen affects the brain. Brain function slows down.’

Sekhar always gave children as much information as possible. These were life lessons. Besides, this is the best way to prepare the children, since the Everest Expedition was to be scheduled shortly.

The army men were pleased to have these little children as their guests and offered them chocolates. They opened a 15 kg carton of raisins and asked them to take as many as they wished.

Parmesh remembered that the children hadn’t had their lunch. The lunch they had carried in their hot bags had frozen. Sekhar requested the army men to heat up their lunch in the army kitchen. The frozen food clacked in the hot vessel like marbles on a tile floor.

Meanwhile, the army men placed chains around the wheels of their vans for better grip on the snowy road. After a few hours of effort, the diesel liquefied and the engine started. As the route to Pangong Lake was closed, the team visited a temple at Chang La pass, but everyone reminded the driver to keep the engine on! Tired of hearing their constant reminders, he glared at the children in mock anger. The children burst out laughing. They enjoyed bullying the driver.

The children returned after praying and taking ‘ Prasad’ and having tea. Although it was nearly an hour, the engine was kept running. They did not want another dreadful cold day.

The Ladakh Winter Expedition served several purposes. It helped children overcome the fear of cold. They learnt to walk in snow. They spent the nights in sleeping bags and tents. The coaches were able to test their tolerance levels and capacities.

Pushing the Boundaries

20 January 2014
11.30 am
Office of the Principal Secretary, Social Welfare Department, Andhra Pradesh

‘Praveen, what is this?’ Raymond Peter asked, pointing to the file on his table.

‘Sir, that’s the proposal to send the children to the Everest.’

‘I know. I know, Praveen. But do you understand where we are heading?’

‘Yes, Sir.’

‘The expeditions so far have been a big success. You provided the children with a wonderful opportunity at an early age. This is a dream for course mountaineers across the world. Don’t you think that the Ladakh expedition is success enough for the children?’

‘Sir, I believe the children can scale greater heights. I see immense potential.’

‘These children don’t have to prove anything to anyone. You have gone crazy. Sending them to the DEATH ZONE!’ he said sternly.

Raymond stood up from his chair and walked toward Praveen Kumar. In a low voice, he said, ‘Do you not understand? There is no scope for such crazy thoughts. These are very young children. This is literally a matter of life and death! Lives are at stake, Praveen. It’s too risky.’

‘I know, Sir. I am aware. I know that I would be stoned to death if something goes wrong. I know that all of them are minors. And the government will be held responsible if something goes wrong.’

Raymond Peter paced back and forth.

‘Something? Everything is wrong. Nothing is right. You want to risk these young lives?’

‘Praveen, please understand. I know...I know that you’ve invested a lot of conviction here. But this is not going to work. If I pass this proposal, I will be putting you in a tight spot. You may lose your job.’

Praveen Kumar had expected this reaction from his boss.

‘Sir, you have belief in my conviction. Then, why not try?’ he said in a very relaxed tone. ‘Sir, I know that we both believe in creating opportunities for our children. Why should we hold ourselves back? They have it in them, Sir. They can touch the DEATH ZONES.’

Raymond Peter pulled out the proposal from the file and read it. He signed and submitted the file to the government.

However, the government rejected the proposal. Word spread among official circles of the Department of Welfare.

One of Praveen’s colleagues said, ‘It is foolish to spend this kind of money on these few children. There are a lot of schools that need better infrastructure – toilets, classrooms, desks, library…’

True. But how about making an inspiring story that could emancipate and liberate the underprivileged from the yoke of slavery? This was Praveen’s argument.

Raymond Peter forwarded the file to the Finance Department, but in vain. Then he sent it to the Sports Department.

The Sports Department said: It is our duty. Why are you doing it?

Exactly! Why are we doing it instead of the Sports department? History has an answer to this question!

‘Bacchon ke saath panga kyon lena?. (Why take a chance with children?) Send them to a few more rock-climbing courses, forest trecks or hikes. Bacche hain na?’ (They are kids, after all!).

The proposal was met with resistance from all quarters. Praveen Kumar’s conviction didn’t wane. It only grew stronger. However, Managing Director of Sports Authority of Andhra Pradesh, Rahul Bojja gauged the potential of the mission. He was also perhaps influenced by the values instilled by his activist father. His positive remarks on the expedition worked in Praveen Kumar’s favour.

After he received the necessary approval, Praveen met Raymond Peter. He said, ‘I will take complete responsibility, sir.’

Raymond Peter sighed. ‘Right, Praveen. I hope you understand. If everything goes well, you win. Else, the sword will fall on your neck.’

‘I am prepared to put my head on the block. I know it’s worth the risk. This expedition will be successful, and the country will be proud, and it will go down in history.’

Praveen met Shamsher Singh Rawat, Secretary to the Chief Minister, another tech savvy, out of the box thinker. Rawat’s relatives, hailing from the Himalyan State of Uttarakhand, had scaled Mount Everest long ago.

Rawat was well informed about Praveen; his origins in the Police Department; the voluntary transfer to the Welfare Department and his achievements so far; and now, this craze that has gotten hold of him. Rawat had accompanied the Chief Minister on his visit to the Social Welfare Schools and had seen first-hand the progress made under Praveen’s leadership.

Rawat was astute. He was discerning. He advised the Chief Minister, ‘The children must go, Sir. I have not seen another officer so keen on creating history with such young children and especially from the underprivileged background. The children truly deserve this opportunity. And we have enough evidence to prove their physical fitness and mental tenacity.’

The Chief Minister, a sports person himself, approved the proposal.

Raymond Peter called Praveen Kumar and Sekhar Babu to his office.

‘So, gentlemen, here is what you have been waiting for.’

He handed them the Government Order.

‘Congratulations! This is a moment to celebrate… your commitment and perseverance.’

Praveen read the Government Order.

To

The Secretary,

Praveen reread it.

To

The Secretary,

This can’t be, he thought. This is a breach of protocol. There can never be such a glaring error in a Government Order.

He raised his head and said, ‘Sir…’

He stopped midway, murmuring, ‘Oh! Okay. Okay. The letter is addressed directly to me instead of the Principal Secretary. I get it now. No one should be held responsible for my madness.’ He nodded dramatically.

He showed the Government Order to Sekhar Babu.

Sekhar Babu frowned.

‘Only for two! Not for four?’

Poorna, Anand, Satya Rao and Gangadhar were selected after the winter expedition. The rest of the children quit voluntarily, or their parents refused to allow them to proceed further.

‘Yes. Only for two. We were advised to invest all our focus on two than four for best outcomes. The budget is R 69 lakhs. That’s enough for two children.’

‘So, I have to choose one of the three boys.’

‘Yes.’

‘Yeh kya hain, (What is this?) Sir? The other two boys will be heart broken.’

‘I know. But there’s not much we can do about it. One girl one boy.

Sekhar Babu pitied the boys.

I will ensure the other two boys will also make it to the Everest. Everest is there forever. If not now, then next year...

‘Sekhar, I really, deeply wish that our children summit the Everest!’

‘Your commitment and enthusiasm have rubbed off on me too,’ Sekhar Babu said. ‘It’s my dream, too; to see that the children succeed. They must become a model for inspiration,’ he said in a tone of sincerity and resolve.

‘Sekhar…. you may not stand to benefit in monetary terms, you know…’

Noticing the fine lines of worry and concern on Praveen’s forehead, ‘Sir,’ interrupted Sekhar. ‘Your interest is in creating opportunities for the underprivileged. My interest is in promoting mountaineering. The world must know that the sublime experience of mountaineering is unparalleled.’

They shared a moment of heavy silence.

‘I will take leave now. I will keep you updated, Sir.’

He went straight to see Parmesh. He was planning a thorough evaluation of each of the three boys.

Poorna couldn’t be dropped for two reasons. Her inclusion would establish gender parity. But the more important reason was that despite being younger than the boys, she had shown superior performance throughout the program.

Praveen Kumar and Raymond Peter were left alone in the room. They looked at each other. ‘Congratulations!’ they said at the same time.

That evening Praveen and Raymond Peter received an SMS from Sekhar Babu.

‘Anand and Poorna – finalists.’

‘Poorna,’ the class teacher called out. Poorna was busy copying notes. ‘This circular says that you have to be sent to Hyderabad for training.’

Poorna instantly knew that this was related to the Everest Expedition. ‘Poorna, you are selected for the Everest Expedition.’

Poorna’s joy was expressed only through her bright, twinkling eyes.

Toughening Up for the Heights

5 February 2014
5.00 am
Gowlidoddi, IIT-Medicom Training Academy

Two pairs of feet moved rhythmically on the tracks of the field. The bright halogen lights tracked them by their shadows. Poorna and Anand, the finalists for the Himalayan Expedition jogged for a couple of rounds and did a few stretches to loosen their muscles. The warm up was followed by yoga, under the instructions of Venugopal. The yoga session included Pranayama (breathing exercises), twelve cycles of Suryanamaskara and a few asanas (Yoga postures) to enhance flexibility, balance and awareness of their bodies. The morning session concluded with ten minutes of Shavasana (Corpse pose) for body relaxation and a twenty-minute meditation session for calming the mind.

After breakfast, by 8.30 am Poorna would rush to Magnet School and Anand to IIT-Medicom Training Academy and Junior College, which were adjacent to each other. Poorna and her trainer Srilatha lodged at Magnet School while Anand was at IIT-Medicom Training Academy

They would return at 3.30  pm to their respective accommo dations. After having light refreshments, they joined Parmesh for the evening workout: warm up, stretching, jogging and two rounds of 200 meters.

The morning and evening workout remained the same, except for jogging and sprinting. Each morning, they jogged twice as many rounds as the previous day. An extra round of sprinting was added every day for three days. No additions were made over the next four days. Then a round was added every day for another four days. This pattern continued until 120 rounds were covered in an hour and a half. This entire exercise helped increase lung capacity. The evening workout was reduced to half of the morning routine. The yoga regimen and the stretches were, however repeated in the evening. The children also played a game of volleyball or kho- kho.

They also did several calf, shoulder and thigh strengthening exercises. They would run carrying weights in their backpacks. Apart from strengthening the back, this technique enhanced their capacity to breathe deep, in preparation to climb high altitudes with their ruck sacks. They wound up by 6.30 pm.

The week-end regimen was tougher. Parmesh would take Poorna and Anand to Bhongir rock. To strengthen their backs, the children with heavy weights in their rucksacks were made to run up and down the 550 feet at least thrice. They also played the role of belayers for climbers who were train ing at Bhongir rock. Belaying needs enormous shoulder strength. Although Poorna and Anand found the belaying exercise difficult in the beginning, they soon got accustomed to it.

Among all the exercises, ‘duck walk’ was the toughest. It enhances the dexterity of muscles and relaxes the legs after a strenuous workout. Softball practice strengthened the wrist, fingers and forearms – the key players in climbing.

Parmesh’s assistant Anil and residential school PET Srilatha monitored the training routine when Parmesh and Sekhar were busy with preparations for the expedition.

The children were on a special protein diet for muscle strengthening. Breakfast included milk and eggs. They had chicken for lunch or dinner. Fresh fruits such as banana, pomegranate, figs and dry fruits were part of their diet. Vitamin supplements were also provided.

Like most teenage children, Poorna resisted eating. She negotiated with Anand and Srilatha. Srilatha was very strict. She threatened that she would complain to Parmesh about her poor eating habits. Poorna was quite scared of Parmesh from the beginning. Yet, at times, when no one was watching, she would quickly transfer food from her plate to Anand’s plate. One day, she was caught red-handed. Since then, Srilatha made sure the two sat separately and sat right next to Poorna to ensure that she emptied her plate.

Anand and Poorna hardly knew each other before the Ladakh Winter Expedition. They bonded very well now and enjoyed each other’s company. Anand called her chinna (the sweet one, a term of endearment) and Poorna called him annayya (brother). They forged a mutually caring relationship.

After a couple of weeks, Parmesh introduced a new physical training technique to maximize their lung capacity. The children had to sprint 100 meters back and forth, followed by a few sit-ups; the next sprint would be followed by push-ups, knee squats and half squats. This cycle of exercise left the children completely drained and exhausted.

Breathing heavily and sweat trickling down her face, Poorna said, ‘ Annayya, do you really think we have to do so much?’

‘I wonder too, chinna. But they know better. Climbing Mount Everest is no child’s play.’

‘But climbing is easy annayya. We have climbed Mount Renock. This is just a few thousand meters higher.’

‘Well, you never know. The challenges may be different,’ Anand wiped the sweat off his brow.

The fitness levels and vitals were continuously monitored. At the beginning of the training program, Poorna weighed only 39 kg. By the end of the program, she had gained 10 to 11 kg.

One Saturday noon, Sekhar Babu and Parmesh came to meet the children. Parmesh carried a laptop. They showed the children photographs and videos of Mount Everest. Sekhar Babu briefed the students about the extreme conditions on Mount Everest. He spoke about the cold winds that swept at a speed of 150 km and the phenomena of landslides. He showed pictures of crevices, the huge gaps between two mountains and videos of how to cross crevices with the Atriar (the technical term for a sling ladder). He showed pictures of different types of frostbites – at the skin, muscle and bone levels. He gave tips on how to avoid frostbites.

Innocence breeds fearlessness in children. Children are less inhibited in trying out new things. But the same qualities must be tempered with knowledge. Otherwise, innocence and fearlessness can become detrimental to success and turn dangerous. Sekhar Babu believed that the children must be given all information about the challenges and dangers that they might encounter during their Mount Everest Expedition as well as preventive measures and precautions to be exercised. He took upon himself the onus to empower them with complete factual and relevant information. However, he was careful not to scare them. The possibility of accidents and death were looming large in his mind. But he was very positive and infused positivity in the children.

Sekhar Babu pointed to his trimmed beard and said, ‘I can’t shave this beard completely, you know.’

‘Oh! Why, Sir?’

‘Because he has chill burns,’ said Parmesh.

‘Oh! Like the one Mohan had at Darjeeling’.

‘Yes. It can be completely treated or partially managed, depending on the extent of the damage.’

‘I summited Everest the first time on bare minimum sponsorship. The only thing that mattered to me then was that I had to summit the Everest at any cost. I didn’t take enough safety precautions. That’s why the chill burns…,’ said Sekhar Babu.

Sekhar Babu stretched out his bare foot. The tip of his big toe on the right leg was missing.

‘I had skin-level frostbite during one of my expeditions, and hence, this part of my toe had to be amputated. At a deeper level, it may affect the muscle and even the bone. So, we have to be careful and ensure we wear appropriate mountaineering gear.’

Poorna and Anand examined the toe.

‘Take care of yourselves. Eat well. Maintain good hygiene. Keep your fingers, nails and toes clean and use them carefully. Make sure you don’t fall ill,’ Parmesh patted their back, and both of them left.

For the first time, the children understood the enormity of the challenges and forces they were up against. This conversation had the desired impact on Poorna and Anand. They became more committed to their mission. It induced a process of building mental resilience toward a mission; a mission that would shortly become a singular focus point; every breath they took, every word they uttered, every act, conscious and sub-conscious, were geared to embrace one of the greatest natural forces of this planet they inhabited. The micro-consciousness of their ‘being’ bloomed to encompass the enormous panorama of the Great Himalayan force. Perhaps, this was also the beginning of their spiritual journey. What can be more spiritual in quality, than a little child hardening every nerve in the body, realigning all energies of the physical being, transcending the mundane, investing in oneself a confidence and faith that goes beyond all reason? The children were striving for an experience that could be life altering and empowering.

The children complained about nothing thereafter. They knew what they had to do. They knew what it took to be able to pursue their mission. The next morning, Poorna and Anand arrived earlier than usual for training.

One evening, when Poorna and Anand were on the seventieth lap on the track, they saw a figure approaching, dressed in track suit and sneakers. They recognized him by his gait. Praveen Kumar, it was! Praveen Kumar began to run alongside them. A fresh burst of energy charged them.

Parmesh watched them, the three dark, lean figures running on the track. The torch bearer and his two committed warriors. As the sun sank in the West, the three shadows ran relentlessly with energy and vigour.

‘A moment to treasure,’ he thought.

Perfectionism. Perseverance. Passion.

Three qualities they shared.

Sekhar Babu joined Parmesh. The children were in the 120th lap. Parmesh blew the whistle and asked them to stop.

After a few relaxation exercises and stretches, they called it a day. Stood at a distance Praveen Kumar had watched doing push-ups. She counted till thirty and ran when she was called for dinner.

The routine of practice and studies continued till mid-March. Over these days, with the right diet and systemic training, Poorna had gained 12 kg.

It was now time to write their final exams. That evening, Poorna and Anand sat munching on chocolate before the evening practice. Anand found her in an exceptionally jolly mood and asked her, ‘What is it?’

‘Anna, today is the last day of practice. We are going back to school tomorrow.’

‘And?’

‘We will resume training after our examinations.’

‘Are you happy to go back?’

‘Yes, of course! It’s been so long. I want to meet all my friends. Don’t you want to go? Aren’t you happy?’

‘Hell, I want to go.’ He smiled. ‘But, you and I… we won’t meet.’

Poorna thought for a while. ‘Yes, annayya. That’s true. But we can do one thing. I will give my PET Madam’s number. Call me after every exam and tell me how you’ve performed. At least, we will get to talk to each other every day.’

Anand was glad, and they exchanged a hi-five. Parmesh walked into the ground. They ran to him.

‘Do we have practice today, Sir?

‘Why do you ask, Anand?’

‘Sir, is today the last day of practice? Are we going back to school tomorrow?’

‘Yes. Sekhar Babu will tell you more about that.’

‘But today, I want to see how far you can stretch yourselves. Push yourselves. I want to test your endurance.’

He blew the whistle. Poorna and Anand looked at him puzzled.

‘Now GO…’

The children finished their jog and then did their warm up exercise and stretches.

Parmesh instructed the children to run till he called off.

They got to the track and started running. At first, their pace was slow. Gradually they picked up speed. Then slowed down again. Before the Ladakh Expedition too, they had practised this technique of increasing and decreasing pace. Poorna and Anand jogged in opposite directions at about the same speed. They exchanged a quiet glance every time they crossed each other.

‘Speed up,’ Parmesh shouted. They picked up speed.

Parmesh counted till hundred. Parmesh walked closer to the tracks to get a better view of them. Poorna easily completed the 120th round covering a distance of 24 km, which she did every day. From the 130th round, their pace dropped.

He pushed them. ‘ Arey! Why did you slow down? RUN.’

He screamed at the top of his voice.

The children increased their pace immediately. They made another 20 rounds at this pace. Their socks were drenched in sweat. Poorna managed another seven rounds after which her legs were beginning to give way. She felt her legs would soon buckle. Parmesh went toward her and held her by her shoulder. Anand dragged himself for another four rounds and came back gasping heavily.

After a five-minute rest, they were asked to do stretches.

Parmesh noted:

Poorna nonstop running record: 31.4 km

Anand nonstop running record: 32.2 km

Poorna and Anand returned to their residential schools to write their final exams. Special instructions were given to the PETs to ensure they maintained their routine of diet and exercise.

Bon Voyage

6 April 2014
5.45 am
Secunderabad Railway Station

The AP express was set to leave the station in fifteen minutes. For a small group of people on the platform, these were anxious moments.

Praveen Kumar stood at a distance, answering phone calls. Poorna and Anand were talking animatedly with their PETs. They were on the threshold of a journey to achieve a goal; a goal, that he had envisioned for his Swaeroes. It is not just a journey to conquer the Everest; but, a journey toward equality to be achieved through sheer hard work and determination.

Parmesh and Mannan were making last-minute checks. The principals of the two schools, Venugopal and a few administrative staff of Social Welfare Residential Schools were in deep discussion.

Devidas, Poorna’s father and Kondal Rao, Anand’s father were squatting near a pillar. They exchanged a word or two every now and then.

Praveen Kumar tried to fathom their thoughts and feelings at that moment. But in, vain.

Am I doing the right thing? They have entrusted their precious children to my hands, not knowing what the future holds; prepared for both, glory or tragedy!

He felt a surge of compassionate warmth toward these souls; steeped in poverty, at the margins of society; uneducated and living a way of life that is as basic as it could get; and, not allowing their filial love and affection to be deterrents to their children’s future. Sending them away from home to a residential school is one thing; sending them away to the mighty laps of nature, malevolent and benevolent at once, hoping and praying that it will protect and nurture their children, is another thing altogether. At this moment, for Praveen, they were the heroes.

He walked toward them with long strides. He stopped short. There he was before Devidas and Kondal Rao. He felt overwhelmed. He exercised restraint lest he appear sentimental. Devidas sprang up to his feet. His worn out, tired face made him look atleast a decade older than he really was. Eking out two square meals a day was the biggest challenge of his life. Yet, his eyes displayed a steely resolve, a reflection of which he had seen in Poorna’s eyes.

‘Devidas, I hope you are completely sure. Let me know…let me know if you are even slightly unsure; or, if you have any misgivings. We can stop her right now.’

Devidas’ eyes brimmed with tears. He wiped his eyes with the edge of the towel lying over his shoulder, looked at Praveen, his small eyes glistening amidst folds of skin, ‘Sir, I am fine.’

He swallowed the fear that stuck in his throat like a lump.

‘She must go and come back, victorious.’

Kondal Rao leaned against the pillar. His wife Lakshmi hadn’t come to see their son off as she had suddenly taken ill. Praveen Kumar asked Kondal Rao, ‘Are you willing to send your son? Please tell me if you have a change of mind. I can stop him even now.’

Anand’s father held Praveen’s hands and laughed nervously even as his eyes filled. ‘Sir, I gave my son away to you the moment I admitted him to school. He is now your child. He belongs to you.’

Praveen, along with Mannan and Parmesh had met Devidas and Kondal Rao a couple of months ago to apprise them of the dangers of the expedition and to complete the necessary formalities. In fact, before each expedition, Praveen Kumar made it a point to meet the parents. When the children embarked on the Ladakh expedition, the parents, for the first time, had realized that this was no child’s play, but serious business. However, since it was a government-sponsored expedition, they were more at ease; but, the real reason to send their children was that they shared Praveen Kumar’s vision and had complete trust in him. Although Devidas and Lakshmi had seen a few pictures of Poorna and her team summiting Mount Renock and of the Ladakh expedition, the Himalayan expedition was like none other. Hence, Praveen Kumar sought parental consent only after giving them a clear and honest picture of what the children were up against. Praveen counseled the parents about the entire expedition and the dangers and risks integral to and inevitable in an expedition of this magnitude.

Praveen Kumar first invited Devidas and Lakshmi into his office. He showed videos of the conditions prevailing on Mount Everest, the possible risks of becoming handicapped or worse, never returning. Lakshmi’s face turned ashen. Her lips quivered, and hands trembled when she saw visuals of dead bodies hanging midair amidst the pristine white mountains or half buried in snow. She outrightly refused to send her child. She broke into a cold sweat and started weeping.

Poorna excused herself and took her parents out of the room.

‘Beta. This is not the right thing to do. I don’t want you to go. I just want you to study well and get a good job. That’s enough!’

‘Yadi, maaku jukoni samazhl (Nothing will happen to me). I will come back for sure. Believe me. Do you know how many children are studying in residential schools? A few lakhs. Out of them, only two are selected, and I am one of them.’

She looked at her father. ‘ Baa, (father) I am one of those two. Please send me.’

While Poorna tried to assure her parents, Praveen and Parmesh spoke to Kondal Rao. He saw all the photographs and videos. He listened to all that Praveen had to tell him with surprising calm. A sense of resignation swept across his face. He sighed deeply and took the pen.

Praveen said, ‘Kondal Rao, think about it. Your son might come back badly hurt. Or he might not...’

‘I know, Sir,’ his voice quivered. ‘The day I admitted him to the residential school, I gave away all rights to you. Now you are his guardian. He belongs to the school. You and your department will shape his future. I only gave birth to him. I don’t want him to miss opportunities just because he is born to me. God will surely watch over my son.’

Praveen and Parmesh were also in deep turmoil.

Parmesh had interacted with these two children for nearly eight months now. This is his team. He had trained and molded them. He thought about them all the time. He constantly planned and revised his own training methods to get the best out of the children. In a few days, they would be reaching the DEATH ZONE.

He has himself experienced first-hand, the magnetism of the Himalayas as a mountaineer. He knows that nothing can stop the children from this point onwards. Initially, it is only a fascination. The beauty captivates you. The enormity leaves you in awe. Then slowly, the Himalayas begin to grow on you, unobtrusively. It enters your sub-conscious. It becomes a part of you. Then you are at the mercy of the Himalayas. You surrender to the Himalayas.

He has invested his emotions in these children. He has trained them like a mother eagle teaching her fledglings to fly. The mother eagle pushes her little ones into the vast expanse, well aware of the dangers they are bound to confront. But there is no other way.

Parmesh got up and went toward the window for some fresh air.

This is serious business. But there is no other way. The line between thinking and doing is very thin. Or, at least, that is what one thinks. But, when the final call has to be made, the same thin line marks life from death. And, it suddenly becomes insurmountable. He loves them. God knows. He closed his eyes in prayer. God, let them come back safe. Whether they summit or not, doesn’t matter to me anymore. They are only buds, just about blossoming. Please do not let them wither away.

Praveen pulled up a stool and sat close to the children. He said, in a soft tone, affectionately, ‘You must earn laurels. Poorna and Anand should be the pride of Social Welfare Residential Schools.’

‘Sir, we will!’ said Poorna. Her eyes twinkled. The enormity of the journey she was about to embark upon had sunk into her. All the more reason, she smiled and held a poised demeanor to give courage to those loving souls around her. She empathized with them. She knew each one was going through turmoil.

Parmesh, a lawyer himself, had drafted consent on non-judicial stamp papers to be signed by the parents of these minor children. Praveen Kumar had taken a written confirmation from both sets of parents for the Everest Expedition.

Only a few minutes were left for the train to depart from the station.

Mannan walked toward Devidas and Kondal Rao. ‘We have a tradition in our schools to pray for those setting out on any sort of challenge.’ He handed a few pamphlets. ‘Take a look.’

The pamphlets made an appeal to all students and teachers to pray for the well-being of their friends, who were part of the Ladakh Winter Expedition. Another pamphlet made a similar appeal for the children who were training at HMI, Darjeeling before heading to Mount Renock.

‘Just before Poorna and Anand begin their expedition, we will print new ones. All the children and staff of all the Social Welfare Residential Schools will pray to the Almighty every single day for their safe return.’

Mannan believed in the power of prayer. And perhaps, in this situation, when all humanly possible precautions would be taken, God’s grace was all that one could seek.

The final announcements for the departure of the train filled the air, drowning the chatter of passengers, their kith and kin and the coolies. The train too signaled its departure as the whistle blew. Praveen shook hands with Sekhar Babu, Poorna and Anand for the last time. He may see them after two months. The usually stoic Praveen batted his eyelids to hold back a tear or two. A few hushed sobs were also heard.

Sekhar Babu was surprised by the courage the children displayed at this moment. They wore a big smile on their faces, although forced. A drop of tear precariously hung at the brim of Poorna’s eyes. She managed to force it back. Anand saw her face and took her hand into his as he cast a final look at his father and gave a reassuring smile.

All of them stood dumbstruck as they watched the train leave the platform. A sudden loud sob split the silence. Poorna’s father was crying uncontrollably, covering his face with his towel. Devidas remembered his four-year-old daughter in Pakal who lost her way and boldly waited for him to pick her up after two hours. His daughter is now going to find her way up Mount Everest, all alone. But, he won’t be able to go pick her up if she lost her way. And she may not be able to find her way back home this time.

Meanwhile, Lakshmi sat at home praying to the Gods of Vemulavada, Tirupati and Kondaguttu. She had vowed to go on a pilgrimage to these holy places once her Poorna returned safely. Till such time, she had decided not to reveal Poorna’s expedition to the Himalayas to family, friends, neighbours or relatives. She hadn’t cooked. She hadn’t visited the fields. She had only sat and prayed.

Devidas reached Tadwai the same evening. Lakshmi sat outside her hut, waiting for him. She paced toward him silently. She looked at him only to see Poorna’s dream in his eyes. And she broke into tears. He went inside the house toward the only framed family photo hanging on the wall. He took the photo frame off the wall gently and sat down on the floor. Lakshmi sat next to him. He ran his fingers on Poorna’s face.

He nudged his wife and said, ‘This girl, our daughter,’ he laughed amid tears strolling down his face, ‘you will see her in the newspapers one day! Just you wait.’

Lakshmi took the photo from him and held it close to her bosom. The day Poorna was born. Her first smile. Her first step. The first time she said amma. The first time she hurt herself while playing in the front yard, her escapades from the Anganwadi centers, the day she was dropped to the residential school – all these images, rolled in front of her eyes, frame by frame. Lakshmi and Devidas sat, God knows for how long, travelling back in memory lane, holding each other’s hand, impervious of thirst and hunger, and the fading light of day outside.

Sagarmatha - So Close, Yet So Far

8 April 2014
7.00 pm
Kathmandu, Nepal

Kathmandu, the capital of Nepal, all of 50 km, located at a height of 1,300 metres, is a visual treat. Poorna was by now quite familiar with the environs of hill stations at high altitudes. In fact, it was a welcome reprieve from the hot, humid climes back home. She loved the variety of flora and fauna of the hill stations, especially the birds and their songs!

The people, she noticed, had a different appearance. They were shorter, pale skinned and their eyes were a tad smaller. The tinge of a friendly smile and the little gleam of delight in their eyes warmed her. Acclimatisation to weather conditions was never a problem for Poorna, but the change in cuisine was a big one. Anand though enjoyed the Nepali cuisine.

Poorna grew quiet, and she bore a demeanour of seriousness, her eyes watching the surroundings keenly. Anand burst into an exciting volley of questions about the place, the people and the journey henceforth. Poorna, Shekar Babu observed, responded to her environment intuitively; she imbibed the contours and specificities of her environment unconsciously and become a part of it, and it of her. For Anand, it was, however, more an intellectual experience. He sought precise data and information. He read, asked questions and even interacted with people to learn more. He was acutely aware of his ‘self’ as much as of the rest of the world.

That evening Poorna and Anand met mountaineers Surabhi Chawla and Kishore Dhankode, who were to be part of their expedition team. They also met Dr. Narendra Patil who would monitor their health while on the expedition.

9 April 2014

The next morning, they visited the Pashupatinath Temple. They stood in a long queue and offered prayers to Lord Shiva.

After breakfast, they headed to the markets to buy some more equipment. Sekhar Babu bought snow boots, fleece jackets, scarves and trekking shoes, among other equipment for the children.

Anand, Poorna and Sekhar Babu were waiting at the bus stop when Anand leaned on one of the equipment bags, and the bag was about to fall. Poorna prevented the bag from falling. She glared at him and snapped, ‘Keep it safe, annayya. We need this equipment. It is our life-line.’

Sekhar Babu and Anand were taken aback by Poorna’s strong emotional reaction to an innocuous slip. Neither of them had seen her respond with such intensity before. She was known to be stoic. That instant, Sekhar Babu shed his illusions about her. Beneath the small frame of a thirteen-year-old was hidden a mature girl with great fortitude. Poorna worshipped her mountaineering gear. She handled it with great respect.

10 April 2014

Sekhar Babu explained that two base camps were located on either sides of Mount Everest. While the South Base Camp was in Nepal at an altitude of 5,364 meters, the North Base Camp was located in Tibet, at 5,150 meters. They would be travelling to North Base Camp, which required passage through China. This route, Sekhar explained, was less harsh and recorded a lower fatality rate as compared to the other route.

After two days at Kathmandu, the six-member contingent took a bus to Panitanki, a small village in Darjeeling district of West Bengal, lying on the Indo-Nepal border. After clearing immigration formalities, they crossed the Sian-Nepal Friendship Bridge to reach Zangbu, a small Chinese town. Sekhar had meticulously planned the eight-day journey from Delhi to the Everest Base Camp in Tibet. He had ensured frequent over-night halts to facilitate acclimatization.

The journey was quite taxing, despite the breaks. However, the spectacular views of snow-capped mountains eased the mind and heart. The winding roads offered breathtaking views of the valleys nestled between peaks. Zangbu was a clean, neat town with meticulously and artistically aligned houses with simple elevation. Anand was surprised to find the usually fussy Poorna relishing a Chinese meal. The children were amused to find that their hotel rooms had electronic locks instead of the conventional padlocks and key. The rooms were spacious, and they enjoyed the VIP treatment accorded by the hotel staff.

Praveen Kumar called them that night and chatted with them for some time.

11 April 2014

They took a bus to Nyalam (3,743 meters), a small Tibetan town lying on the border of Nepal. Nyalam offers a panoramic view of the Himalayas. The meandering roads made beautiful patterns as it wound its way up the mountains. As they ascended higher altitudes, they caught glimpses of a majestic river glistening in the valley below.

They reached Nyalam by noon. Houses here, Poorna noticed, were built of wood and not concrete. They sat at a hotel, waiting for lunch to arrive. They were amused to see people eating with chopsticks. The children tried their hand at chopsticks, but in vain. They gave up and used spoons instead.

The doctor examined them that night and certified their fitness. They spent the night at the Xizang Nielamu Xueyu Hotel.

The following day, the team trekked up a nearby hill to acclimatize their bodies to the high altitude. They experienced a snow shower for the first time. Since they were appropriately geared, they enjoyed the shower. Poorna so loved the pristine little town, she wished she could stay there forever!

Now, Poorna had developed a distaste for Chinese food and chose Nepalese, instead. That night, Surabhi and the doctor cooked dinner. Everyone enjoyed the meal.

Praveen Kumar called to check on the children late that night.

13 April 2014

The contingent took a bus to Tingri the next morning. The first thing that struck Poorna was that China was a left-hand driving country.

Every journey turned out to be more blissful that the other; and every view, a feast for the eyes. En route, they saw debris from recent landslides. They reached Tingri by noon.

‘This is paradise on Earth!’ said Poorna.

‘Paradise reminds me of Gymsam of Ladakh,’ said Anand.

They laughed out loud when they heard that the name of their hotel was Hahoo Hotel. Since the temperature here was quite low, Sekhar Babu took them out for an acclimatization walk. The Doctor once again examined the children and the other two members of the team and certified their fitness.

14 April 2014

Fourteenth April is a special day for Swaeroes as it marks Ambedkar’s birthday. Poorna and Anand wished each other. They were happy when Mannan called them. He told them that he was in touch with their parents, updating them about their well-being and progress. The children hoped to hear from Praveen Kumar as well, but they learnt that he was busy participating in programs scheduled for the special day.

The team trekked nearly 4,670 metres when they suddenly spotted the Everest amidst the mountains! For Poorna, this was a surreal experience. The howling chilly winds absorbed her existence. Between the mountains, far away, the Everest stood like a Sage. Yes, like a Sage, consciously, observing the course of life but oblivious to its joys, sorrows and struggles. Its nonchalance and detachment to human life sent shivers up her spine.

‘If I have managed to arrive here, then I certainly can and will reach the summit.’

It was past 7 o’ clock on her watch, and the sunlight hadn’t faded into darkness. Poorna sat watching the hues of green dancing to the mild zephyr and the hills beyond. ‘It is a special day, indeed,’ Poorna said to herself.

15 April 2014

Another day had passed by. Another day would take birth. And yet another day, she will summit the Everest.

The team reached the Everest Base Camp by late noon. Mount Everest was clearly visible from the Base Camp. On this day, in the month of May, the site of the camp had reasonably good weather, varying between 15˚c high and 0˚c low. The ground was naked, free from snow. The Quianjingou River remains frozen the entire month.

Each member was given a tent. The dining tent was large enough to accommodate about 30 people. Poorna loved the food that was served here. The noons were quite warm.

The Everest Base Camp, run by liaison officers of the Defence Department was richly diverse. People from different countries, speaking different languages and practicing diffe rent religions arrive here with the sole purpose of experiencing and summiting the Everest. They all share one thing in common – undying passion for mountaineering! The Everest Base Camp works as a waiting area for climbers to start their Everest ascent based on weather reports. This Camp is well equipped with all logistics necessary for living. Multiple huge tents double up as a kitchen, dining area, rest area, among others. Diet meals are prepared for mountaineers. A robust mobile phone and satellite phone network are in place. Climbers can call from Camp 3 to the Base Camp and to anywhere in India via the satellite phones.

Television is also available for entertainment.

‘Annayya…isn’t this amazing? We are finally here,’ Poorna said with irrepressible excitement.

16 April 2014

The next morning, she stepped out of her tent to brush her teeth. The sky was clear, and she looked around to see if she could locate the Everest. She remembered seeing it from the Kanchenjunga stretch. After a few seconds, she was surprised to find the Everest closer than expected. She hurriedly brushed and rushed to Sekhar and Anand.

‘Sir,’ she shouted, ‘It is so close…can we start right away, Sir?’

Sekhar and Anand stopped talking and looked at her puzzled. Poorna pointed toward her new discovery.

‘Sir, daggarne kada (close enough, right), why can’t we start now and return by evening?’

Sekhar comprehended the implication of her words and laughed.

‘Yeah, yeah! Why not? Find your way, peddamma (big girl). You think it’s so easy, huh?’

He was amused at her innocence! The enormity of the task ahead of her loomed large on his horizon.

What’s the fuss all about, wondered Poorna.

‘It’s very close, isn’t it? Do you know what it takes to reach the Everest? You will have to touch the borders of the DEATH ZONE. And you have to come back alive. These nine kilometres, as short a distance as it may sound, is equal to a few weeks of expedition, driving the very life out of your body and, hopefully, gulping it back.’

Yeah! The DEATH ZONE. Poorna muttered in annoyance.

‘Is it that risky, Sir? I think we will come back safe. We’ll not die. But once we come back, we will be treated special. Chinna, remember how we were treated after Mount Renock summit. We met the CM, and the Deputy CM felicitated us. Now it is Mount Everest,’ said Anand casting a glance at Mount Everest, ‘Wow… we will soon be famous.’

Sekhar cleared his throat.

‘Babu…let me tell you something. Success should become a part of history and of books; don’t ever let it get into your head. Because, once it gets into your head, you are finished, forever. We must only do what we believe in with due diligence. Let people record that on our behalf; for us, every milestone achieved should only be the starting point for another milestone. Do you understand?’

Anand smiled. ‘Yes, Sir,’ he said, embarrassed.

‘Good. Now, let’s get a good night’s sleep.’

Poorna couldn’t fall asleep immediately that night. She wondered what her parents would be doing. Her father must be resting on the navvar bed in the front yard. It must be very hot. They would be thinking of her, of course. She hoped Mannan is keeping them informed of her well-being.

The night sky was jubilant. The sky at Pakala was also clear but never this dense with stars. The stars and the mountains! They belong to each other! Perhaps the mountains lend their luminescence to the starts at night, before going to sleep. The stars watch over them and return their light in the morning.

17 April 2014

The next morning, Sekhar woke them up quite early.

‘Sir, are we leaving today?’ Anand peeped out of his sleeping bag.

Poorna had the same question.

‘Nahi re, not yet. Let us go roam around a bit.’

Acclimatization, Poorna said to herself, otherwise, Acute Mountain Sickness.

They went out for a short trek every day for the next four days. Poorna marveled the beauty of each mountain – mountains draped in white, dappled with brown spots of earth. Mornings were bright. Nights were freezing. They would slip into the sleeping bags and resist waking up in the morning. Sekhar used to encourage them to spend as much time as possible outside the tent. The noons were warm and cozy.

‘You will fall sick, if you stay inside the tent too much,’ he would say.

Sekhar took advantage of every resource available. He made his team walk with crampons on the frozen river. He occasionally took them out for lunch to the nearby Tibetan villages to try the local food. Usually, this ritual was preceded by a trek.

Poorna, Anand and Sekhar enjoyed every moment of their stay at Everest Base Camp. Sekhar knew what it meant for these young children to be away from the comfort of their home and friends. He kept the children at ease at all times. The children too never fussed about anything. They had learned to make do with whatever was available. Well, they hadn’t exactly learned. That was a way of life for them anyway. They sometimes played antakshari and were surprised when Sekhar Babu beat them.

Several mountaineers had halted at the Everest Base camp and were seen trekking nearby mountains to acclimatize themselves. They were surprised to see such young children attempting the Everest. A few thought the attempt was nothing but ridiculous!

18 April 2014

The next morning, Anand told Poorna over breakfast that he had overheard Sekhar Babu speaking to Praveen Kumar and praising Poorna for her endurance.

Shekar Babu had tested their endurance by taking them on a long hike – all the way up to 5,200 meters. The wind was stronger, and the temperature lower. The children are gradually acclimatizing, he noted. Except for a mild headache, there was no other complaint.

Sekhar Babu took the children to participate in the Lama Puja (a prayer ritual), to be performed in front of the Stupa (the divine pilllar) by the sherpas before embarking on an expedition. The Puja is open for all. Then, the sherpas performed a slow dance. Poorna and her team also joined the dance and tried a few simple steps. While dancing, the sherpas were chanting ‘Sagarmatha’ (forehead of the ocean) and ‘Chomolungma’ (Goddess Mother of Mountains) – names by which the Everest is referred to in Nepali and Tibetan, respectively. Poorna wondered why Mount Everest is called the Sagarmatha. Sagar means the Ocean. Why would a mountain be addressed as an ocean? Because it is surrounded by ice and snow, which is nothing but water? Would the Himalayas liquify to form an ocean someday?

The contingent visited a Buddhist Cave Monastery. The ancient Buddha statues were elegant and solemn. They took some pictures. Inside the caves, was a labyrinth of smaller cave rooms. The walls were inscribed with the history of the monastery. In the first cave room, they were guided to light oil lamps. Poorna experienced a sense of serenity and peace as the lamps glowed in the darkness of the ancient caves. Time seemed to have come to a standstill. She felt one with herself.

They returned from the monastery, to find a flurry of whispered voices and subdued commotion at the Base Camp premises. The mood at the Base Camp was rather sombre.

‘Derek, what’s the matter?’ Sekhar Babu went into the next tent.

He didn’t come out for a while. Overcome by weariness, Poorna and Anand stepped into their tents to rest. After some time, she felt hungry. She went in search of Sekhar Babu. She found him among a group of people engaged in some serious discussion.

‘Sir, let us go for dinner.’

Poorna found Sekhar Babu unusually serious. She had never seen him this way before. She was scared. Had she done something to cross him? Is he upset because she does not eat well?

She went to Anand. ‘Annayya, Sir looks very serious. What could it be?’

Praveen was at a meeting at Bapatla, when his phone rang. It was Raymond Peter.

‘Yes, Sir,’ he said into the phone.

‘Praveen, did you hear the news?’

‘What news, Sir?’

Raymond Peter sighed, ‘Well Praveen, an avalanche has been reported close to Mount Everest. Have you heard from Sekhar? Any news at all? How are they?’

Praveen’s heart skipped a beat. He called Sekhar Babu immediately.

Sekhar Babu came into Poorna’s tent. Poorna and Anand were chatting with each other. He announced, ‘There was an avalanche. Sixteen sherpas are missing.’

‘Avalanche?!!’

Anand said, ‘We may find them, Sir.’

At the onset of the mountaineering season, a team of authorized sherpas are sent to officially open the route to Everest. This time too, the group left the Base Camp, little knowing that a disaster awaited them. They got caught in an avalanche. They got caught in an avalanche at South Col, a sharp edged Col between Lhotse and Mount Everest. A Col is the lowest point of a ridge between two peaks, which provides a pathway from one side of the mountain range to another. Chances of survival, as is known, are usually zero.

Poorna broke the silence. ‘The avalanche has occurred in the southern route, isn’t it Sir?’

‘Yes. Thank God. We didn’t take that route!’

‘Why didn’t we, Sir? Did God appear in your dreams and advise you?’

‘Kaadu raa..(No buddy). You guys did not get permission from the Nepal government for the south route. I am familiar with this route. I am better equipped to handle the challenges that you may face on this route. And your training is also based on the requirements of climbing this route. Arthamainda? (Do you understand?)’

Poorna and Anand remained silent.

Sekhar Babu’s phone rang.

Gearing Up for the Rendezvous

‘Hi, Sekhar! How are you guys?’ Praveen Kumar was on the line.

‘Hello, Sir. We are doing very well.’

‘How are Poorna and Anand?’

‘They are good too, Sir. They are here with me right now.’

‘I heard about the avalanche at South Col.’

‘Well, yes. Unfortunate.’

‘Would the avalanche affect your journey in any way?’

‘Not really, Sir. But we may have difficulty finding sherpas. Sixteen sherpas are missing. After the incident, the sherpa community is fighting with the government for a larger share in income.’

‘Can you turn on the speaker? I want to talk to Poorna and Anand.’

‘Sure, Sir.’ Sekhar Babu turned on the speaker of his phone.

‘Hello Poorna, Anand. How are you guys doing?’

‘We are fine, Sir. How are you?’

‘I am good. You would have heard about the avalanche, right?’

‘Yes, Sir.’

‘So, what do you want to do? Do you still want to go ahead? Or do you think you want to come back?’

‘Sir?!!!!’

‘Poorna. Listen to me. It’s okay to come back. Making it to the Everest Base Camp itself is a summit for us. Your safety is more important to me. So, what I…’

‘Sir,’ Poorna interrupted. ‘I want us to go. We have come this far. I am sure we can make it till Mount Everest too.’

‘Poorna…’

‘Sir, we are Swaeroes. We have no reverse gears. That is our tenth commandment…remember?’

Anand chipped in. ‘Sir, we are not coming back. We have embarked on this journey. And we will go the whole way. The sky is the limit.’

19 April 2014

In a few days, Sekhar organized a team of sherpas for the expedition. Ngima Nuru and Gyansto sherpa would assist Poorna, and Mingma Nuru, and Mingma sherpa would assist Anand. Usually, one climber needs one sherpa. Since Poorna and Anand are children, Sekhar took extra precaution and appointed two sherpas for each of them.

Sherpas assist and guide mountaineers to the top of Mount Everest. They are born and live in the Himalayas, and above an altitude of 14,000 feet. The pregnant women of the community are taken to the monasteries on the peak of the Himalayan Mountains. The babies born in the monasteries naturally acquire the ability to acclimatize themselves to the climatic conditions of the Himalayas. They are able to generate oxygen as demanded by the body at that altitude. Other populations, especially those that live in extremely hot climatic conditions do not have the same body constitutions.

The genetic composition and the natural acclimatization by birth to the extreme climate make sherpas agile on the mountains. Most of the local people turn into professional sherpas for livelihood. Sherpas play a very important role in mountaineering. It is almost impossible for first timers to scale the Everest without the help of sherpas. Sherpas not only act as guides but also work as porters and cooks during the expedition. Thus, most sherpas summit the Everest multiple times. For Poorna’s sherpa Mingma Nuru, this would be the seventeenth time to summit the Everest!

The team now comprised 16 members: Poorna, Anand and their four sherpas; Surabhi and Kishore and their two sherpas; and four cooks, the doctor and Sekar Babu.

The sherpas left to the higher camps with the luggage mounted on Yaks. Yaks native to the Himalayan ranges are a primary means of transportation on the mountains. They have a huge tolerance to cold climate.

20 April 2014 and 21 April 2014

Sekhar Babu took his team on a hike. The hill was rather steep and maintaining consistent breathing pattern itself turned into a big challenge. While descending the steep slope, Poorna and Anand used the body balancing technique they had learnt at Bhongir.

The next day, Sekhar Babu took them to Quianjingou Lake, a frozen stream behind the Everest Base Camp for crampon practice. Although Poorna had practised with a crampon before, this time around, she experienced shortness of breath, yet managed to complete the exercise.

22 April 2014

The team was to commence the expedition drill for acclimatization the next day. They would climb to Advance Base Camp (ABC), then to Intermediary Camp and reach Camp 1. They would return to ABC via the same route. They would rest at each camp for two days.

‘Why aren’t we going straight to Camp 2?’ asked Anand.

‘Well, some trekkers return to ABC and go back to Camp 1 and then to Camp 2. But it is not advisable. Acclimatization is very essential,’ said Sekhar Babu.

Hypoxia, pulmonary edema and cerebral edema are the major threats to the life of a mountaineer at these heights. Acclimatization is the key to prevent these symptoms. Precaution must be taken to prevent frost-bites and chill-burns.

23 April 2014 to 5 May 2014

Sekhar Babu’s contingent started their trek in the morning from Everest Base Camp and reached the Intermediate Camp located at 6,187 meters before noon. Although Poorna and Anand experienced slight dizziness and nausea, they managed this trek quite well.

The challenge is yet to begin, Poorna thought.

One step at a time, she kept telling herself.

Numbing winds were pressing against them. Sheets of clouds floated below them. They were inching closer and closer to the Everest. Although amidst a spectacular 360-degree view, weariness was weighing down upon them heavily.

The contingent now continued its ascent toward Advance Base Camp. The trek up this stretch became more labored. Poorna experienced dizziness. Anand developed cramps in both legs. After some time, Poorna started vomiting. Despite the vomiting, she remained active. But she was hardly able to eat after that.

Poorna continued to be fussy about food at ABC too. She had now developed an aversion for rotis and meat cooked by the sherpas. She preferred eating regular pickle rice. At Everest Base Camp, she even had cool drinks during the noons. Sekhar Babu had been very patient with Poorna as far as her eating habits were concerned. He explained to her many times and finally resorted to scold her. She cried but couldn’t eat.

Sekhar Babu requested Parmesh to speak to her over the phone. Parmesh sent her a voice message. Poorna had utmost respect for Parmesh, but she also feared him. She respected Sekhar Babu immensely. He was more cheerful and approachable. Poorna cried, forcing herself to eat even as she listened to Parmesh’s message. She wondered if there was an alternative to eating! That could have made her life so easy.

Poorna’s fussiness, her vomiting episodes and further aversion to food were proving to be a problem. Anand was not doing very well, either. Shekar Babu decided to put them on oxygen for an hour. After an hour, they felt much better. Anand moved around comfortably. Poorna seemed all right for the first five minutes but started throwing up again.

Sekhar Babu realized he had to take a call.

He called Ngima Nuru sherpa, who was resting in his tent and said, ‘Please take her back to Everest Base Camp and bring her back after two days. We will wait for her here. If she doesn’t improve after you bring her back, we will have to send her back to the Everest Base Camp.’

Poorna was disappointed. She didn’t like the idea of returning to ABC. Not going to the Everest because of vomiting! She found it ridiculous. She felt well inside, despite the bouts of vomiting. But, Sekhar Babu was very concerned, and he didn’t want to take chances.

‘Poorna, you get to eat only packaged food once you are above Camp 1. How will you manage if you cannot eat this cooked food itself? You will have to go back to Everest Base Camp and come back again. Let’s see if that works. Otherwise, ...’ he frowned and shrugged his shoulders.

Poorna left for Everest Base Camp with a sherpa. She realized how precarious the path to the Everest was and how uncertain her chances of returning were. Tears rolled down her cheeks as she descended.

I want to summit. I will come back. For sure. After all that training and hard work! Mind over Body. Yes! Yes! Yes!

There are some situations in life when one has to rely heavily on inner strength. This was one such for Poorna. Despite the physical fitness, the long hours of training, all she needed now was that deep resource within her that is almost divine! That cannot be enhanced externally or measured by any yardstick. This strength, the divine life force itself, is harnessed at those moments when the lines differentiating life and death become narrow.

Poorna remembered a transformative experience from Tadwai. Poorna was once a timid, fearful, withdrawn child. When she joined the Social Welfare Residential School at Tadwai, she was too shy to make friends. After school hours, the children had to engage in some outdoor sport. While the other girls ran, laughed and played, Poorna would find a quiet corner, away from the sight of the others. As time passed, she became friendlier, and she played hesitantly with the other girls. She desisted from participating in team sports such as volleyball and throwball simply because she was scared of the older girls, and she feared being beaten by them in a game. Her entry into serious sports was when one of her friends gave her name for the volleyball team without her knowledge. Neither could she withdraw nor would her friends let her escape. Just before she entered the court, she knew the moment of change had come. She could no longer cower and hide. Once she stepped onto the court, she forgot all her fears. She went all out and played. Her performance stunned her friends, seniors and teachers alike. There was no looking back. She went on to become the sports champion for the year.

She found herself in a similar situation now. The stakes, however, were very, very high. Did she have the inner strength to quell mountain sickness?

Meanwhile, Anand and Sekhar Babu trekked from ABC to Camp 1 and returned to Advance Base Camp. They now only waited for Poorna. Poorna was back in form after three days and arrived at the Advance Base Camp from the Everest Base Camp. She successfully reached Camp 1 along with her sherpa. After a night halt at Camp 1, she returned to Advance Base Camp.

That night at dinner, Sekhar Babu was relieved to see Poorna eat without a fuss. It was apparent that she didn’t like the food, but she managed to gulp it down. Energy is vital in these altitudes.

The team reached the Everest Base Camp after the trial. Now they waited for the weather report for clearance to resume their trek. Surabhi had to leave the trek due to some technical difficulties. So now Poorna, Anand and Kishore were on this journey together.

6 May 2014 – 23 May 2014

The team waited at the Everest Base Camp for the weather Gods to turn cordial. Praveen Kumar called them almost every day. The children bonded well with the sherpas. Ngima sherpa even played with the children .

On 10th May 2014, the team met Ralf Dujmovits, a German mountaineer, who had summited 14 peaks. Anand and Poorna worshipped him, he was their idol. The 14 peaks he summitted were DEATH ZONES. Although they did not understand much of what he said in his heavily accented English, meeting him made a huge impact on the young minds.

The weather was still not conducive. They visited a temple. They were offered holy water, which was clear, cold and very tasty. From the temple, they walked to a monastery. The monastery showcased long black swords and tall black statues. The walls of the cave adjoining the monastery had imprints of Buddha’s feet and hands.

The monastery did have a few inhabitants. Some men and even small children. They were dressed in red robes and held rosary bead strings. They offered bread to Anand and Poorna. They sat and ate it along with the little children. Their faces were beatific with twinkling eyes and mischievous smiles.

They explored further into the cave to find a big golden statue of about 12 feet high. Poorna and Anand wondered about the antiquity of the statue. They drank the milk tea that was offered. They did not like the taste, though.

Policemen were stationed outside the temple and cave. Poorna found it amusing that these short stout men commuted in large four-wheeler vehicles.

17 May 2014

The weather seemed pleasant today. About nine teams, totaling 60 people, were stationed at the Advance Base Camp waiting for favourable weather.

When Praveen called to talk to the children that morning, he suggested that it was a good idea to hoist a flag of the Telangana State, which was just formed, although not yet bifurcated.

But how? Poorna and Anand were at a loss. They had carried only three flags: Party flags of S.P. Sankaran and Ambedkar and the Swaeroes’ flag. Anand and Poorna rummaged through their clothes for a pink shirt. Pink was the colour of Telangana’s revolution. Poorna did find a brand new plain pink T-shirt. Anand painted TELANGANA in his beautiful handwriting with grey fabric paint. When Sekhar Babu arrived, he found both the children painting the T-shirt.

18 May 2014

Sekhar Babu broke the good news to the children. The weather report was favourable for ascent until 25th May, 2014. The team would start their final trek up the Everest early next morning. Sekhar Babu called Praveen Kumar and informed him.

‘Summit before 11.00 am 25th May. That’s our target,’ Shekar Babu said.

The ABC is enveloped in an atmosphere of excitement. A new sense of energy is radiating among the 60 odd mountaineers. The Seven Summits Club hosted a party that night, complete with DJ and plenty of food. The Seven Summits Club is an alpine club for those aspiring to climb the seven highest peaks from across the seven continents of the world. There was a lot of merriment. Poorna enjoyed the music and dance. Poorna met mountaineers from all over the world. They were in awe of the Himalayas. She learnt that the ultimate desire of mountaineers from all over the world, who have summited several ranges such as the Alps, is to summit the Himalayas.

Anand, Sekhar Babu and Poorna danced to Bollywood music. She stepped aside for a sip of water when a group of foreigners approached her. They had crossed each other’s path quite often at the camp. They had learnt that she was starting her expedition the next morning.

One of them said, ‘So you are going to summit Mount Everest?’

‘Yes,’ Poorna smiled.

At the Everest Base Camp Dr. Narendra Patil had tutored them enough to understand and express in English.

‘Oh, that is awesome! I am very proud of you. You have come this far. You can definitely go up there!’

Poorna was thrilled.

‘All the best and bye.’

He walked away.

‘Hey you, Poorna,’ he turned around and called.

‘Don’t forget me once you summit. I am the first one to congratulate you for summiting,’ he blew a kiss in the air.

Sekhar and Poorna laughed. Poorna waved back at him.

‘So, big lady, we are starting tomorrow. Be good. Eat well for heaven’s sake. No throwing up. You know how tough and tricky the climb becomes from ABC. I will have to send you back like last time. Don’t let that happen. You will not get another opportunity,’ Sekhar Babu said.

Poorna giggled.

Inching Toward the Dream

19 May 2014
7.00 am
Everest Base Camp

Poorna checked her rucksack one more time; lest she had forgotten something – flags, spare gloves, socks, fleece jacket, Gortex (windproof jacket), tissue, chocolates, dry fruits and sanitary pads – everything was there. She had had her menstrual period just before reaching the Base Camp. During fitness assessment, the need to use medication to delay her periods until after the expedition was discussed. However, her consulting gynecologist, Dr. Lakshmi, was not in favour of meddling with her health unnecessarily.

‘Nature has to take its own course. Besides, Poorna hardly experiences discomfort during her menstrual cycles. I think she can manage,’ Dr. Lakshmi had said.

‘All set?’ Sekhar Babu called out to Poorna and Anand from outside the tents.

The trio reached the Stupa, (a dome-like structure with a spire, built on a brick base) where the puja was to be performed before their departure. Poorna and her team had attended Lama pujas earlier too. But today, it was Poorna’s puja; she was to offer her worship to the Sagarmaatha seeking her blessings, and beseeching her to remain tranquil and not turn ferocious during her expedition.

Rice and beer were offered to the Dalai Lama (whose picture is worshipped), while a lama chanted prayers. The sherpas joined him in the chanting. The heavy smoke of incense sticks coiled and rose up to the skies. The holy flags atop the stupa fluttered. Birds flocked around the offerings to partake of it.

The lama, who was chanting pointed to a bird that sat atop the stupa and said something.

One of the sherpa’s explained that the bird, a Himalayan Cluff perching atop the Stupa during puja was a good omen.

After the puja, the team headed back to their tents to fetch their rucksacks.

Sekhar Babu sat on the floor outside the tent and said, ‘Let’s meditate to prepare ourselves for the challenges ahead.’

Poorna and Anand joined him.

Poorna closed her eyes. She had been trained in the technique of visualization. She visualized Mount Everest. She visualized the peak. She summited. She stood there at the peak. The cold winds caressed her face. The holy flags fluttered behind her. She came back to meet her parents. She came back as a message to her Swaeroes.

She stayed in that state of tranquility for some time.

The mighty Everest loomed enormously on all sides. Since the weather forecast was favourable, numerous mountaineers were proceeding to the Everest peak. She acclimatized her sensibility to the environment. She allowed her senses to absorb as much of the atmosphere as possible. She took step after step. And with each step, her focus grew narrower and narrower. Finally, her mind shut out every thought. Her focus now was only on the next step. To take as many steps as possible from one mindful moment to another mindful moment. They reached the Intermediate Camp in seven hours. They were solemnly aware that the challenge would begin from this junction onwards.

20 May 2014

They began their journey from Intermediate Camp to the Advance Base Camp. They rested at the Advance Base Camp. Poorna was a little restless. She couldn’t fall asleep easily, despite being exhausted. She stepped out of her tent in the freezing cold. The chill winds howled under the enormous expanse of the star-lit sky. Devoid of the thick layers of pollution and other sources of light, the sky looked magnificent. Poorna had never seen so many stars at once. She identified the Little Bear constellation! She remembered lying down with her father on the navvar bed outside their hut gazing at stars on hot summer nights.

He pointed to the North Star and said, ‘You must always be as steady and constant as the North Star.’

‘What does that mean, Baa? To be constant, to be steady?’

‘The star is fixed. It doesn’t move. In olden day, sailors took help of the Pole Star to navigate in the sea. Just like the North Star, once you set your mind on a goal, you must not waver. You must remain constant. Only then can you achieve what you set out for.’

She gazed at the star for a few minutes.

She remembered Sekhar Babu’s words as he oriented them after the Darjeeling trip:

‘Guys, Praveen Sir is doing something really good for you. This is a great opportunity. If you want to better your lives, and if you want your children to live better than you do, put in all your efforts.’

She folded her hands in prayer.

She bowed down in reverence to her parents. She submitted herself to Sagarmatha. Praveen Kumar’s goal was her sole purpose.

22 May 2014

The next destination was Camp 1. Henceforth, Poorna and Anand would be on their own with the sherpas. Sekhar Babu would not accompany them any further. He is not permitted to.

Just before starting the expedition, Sekhar Babu advised everyone to use the washroom. This is perhaps the last toilet-like facility they would use in a long time. The morning breakfast was also the last freshly-cooked meal they would eat in a while.

Poorna thought: I will miss this luxury.

Using tissues instead of water, eating packaged rotis, and of course the extreme temperature – these were the primary challenges for Poorna and Anand during the expedition. Attending to nature’s calls during the Everest Expedition is not an easy task. Some prefer pee bottles but Poorna managed to attend to them outdoors. Once on the final expedition, the frequency of nature calls reduce due to a decreased rate of metabolism and excessive sweating.

Sekhar Babu held the children’s hands. He looked into their eyes for a few moments and wished them luck.

‘Give it your best shot. If things go bad, just come back. We want you to achieve your goal. We have tried our very best. If at any point, you feel you cannot go on, just let go and come back.’

He embraced them.

‘Everest will always be there baba. This year, next year and the year after. You being with us is more important.’

Poorna listened quietly. Anand chuckled.

‘You are our heroes,’ Sekhar Babu said. ‘Now go, rock it.’

The trek from Advance Base Camp to Camp 1 was steep; so steep that it had earned the sobriquet of ‘wall’.

After half an hour, they reached the Rangbok Glacier. The sherpas directed the children to wear their crampons and harness seats. Crampons were not new for them. They had used them while learning Ice Craft and Snow Craft during the Darjeeling expedition. They had practiced walking with crampons on the frozen river at Base Camp. They were wearing most of the gear and using most of the equipment they had carried. They had worn the helmet for a long time now, and they had begun to use the ice hand axe.

They trekked for half an hour with the help of snow axes and reached the Jumaring point. (Jumar is an ascend device used to climb heights). The word ‘Jumaring’ comes from Jumar. The second climber uses a rope and a ‘Jumar’, (otherwise called ‘Ascender’) to climb up. From this point onwards, the trek was vertical.

After about an hour of climbing, Anand complained of leg pain. Poorna began to throw up. Although she was energetic and lively, the sherpas were concerned. Usually, oxygen is administered after reaching Camp 1, at an altitude of 7,100 meters. However, to avoid Acute Mountain Sickness (AMS), Poorna was administered oxygen at 6,700 meters. Poorna soon regained her agility and resumed the ascent with greater confidence. The sherpas advised her to wear the oxygen mask even while sleeping.

The snowy terrain posed a challenge in itself. The snowy terrain was often interrupted by rocky terrain. Crampons, of course, were meant for trekking in snow. Trekking on rocky surfaces with Crampons was a difficult task. The children didn’t have the liberty to remove crampons as and when necessary.

23 May 2014
Camp 1

Anand woke up to find that his sleeping bag was stuck to the mat below. The mat was placed above the tent layer on the floor. The sleeping bag was placed above the mat. This had happened once at Advance Base Camp too. Poorna yanked off the mat from the tent layer as Anand held up the sleeping bag. They then brushed off all the snow that was stuck to the mat.

Large amounts of snow had collected on the roof of their tents. They helped each other to lift the tent roof from inside so that the snow would slide down the walls.

They drank liquids and started their ascent. Water is very essential to beat AMS. Water increases the efficiency of Red Blood Cells to absorb oxygen while breathing. Else, dehydration leads to fatigue, nausea and headaches.

24 May 2014
Camp 2

Camp 2 is at a height of 7,500 meters. The path from Camp 1 to Camp 2 requires a brief use of the ladder. The ascent gradually turned so steep that they had to use ropes for climbing. All the other camps were visible from Camp 2.

Early in the morning, the team began its journey from Camp 2. Although the weather was not hostile enough to stall their progress, they had to brave extremely strong winds sweeping the mountain terrains at 70-150 km per hour. Ngima Nuru sherpa kept a close watch on Poorna.

Poorna and Anand had barely spoken to each other for several days now. As they tread higher and higher, the body’s capacity to inhale sufficient oxygen began to reduce. Any attempt to speak, after removing the oxygen mask, at best sounded like feeble gasps. Besides, each of them climbed at their own pace, along with their sherpas, resting as and when necessary.

The trek path was rather narrow from this point onwards. At times, there was space enough for only one person to walk and at others, three people could walk.

Anand was trudging behind Poorna on the extremely narrow stretch. He was feeling quite exhausted. Narrow and limited spaces disturbed him. He bore a grudge against such spaces. He remembered that night. He woke up to the loud roar of thunder to find his parents sitting in a corner of the house drenched by the heavy water that leaked through the roof, leaving the only small dry portion of the house to him and his brother. Anand felt angry and helpless. That moment, he resolved to do whatever it takes to change the circumstances of his life, so, his parents could live with dignity. Summiting the Everest is perhaps the first step toward bettering his family’s circumstances; it is perhaps one way of conquering space, the physical space of shelter denied to his family. If he could summit the Everest, then no task was insurmountable. This achievement itself would change his life for the better. He kept pushing himself on the ridge until his legs collapsed.

Anand opened his eyes. He was lying sprawled on the snow-covered ground. He saw a tall man bending over him – probably a Russian, waiting for him to get up and clear the way. It dawned on him that he had fainted. Fortunately, he had fallen forward on the path. Had he fallen off to his right, he would have landed in the base of a deep gorge. Anand hoped the Russian climber would give him a helping hand. But he stood there indifferent. Anand managed to prop himself up. He shot an angry glance at the foreigner and began to walk.

He felt thirsty and tried to open his water bottle. He couldn’t. He removed his heavy-duty glove on his right hand beneath which, were another two layers of gloves. But he didn’t have to remove them. He opened the bottle, drank water, closed the lid and put it back in his bag. He tried wearing his gloves again. But they wouldn’t fit. He tried again. He couldn’t insert his fingers into the gloves. Anand suspected frostbite. He panicked, and his eyes welled up. Tears trickled down but halfway down his cheeks they froze into ice. Crying would only make things worse. He knew that. He would then have to remove his oxygen mask. His breath would leave vapour on the goggles, the vapour would turn into ice, and that would affect his visibility. He would then have to remove his goggles too.

He laughed to himself. Why blame the Russian climber for not helping, when taking care of oneself is the only challenge on the path to Everest?

You are in the Himalayas! Keep moving, just keep moving….

24 May 2014
3.00 pm
Camp 3

The team reached Camp 3. The terrain hereafter was very rocky and excessively exposed to the weather. Since the winds were strong enough to blow off the tents, the sherpas pitched their tents for the night between high rocks.

Anand’s sherpa lit the butane gas stove. He poured some ice into a vessel and placed it on the stove. The ice liquefied and began to boil. He then dipped the packaged food into boiling water. Once the food was heated, they consumed it directly from the packet. Anand and Poorna had opted for flavored rice, such as jeera rice and tomato rice.

Sekhar Babu called over the satellite phone around 5 pm, when Poorna and Anand were resting in their tents. ‘I just received the weather report. I think you should start tonight. Prepare yourselves for a night trek. You will start by 9 pm. Rest until then. And eat well. Poorna, especially you! Make sure you eat enough.’

This came as a surprise to the children who had assumed that they would rest that night. Anand was especially looking forward to the rest as he was feeling exhausted.

‘Sir, ippudaa…(Now?) I cannot Sir…I am too tired.’

Poorna, however, was all geared up. She was prepared for every hardship. Climbing this far, she had learnt that nothing was impossible.

Night trek is recommended in the DEATH ZONE for various reasons. It takes around eight to nine hours to reach the summit from Camp 3, at an altitude of 8,300 metres. The snow turns into solid, compact ice, at night making it easy to walk over it. However, with the rising day temperature, the snow melts and the surface becomes soft. Besides, a night trek saves the oxygen consumed during sleep and extends it for another eight hours in the DEATH ZONE, where one can barely survive without oxygen. Climbers spend minimum time in the DEATH ZONE to minimize chances of mishaps. Since a night trek ensures that a climber summits in the early hours of the morning, the climber has enough time to reach the safe zone before the end of day and it is easy to descend on snow than on ice and daylight is a big advantage.

The children were about to enter the DEATH ZONE – the distance between Camp 3 and the Summit of the Everest. There are only fourteen DEATH ZONES in the whole world. Chances of survival are minimal in this extreme climate as the layer of oxygen is very thin. A simple misstep or dysfunction of the oxygen tank can be fatal. Many a time, deaths occur after summiting and while descending, only because the oxygen in the cylinder is completely spent.

The sherpas place a few cylinders above Camp 3 as well for the return journey.

Sekhar Babu called Praveen Kumar just before the children were to enter the DEATH ZONE.

‘Sir, hereafter, I will have no communication with Poorna and Anand. They are heading into the DEATH ZONE. If everything goes well, they will summit by the early hours of tomorrow. I will call you in the morning.’

24 May 2014
9.30 pm

Poorna secured a headlamp to her helmet. Her companions sherpa Ngima Nuru and Gyansto guided the way. The night was quiet. The ice peaks nose above them occasionally. The only sound was the gasp of inhaling and exhaling. With every breath Poorna strengthened her will to succeed and survive.

Poorna chanted, ‘Jai Hanuman’ and rendered the Ten Commandments, alternately.

One step at a time. One step up. One step higher. One step closer to the Summit.

One step for adventure. One step for endurance.

One step for confidence.

One step toward liberation.

Poorna kept moving.

The path from Camp 3 to Mount Everest is divided into three steps. Each step has a different gradient and topography. To reach the first step, they had to use the rope. A steep rock covered in snow stood intimidating in front of her. This was once again a vertical ascent.

That night for the first time, Poorna understood the importance of the rigorous training they had undergone for so many months. She saluted Sekhar Babu and Parmesh in her mind.

The blustery wind made strange noises as it gushed forward and found its way between the undulating peaks. Although well secured with ropes, the force of the wind was strong enough to hurl a climber to the other end of the peak. If he is not firmly grounded, he can end up anywhere between glaciers and crevices. Poorna squatted for a couple of minutes to rest but held on tightly to the rope, firmly thrusting her legs against the peak to prevent the winds from sweeping her away. She started her ascent once again.

She remembered her father, who used to ride his bycycle to Kondapur every day, almost 10 kilometers away. The terrain was rocky and hilly. Devidas had to cross a few hillocks to reach Kondapur. The road was not tarred, and the ride was bumpy and back breaking. How did he manage? She wondered.

It’s his genes that I have inherited, after all. And, of course, the training, practice, nutrition and determination.

As she climbed higher and higher, she began to feel a little dizzy. She had experienced dizziness in Ladakh too. A sudden increase in height makes her dizzy. She didn’t tell the sherpas, lest they ask her to return. She continued despite the mild dizziness. The only thought that enveloped her mind was to take the next step. She was not willing to stop at any cost.

The dizziness increased, and her head started to spin. She couldn’t push herself any further. Dark spots and flashes floated before her eyes. She was barely able to see anything. Finally, she said, ‘Let us sit for a while, I am a bit tired.’

Where was the place to sit and rest? They were crossing a ridge, and the path was so narrow they could barely walk.

‘Five more minutes,’ Gyansto sherpa said.

She managed to walk, dragging her feet and praying for strength. They reached a place where there was space enough to sit down. Poorna sat down, exhausted. The sherpa checked her oxygen cylinder. To his shock, it was completely empty! He changed the oxygen tank. Instantly, Poorna felt better. He wondered how she had walked this long without oxygen. What if she had passed out on her way!

Oxygen depletion is a major reason for death on Mount Everest.

Poorna stretched her body and arched her back. The dark blanket above with randomly sprinkled dense glitter was mesmerizing. She remembered Praveen Kumar saying, ‘Reach out to the stars…’ She said that aloud and raised one hand as if to pluck one of them. They seemed so near.

What if these stars are flowers and the Mount Everest, a tree! She wondered.

After a few minutes of rest, they continued their ascent. The second step was more challenging. She used the ladder to cross two deep crevices. Crossing a crevice, often thousands of feet deep, was indeed a dreadful experience even for experienced trekkers. Taking step after step on the rungs of the ladder with only a measly rope for support can be quite unnerving. A strong gust of wind can disturb the balance and lead to a fatal fall.

The first crevice was 10 feet long. It was not easy crossing the crevice with crampons fastened to the shoes. The next crevice was about 10,000 feet deep. The ladder lay stretched for 30 feet at an angle of 60 degrees!

She reached the third step, which was very easy compared to the first two. Yet, she couldn’t let her guard down for even a split-second. After the third step, there is a traverse, where climbers going up toward the north have to take a left turn, toward the Pyramid, which is just a few hundred meters from the Summit. The path is a roundabout the highest wall. The roundabout-ridge has a wall on one side and nothing on the other side. A misstep can take her to the unknown lands of the void. Like a lizard, she pressed herself against the wall taking small steps to cross the round-about ridge.

Poorna reached the Summit Pyramid. She was just 500 meters away from the Summit point.

‘How long?’ she kept asking her sherpa every two minutes.

‘Almost there,’ he kept saying.

She trudged uphill climbing rocks with thirty to seventy-degree gradient. Poorna began to chant, ‘Jai Hanuman!’ With each utterance, she harnessed her strength from deep within. She was just a few feet away from the Summit.

Humbled by the Himalayas

24 May 2014

On the outskirts of Hyderabad the summer evening was still bright. Praveen Kumar was heading back to Hyderabad city after meetings at Piduguralla and Kandukuru. The roads were lined with pink flags. Although not officially declared, Telangana was soon going to be a separate State. The government and bureaucracy were making every effort to make the bifurcation of the State of Andhra Pradesh into Andhra Pradesh and Telangana as smooth as possible. The media was ablaze with news, reports, debates and discussions. In the midst of this political melee, news of the Himalayan Expedition of two Swaeroes has taken a back seat. Except for E TV 2, no other television channel covered the Expedition.

Praveen had had many sleepless nights ever since the news of the avalanche that took a toll of several sherpas. He was tempted to abort the expedition and recall the children. However, calling them back out of fear would not only kill the aspirations of these two children but of so many other Swaeroes who were keenly following this expedition and awaiting the successful return of their icons.

Praveen had been extremely restless ever since the children embarked on the last leg of their journey to the Summit. He knew that Poorna and Anand would have to summit before 11.00 am tomorrow for their safe return.

That night, Praveen lay awake tossing and turning in his bed. His wife, Lakshmi Bai sat up reading late into the night.

She looked up from her book, ‘Shouldn’t you get some sleep?’

‘Well. I’m not able to. Why are you sitting up?’

‘I can’t seem to sleep either.’

She resumed reading.

After some time, she placed the book away and said, ‘I hope they come back safe.’

‘Of course, they will,’ he smiled at her.

‘Heard from Sekhar yet?’

‘Not until morning. They are now in the DEATH ZONE covering 8,400 meters.’

‘The DEATH ZONE. My goodness!’ She took a deep breath. ‘Praveen, I have this feeling … it’s all going to go very well. You have wished the best for your society. This task will be accomplished,’ she said with conviction. ‘And you are a policeman, Praveen. Be brave.’

Their eyes met. They were assuring each other and seeking assurance at the same time.

He tried to sleep.

What if the children don’t make it back? What if something happens to them? Will the idea of Swaeroes survive? Will the Ten Commandments be proven wrong?

These thoughts were swirling in his head, relentlessly. He couldn’t shake his mind off them. He would barely sleep for half an hour, and he would wake up, his mouth dry. He would sip some water and try to calm his mind. He had never been this desperate to see the light of day. Each time he woke up, he looked at the time on his mobile and for a message or call from Sekhar Babu, knowing very well that he will not hear from him until dawn.

25 May 2014
5.45 am

Poorna had barely taken a few steps. She stopped suddenly with her eyes transfixed on the ground. It took her a couple of seconds to figure out that what lay half covered in snow was not a rock surface, but a body; the corpse of an ill-fated mountaineer. The body was dressed exactly like her: the same kind of mountaineering gear, oxygen tank, shoes and crampons. The now icy hand held an ice axe exactly like the one she held. A chill ran down her spine. Her legs shivered. This man or woman must have come here with dreams. But the mighty Himalayas had taken the climber’s breath away!

She wondered how many bodies she had passed by until now. She must have even walked over a few!!

Human life can be the most precious or the most worthless. The line is so thin! As thin as air!

She would have ended up a mere worthless body buried somewhere, unknown, on the mighty Himalayas, had her sherpa not swapped her empty oxygen tank.

Dawn was breaking. The veil of darkness was slipping even as the undulating snowcapped peaks began to emerge in a golden hue.

Poorna stood still on the peak of Mount Everest. The camps and paths that she had crossed to reach there lay beneath her. The colourful triangular prayer flags strung together hung here and there; a few lines of flags, whose thread had snapped, lay on the ground. On the other side, the entire length of Mount Everest lay completely exposed. She felt like she was an eagle hovering above an eternal bed of clouds.

The temperature on Everest was between -40 and -45°c. Chilly winds were slapping against her face. She stayed motionless for some time. The thumping of the heart was the only human experience she discerned at this moment. All else was elemental – the howling wind, the panorama of undulating snow-covered peaks, the sky above.

The sun rose to full glory, bathing the enormous expanse of the mountains in a golden hue. This was indeed the most surreal experience she had ever had; and probably, she would ever have in this life time. She felt overwhelmed. Her soul thirsted to soak in as much as was possible. She felt that she had finally seen the Ultimate. The experience of God is what you choose to make out of it. This is her personal experience of God. It was her ultimate truth, and she had realized it. She closed her eyes and bowed her head. She felt humbled by the colossal beauty of nature. For a moment, time and space ceased to exist. She was one with time and space! One with everything and with nothing! All dualities merged. Ceased to exist.

She sought to orient herself. Her tiny mind tried to encapsulate the enormity of the mountain, but in vain. All that was palpable to her were the moments she had spent since she left the Advance Base Camp and every step she had taken forward. This night that she had spent transcending the DEATH ZONE seemed like much, much longer than it had been.

Poorna sat on a small rock on the Everest, having spent every ounce of energy.

One of Poorna’s sherpa, removed a T-shirt from his rucksack and gave it to her. Poorna read the words printed right across the shirt: I AM THE YOUNGEST GIRL TO CLIMB MOUNT EVEREST. She flashed a big smile. Gyansto sherpa and Ngima sherpa gestured a thumbs-up and smiled broadly. She looked into their small eyes, deep set amidst folds of weathered skin – her sole companions, here on the Everest, to share her joy and pride.

Gyansto helped her wear the shirt. He took a few pictures of her. The sherpas left her alone to savour those moments; moments of a life-time. She noticed the s herpas closing their eyes for a few moments.

Seventeen ascents! she thought.

Poorna pulled out a few flags from her bag. She hoisted the Indian flag and then the Telangana State flag. Little did she know then that she would go down in history as the first to hoist the Telangana State flag, even before the official formation of the State and that too on the highest peak in the world!

Poorna next hoisted flags bearing the pictures of S.R. Sankaran and B.R. Ambedkar. And finally, the Swaeroes flag. She was a very proud Swaeroe at that moment. She remembered Praveen Kumar with pride and respect. She saluted Sekhar Babu and Parmesh, her gurus. Her eyes moistened when her parents flashed in her mind. Can a child ever thank her parents enough??

A few mountaineers from the Chinese Mountaineering Federation, who had arrived at the Summit after officially opening the route to Everest from China approached Poorna and said, ‘Congratulations! You are the first to set foot on Everest this year after the routes were opened.’

Those words went over Poorna’s head. She really could not comprehend the enormous import of the words as she stood against the expansive spread of earth’s curvature. She had just accomplished several firsts to her credit; she was the youngest girl in the world to summit the Everest ever; first to hoist the Telangana State Flag; and, first to summit that year. All at the tender age of thirteen!

Another of them shook hands with her and said, ‘Aww, that’s a great grip! You have strong arms, young lady.’

Poorna’s sherpa indicated to Poorna that they should start descent. A mountaineer is not allowed to stay for more than 15 minutes at the peak. If the traffic picks up descent can become delayed and difficult.

She picked up a small stone from the ground. She would treasure it forever. A memento of the most profound life experience! A trophy, she gave herself! She turned around and walked toward her sherpa, who was waiting patiently for her.

25 May 2014
7.00 am
Residence of Praveen Kumar, IPS

Praveen woke up with a start. He could hear his heart thumping in his ears. He had broken into a cold sweat. He felt he had committed a sin falling asleep that night! In fact, he had slept just before the break of dawn when the early birds had begun their symphony. In want of fresh air, he stepped out into the lawn of his residential quarters with a cup of steaming hot coffee. The phone rang in his pocket.

Sekhar Babu!

‘Hello.’

‘Hello, Sir,’ Sekhar Babu said.

Praveen sensed that Sekhar had turned the speaker mode on. He could hear the radio on full volume. He heard a lot of conversation in the Nepali language.

Praveen became impatient. ‘Sekhar, just tell me. How are the children?’

‘Sir, please listen to this.’ Sekhar again placed the phone close to the radio.

Praveen was exasperated. ‘Why can’t you just tell me??!!’

‘Congratulations, Sir,’ Sekhar said. ‘Poorna and Anand have summited. Poorna is now a world record holder. She is the youngest girl to scale Mount Everest. The children are on their way back.’

Praveen went blank. The world around him froze for a while. He found himself a chair and collapsed in it. He barely moved for a few moments. Then he closed his eyes. What a relief! After a minute, he took the phone and typed out a message:

Poorna and Anand have summited Mount Everest. Poorna has made a world record. She is the youngest girl to climb Mount Everest.

He sent the message to Raymond Peter and Shamsher Singh Rawat. He sat back in his chair.

He took a deep breath.

Ever since the children got approval for the Himalayan Expedition, he was on tenterhooks. He had been plagued by guilt.

Had he put their lives at stake to fulfill some idealism of his own? How would he live the rest of his life if something were to happen to the children? What would he tell their parents?

He had endured an excruciating moral, ethical turmoil.

He looked up.

‘The sky is our limit, Swaeroes!’

The descent, in comparison to ascent, was very easy. But Poorna’s sherpa, Ngima Nuru was very careful. Complacence and negligence during descent have resulted in many a death. Besides the centre of gravity of the body shifts making descent difficult.

She passed by five more corpses.

Why do we end up seeing things we don’t want to? The more you resist, the more it persists.

The traffic on this route increased as the Nepal routes were closed following the avalanche.

Poorna met Anand on her way back.

‘Do you want to go to the Summit again? Come on. Let’s do it together.’

Poorna was too tired.

She handed over all the flags to him.

She thought she would warn him about the corpses. She decided not to.

Anand summited around 6.45 am.

He recorded his message to Praveen Kumar through Go-pro.

‘Praveen Sir, we, your Swereaos, have done it. We have achieved this. Jai Bheem,’ he gasped for oxygen.

Poorna called Praveen Kumar from the satellite phone even before she reached Camp 3.

‘Sir, we did it. It was very tough, Sir. Very, very tough, but we succeeded.’

Praveen just listened.

Neither of them could say more.

Sekhar Babu informed Praveen Kumar that he would bring the children back to Advance Base Camp the same day since the weather forecast predicted snow fall with chances of an avalanche the next day.

The descent to Advance Base Camp from Camp 1 was quite enjoyable. They slid down the ice effortlessly. But they had to be careful with the carabiner. Poorna ensured her carabiner was attached to the rope. She attached the rope to the other side of the Jumar. Now the ascender turns into a descender. She kept moving, attaching, detaching and reattaching her descender to the ropes that were fixed along the route. Her s herpas, confident of her skills let her descend independently and at her own pace. Snowfall obstructed her vision. She removed her goggles and forgot to wear them back in her eagerness to reach ABC. The snow hit directly into her eyes. The sharp ice particles hurt her eyes.

They reached Advance Base Camp by evening. Poorna’s eyes had turned bloody red and burned as if set on fire. The doctor at ABC examined her and found her to be fit. He prescribed eye drops.

She rested well that night. The redness in the eyes had decreased.

The same evening, a snowstorm with strong winds hit the ABC area. Visibility was limited to just four feet. The whole atmosphere was enveloped in a blanket of thick white fog. The first thought on Poorna’s mind was the plight of those still at Camp 2 and 3. She prayed for their well-being. There was some anxiety in Camp 3 as three climbers were found missing. Fortunately, they reached ABC, after trudging along in knee-deep snow.

Poorna got her periods. She remembered, ‘Mind over matter.’

Just before retiring for the night, Sekhar Babu said, ‘Poorna, you now hold the world record for being the youngest girl to summit Mount Everest!’

‘Ah!’ she gasped. ‘Yes. My sherpa told me.’

‘Poorna, you are also the first climber to set foot on Mount Everest for this year.’

Anand held Poorna by the shoulder affectionately.

‘Chinna, there’s one more achievement to your credit. You hoisted the Telangana flag for the first time. And where!! ON Mount Everest!’ he beamed.

‘You hoisted the Telangana Flag even before the State is officially formed,’ he laughed, ‘How do you like it?’

‘Arey yaar, she is too young to understand all of this,’ said Sekhar Babu.

‘You are so naïve Poorna. You don’t know that you have achieved an incredible feat! Your innocence and humility.....,’ said Sekhar Babu.

Your innocence and humility Poorna, is what makes your achievement all the more priceless!

1 June 2014

Delhi was wilting under the sweltering summer heat. K. F. Reddy, the Senior Consultant of Social Welfare Schools flew to Kathmandu to receive Anand and Poorna. He trained the children to face interviews and handle press meets. Later, Sharma, the Academic Coordinator of Social Welfare Schools, also flew to Delhi to make arrangements and to help the children in their interaction with the media.

The children took two days to transition from subzero temperatures to extreme heat. They stayed at Andhra Pradesh Bhavan in New Delhi. After four days, the children met Prime Minister Narendra Modi who congratulated them. He expressed his happiness on Poorna’s achievement as a realization of his ‘Beti bachaavo, beti Padaavo’ (Save the girl child, Educate the girl child) campaign.

The media at Andhra Pradesh Bhavan recorded bytes from the children regarding their success.

6 June 2014
Rajiv Gandhi International Airport, Hyderabad

Poorna, Anand and Sekhar Babu walked swiftly toward the private lounge of the airport. Poorna spotted her parents. A month ago, she wasn’t sure she would live to see them. She waved at them shyly.

She ran up to them, held their hands and said, ‘ Yadi, Ba - I told you I would be back. Look, now I am back. For real.’

Tears rolled down Lakshmi’s face. Anand’s mother Lakshmi too shed tears of happiness. It was only after all the media attention and appreciation and congratulations pouring in from all quarters of the country and abroad, that the parents actually began to understand the gravity of the adventure their children had undertaken and the enormity of the success they had achieved.

Praveen Kumar stood with his arms folded. Without batting an eyelid, he watched the two Swaeroes walk up to him.

‘Congratulations,’ he said. He held their hands in a tight warm clasp. He hugged them both.

‘Congratulations,’ he said one more time. ‘You did it.’ You have made us proud.

Poorna said, ‘Thank you.’

How could she tell him that she thought of him at every step up in the DEATH ZONE? That it was his faith in her that ran through her body as pulsating energy? That it was him that she thanked when she was at the top of the world?

Poorna stepped out of the Airport lounge. She was overwhelmed when she saw her principal, teachers and friends who had assembled to greet her.

Poorna’s eyes darted from face to face. She searched for a particular face in the crowd. Her eyes suddenly lit up. She ducked down and disappeared for a few seconds. She found her way through the crowd. like a rabbit scurrying through the bushes. She sprung up before Swapna, her PET teacher from Tadwai.

‘Swapna Madam!!!’

Swapna was taken aback. The next second, she smiled from ear to ear and hugged Poorna. Poorna hugged her right back. Tears rolled over Swapna’s face.

Poorna whispered, ‘Thank you,’ in her ears, and headed toward Parmesh- the first two people who showed her that a path such as this existed.

Poorna and Anand interacted with media persons. A rally was also organized from Shamshabad airport to Charminar. Thousands of students from all the Social Welfare Residential Schools and hundreds of alumni joined. Social activists, social workers, educationists, sports persons, journalists also joined the rally in celebration of an achievement which transcended the narrow confines of age, religion, caste and class. The rally continued for hours with people on bikes, in cars, jeeps and lorries joining in.

‘Look at that, Poorna,’ Anand whispered pointing to the sea of people following them.

‘You are a star, Poorna. You are an inspiration. You have created history.’

For the first time, it sunk into Poorna that her achievement was indeed great! On the peak, she remembered having bowed down to the entire human race. And now once again she felt overwhelmed. Her achievement was a result of blessings from each one of them.

Praveen observed Poorna from a distance. She was a lot more confident now. However, her eyes were still humble and unpretentious. She sure knew how to handle this sudden fame and attention. She has her head fixed firmly on her shoulders.

POORNA.

The Complete One.

For Poorna and her ilk, the journey of the conquest of the real world has begun.

THE END

Beyond Everest

Poorna summited Mount Everest, the world’s highest peak (8,843 meters) on 25th May 2014. She set the world record of being the youngest girl (13 years and 11 months) in the world to summit Mount Everest.

Poorna did not stop with the Everest. She aimed for the seven summits across the seven continents in the world. She summited Kilimanjaro (5,895 meters) in Africa in 2016, Mount Elbrus (5,642 meters) in Europe in 2017, Carstensz Pyramid (4,884 meters) in Ocenia region in March 2019 and Aconcagua (6,961 meters) in South America in April 2019. Now, her aim is to conquer Denali (6,190 meters) in North America and Vinson Massif (4,892 meters) in Antarctica.

In the meanwhile, Anand scaled Kilimanjaro (5,895 meters) and Mount Kosciuszko (2,228 meters) in Australia. He is today a certified skiing coach from the Atal Bihari Vajpayee Institute of Mountaineering and Allied Sports, Manali. He aspires to become an international trainer in mountaineering.

Awards and Recognitions

* Received the ‘Prime Minister’s Excellence Award’ in 2014 and ‘Amazing Indians’ award in 2015, from Sri Narendra Modi, the honorable Prime Minister of India.

* Received the ‘Presidential Excellence Award’ in 2017 from Sri Pranab Mukherjee, the honorable President of India.

* Represented Telangana state from India in the UN Sustainable Development Summit - 2015 held in New York. Poorna boarded a Metro for the first time in New York city.

* Met the Honorable Chief Minister K Chandrashekar Rao. He declared a grant of five acres of land in Indalwai, Nizamabad district and R 25 lakhs each to Poorna and Anand and a three-bedroom house in Kamareddy. The MLA of Nizamabad district awarded another 1 lakh rupees as a reward for her Everest summit.

* After her successful ascent of the Everest, Poorna’s name was printed on all the Indigo carrier luggage for a whole week in the entire country. All air hostesses of the carrier wore badges etched with the words, ‘I am Poorna.’ The aircraft was painted blue. Poorna’s name was painted on it.

* In 2017, Bollywood Actor-Director, Rahul Bose released a mainstream movie called ‘Poorna’. Poorna and Praveen Kumar watched the movie along with Pranab Mukharjee, the then President of India.

* Named a Paul Harris Fellow by the Rotary Foundation of Rotary International in appreciation of tangible and significant assistance given for the furtherance of better understanding and friendly relations among peoples of the world.

* Invited as Chief Guest for All India Police Sports Meet of the Border Security Force in 2016.

* Received the TiE-ASPIRE Young Achiever Award, 2014 from ASPIRE Grow More in appreciation of her unrivaled contribution as a role model to the youth of India.

* Won the Pogo Amazing Kids Award, 2014 from POGO channel.

* Awarded the Sakshi Excellence award from Sakshi TV Channel in 2015.

* Awarded the APSARA Award from Zee Telugu in 2018.

* Awarded one lakh rupees by TV 9 channel for her ‘enduring will’ to climb Mount Everest.

* Conferred the Vasundhara Award on Women’s Day in 2019 E TV channel.

Postscript

Poorna’s family hardly comprehend the magnitude of Poorna’s achievements. They just wanted their daughter to come back home safe. A victory would be a bonus. Neither her parents nor her brother Naresh had any inkling of what Poorna had achieved and the dangers that were lurking along the path of her journey.

When Poorna called home from Camp 3, her father received the call, and her mother was not even around. Devidas was only relieved to know that his daughter was on her way back after summiting. That afternoon, their neighbors rushed in to tell them that Poorna was on TV talking about her summit to Mount Everest. In an hour, the media swarmed her village.

The villagers thought that the mountain may at the most be a little more higher than the guttas (hillocks), that they trekked as a routine. It was no big deal for them.

However, after watching repeated telecasts of Poorna’s feat and after seeing visuals of the Everest, they, for the first time began to understand the concept of snow mountains and extreme climatic conditions. But even that did not fascinate the villagers for a long time. For them, Poorna was their Poorna, the girl who belonged to Pakala village, their village.

Rollout at the Social Welfare Residential Schools after Poorna’s Accomplishment

Poorna’s achievement is indeed a testimony of the efforts to revamp the Social Welfare Department policies and principles. With the formation of the Telangana State and Poorna’s achievement, the Social Welfare Residential Schools came under the spotlight. In Telangana, 134 new institutions were added to the existing 134 institutions. The strength of the students in the academic year 2011–12 was 65, 525. By 2018–19 it increased to 1, 49, 680.

Poorna’s success played a significant role in changing the perspectives of all the stakeholders of Social Welfare Schools, including teachers, parents, the government of Telangana and the society at large. The otherwise rigid and rudimentary system marched toward holistic learning without compromising the quality of education.

Previously, providing basic amenities was a challenge. Today, 27 Center for Excellence colleges have been instituted to offer preparatory courses for children aspiring to join professional courses. A special defense training college for women, a Sainik school (to train children aspiring to join the National Defense Academy) and a school of fine arts have been established.

Social Welfare Schools, which were sought only by the poorest strata of the society, are now competing with concept schools for admissions. Parents from the middle class are looking at Social Welfare Schools as a viable option for their children, because of the high standards of education and facilities, for a modest fee.